<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Battering rams against Rome; or, The battel of John the follower of the lamb, fought with the pope and his priests, whilst he was a prisoner in the inquisition-prison of Rome. Also, a certain remonstrance of righteous reason, written in Rome-prison of mad-men, unto all Rome's rulers. Together with a post-script, to all tender-hearted Roman Catholicks.</title>
            <title>Battering rams against Rome.</title>
            <author>J. P. ((John Perrot)), d. 1671?.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 229 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54424</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1612</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217527</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829189</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829189</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33625</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54424)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33625)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ;  1975:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Battering rams against Rome; or, The battel of John the follower of the lamb, fought with the pope and his priests, whilst he was a prisoner in the inquisition-prison of Rome. Also, a certain remonstrance of righteous reason, written in Rome-prison of mad-men, unto all Rome's rulers. Together with a post-script, to all tender-hearted Roman Catholicks.</title>
                  <title>Battering rams against Rome.</title>
                  <author>J. P. ((John Perrot)), d. 1671?.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 148 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Robert Wilson, at the sign of the Black-Spread-Eagle and Wind-mil, in Martins Le Grand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the tender, moderate, Roman-Catholick Reader" is signed: John Perrot.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Lambeth Palace Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>J. P. --  ((John Perrot)), d. 1671? --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Rome (Italy) --  History --  1420-1798 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33625:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33625:1"/>
            <p>Battering Rams AGAINST ROME; OR, The BATTEL of <hi>JOHN,</hi> the Follower of the LAMB, Fought with the <hi>POPE</hi> and his <hi>Prieſts,</hi> whilſt he was a Priſoner in the <hi>Inquiſition-Priſon</hi> of <hi>ROME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO, A Certain <hi>REMONSTRANCE</hi> of <hi>Righteous Reaſon,</hi> written in <hi>Rome</hi>-Priſon of Mad-men, unto all <hi>Rome's</hi> Rulers.</p>
            <p>Together with a <hi>POST-SCRIPT,</hi> to all tender-hearted <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Black-Spread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Wind-mil,</hi> in <hi>Martins Le Grand,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_moderate_Papist_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33625:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33625:2"/>
            <head>To the tender, moderate, <hi>Roman-Catholick Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe following Writings, being ſuch as have been diſpenſed in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> unto which Anſwers were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by me, from them, whom it chiefly concerned; but not receiving any (unto any of my Queries pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to <hi>Pope, Prieſts,</hi> &amp;c. in <hi>Rome</hi>) even unto this day; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now returned unto this Land of <hi>England,</hi> may expect ſomething of Anſwer from thee unto the ſaid <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogations,</hi> which are of general concernment unto all <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks;</hi> or elſe, I may conclude that Truth is in no wiſe on your ſide, but abſolutely and undeniably againſt
<pb facs="tcp:33625:3"/>
you, which I therefore leave unto thy conſideration: and if [from that which followeth] thou ſhalt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the Truth which is held forth therein, confeſſing it in ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſimplicity of heart and mind; if afterwards thou deſireſt to be further ſatisfied touching <hi>any</hi> thing of our <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Practices,</hi> ask it in the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Moderation</hi> either by <hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Writing</hi> of me, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Light of the Knowledge of GOD given unto me, I may <hi>meekly anſwer thee</hi> in the <hi>tenderneſſe</hi> of my Soul; Who am a real, faithful and true lover of all Souls,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Called, <hi>John Perrott.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33625:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have found it expedient, for the ſatisfaction of many <hi>tender Deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> to intimate theſe few preceding Words to the following Tract; ſhewing the <hi>certainty</hi> of the <hi>thing</hi> which many have enquired after; yet not as if the relation thereof were able to enduce any Souls to <hi>believe</hi> in the True GOD, foraſmuch as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>If they will not believe</hi> Moſes <hi>and the</hi> Prophets, <hi>neither would they believe if one ſhould come from the dead.</hi> Yet every Work of the Lord God to me is of exceeding weight, eſpecially ſuch, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the life and ſafety of my outward man was very much concerned, in the time of my Pilgrimage in Forreign Parts and Countries.</p>
            <p>In brief, I give this <hi>Relation</hi> (to wit)
<pb facs="tcp:33625:4"/>
When I was in <hi>Legorn</hi> in my Travel onwards to <hi>Turky,</hi> on a certain night an <hi>Angel</hi> of the LORD <hi>awakened</hi> me out of my ſleep, ſaying, <hi>Ariſe and go to the Window:</hi> the which I did in very much <hi>dread</hi> and <hi>trembling;</hi> where ſtanding, I ſuddenly heard cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> in another Room at a Neighbour's houſe, wickedly <hi>conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> my hurt: but bleſſed be God (who ſent his Meſſenger to warn me) by the Power of his own Life <hi>delivered</hi> and <hi>ſaved</hi> me, from the Evil of the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy.</p>
            <p>Moreover, In <hi>Greece</hi> I met with divers <hi>difficulties,</hi> being in my Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage led through many <hi>Tryals</hi> and <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> by being brought before <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> and ſometimes deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of any thing to purchaſe <hi>natural food:</hi> yet ſtill the preſence of the Lord was with me both by Sea and Land, and in the <hi>greateſt ſtraits</hi> he alwayes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the <hi>greateſt power of Love,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33625:4"/>
caring and providing for me, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all that my heart could ever think; which things to mention at large, would fill up much Paper: And therefore in this compendious Preface may only hint one paſſage more, of the powerful Arm of God, battelling for mine Innocent Soul in a Righteous Cauſe; which the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> were well informed of before I arrived at <hi>Rome,</hi> and that by divers hands from <hi>Venice,</hi> by which they might at leaſt-wiſe underſtand, That God was my God, and that I was his faithfull Servant in the Work that he had called me unto.</p>
            <p>It came to paſs in proceed of my <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage,</hi> as I was returning by Sea from <hi>Smyrna</hi> to <hi>Venice,</hi> that upon the way near unto <hi>Corfu,</hi> the Sea-men and Captain of the Ship took a wrongful oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of Anger and Wrath againſt me, at which time I offered my ſelf in much meekneſſe and moderation to reaſon the matter with the ſaid <hi>Commander</hi> of the
<pb facs="tcp:33625:5"/>
Ship; but in brief, he threatned to caſt me on ſhore on a certain <hi>barren Iſland,</hi> on which there was <hi>no Inhabitant;</hi> who when he ſaw that I was in that <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented</hi> (being wholly offered unto God in all place and time) deſiſted that <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt;</hi> but forthwith bound himſelf under an <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Curſe,</hi> that when I came to <hi>Venice</hi> he would have me <hi>burnt to death</hi> by <hi>fire;</hi> To whom I replyed, ſaying, <hi>I fear not man, whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, but the God of life, who was my Leader in all that he had called me unto:</hi> This being at even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſuddenly after theſe <hi>paſſages</hi> there was a <hi>ceſſation</hi> of many of his <hi>words</hi> of <hi>bitterneſs,</hi> though ſome there were that grinned their teeth upon me, and could even have found in their hearts to have bitten off my fleſh from my bones; which kindled the <hi>Anger</hi> of the <hi>LORD GOD Almighty</hi> againſt them; for all that Night his <hi>ſore Indignation</hi> and <hi>Vengeance</hi> did burn as a <hi>flame</hi> in his
<pb facs="tcp:33625:5"/>
               <hi>boſom;</hi> ſo that it came to paſs, at the <hi>dawning</hi> of the <hi>next day,</hi> that he caſt down <hi>a ball of Fire</hi> betwixt the <hi>Decks,</hi> amongſt <hi>divers Paſſengers,</hi> which brake as into the <hi>roaring</hi> of a <hi>Cannon</hi> amongſt them, and <hi>ſlew two perſons,</hi> and wounded <hi>one more;</hi> and beſides that, the Lord cauſed <hi>Fire</hi> to <hi>Rain down</hi> from <hi>Heaven</hi> in <hi>coals</hi> upon them, which <hi>burned ſome</hi> in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, others it <hi>ſmote</hi> and <hi>wounded,</hi> and others it <hi>ſlew</hi> in the Ship. And this is the <hi>Account</hi> of the <hi>ſlain,</hi> viz. An <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> the Gunner, a <hi>Dutch-man</hi> the Carpenter, and an <hi>Italian</hi> a Marriner, an <hi>Armenian</hi> Merchant, and a <hi>Turk</hi> a Servant; which were <hi>five</hi> of <hi>five ſeveral Nations;</hi> and <hi>five</hi> others <hi>wounded,</hi> which the Lord God Almighty gave as <hi>Examples</hi> of his <hi>Wrath,</hi> that the reſt that lived might <hi>fear</hi> his <hi>dreadful</hi> and <hi>terrible Name.</hi> Moreover, the ſaid <hi>coals</hi> of <hi>Fire</hi> burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many holes through <hi>their Sails,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:33625:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>ſplit</hi> their <hi>Main-Top-Maſt</hi> in the <hi>Put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tox,</hi> and then grievous was the cry of all Fleſh amongſt them: And from thence their perverſe Spirits were much more moderated, to hear me in cauſes of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Truth.</p>
            <p>Many things more I might mention, of the wonderful Works of my God, whom my ſimple ſoul ſerves, even in the integrity and uprightneſs of my whole Heart. But in theſe things I ceaſe at this inſtant, having hinted ſome things of other Paſſages in other Writings, and therefore at the preſent do draw to the putting in order the following Writings, which were diſpenſed by me in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition-Priſon at <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33625:6"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle general to the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>GOD,</hi> who at ſundry times, and in divers manners, in the dayes of old, ſpake by the mouth of his <hi>holy Prophets,</hi> hath <hi>now</hi> in theſe latter dayes ſpoken unto us by the Revelation of <hi>his Son,</hi> the <hi>LORD</hi> from <hi>Heaven;</hi> who in the fulneſs of the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of time, came a <hi>Light</hi> into the world to be the <hi>manifest Salvation</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> unto the ends of the Earth; as was ſpoken by the Word unto <hi>Iſaiah</hi> his Prophet, in whoſe face <hi>expreſly</hi> we have the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Father,</hi> in whom we behold the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Son,</hi> as the <hi>Glory</hi> of the only <hi>begotton</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> full of <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> hereby knowing what we <hi>Worſhip,</hi> whom the whole world <hi>alienated</hi> from the <hi>Power, Life, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> do ignorantly <hi>Worſhip</hi> in the imaginations of their own hearts, which before the Lord are only <hi>evil</hi> continually; <hi>Him</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore declare I unto you, <hi>GOD,</hi> the <hi>Eternal</hi> (and unto every mortal) <hi>Inviſible,</hi> and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33625:7"/>
               <hi>Incomprehenſible Spirit,</hi> who is not likened unto the <hi>Creation,</hi> which by the <hi>Power</hi> of his <hi>Eternal Word</hi> was made to <hi>glorifie</hi> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Name,</hi> by the <hi>Spirit;</hi> ſheweth, <hi>That he dwelleth not in Temples made with hands, neither is he worſhipped by the Works of mens hands, as if he needed any thing;</hi> who from the <hi>beginning</hi> determined the <hi>times</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and made <hi>all mankind</hi> of one <hi>mould,</hi> and gave unto them <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Breath,</hi> and added thereunto of the <hi>Grace</hi> of his <hi>Mercy,</hi> a meaſure of the <hi>Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> if haply that thereby they might <hi>ſeek</hi> and <hi>feel</hi> after him, the <hi>LORD</hi> their <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor:</hi> But <hi>Man,</hi> whom the <hi>LORD</hi> made little lower than the <hi>Angels,</hi> and gave him the <hi>fulneſs</hi> of the <hi>Earth</hi> to <hi>poſſeſs,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled at all times againſt his <hi>GOD;</hi> he departed from the <hi>beginning,</hi> from the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Way,</hi> and made <hi>Invention</hi> the joy of his <hi>Heart,</hi> and made his <hi>Inventions</hi> a fence againſt <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Imaginations</hi> a Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark of <hi>defence;</hi> and in all <hi>Ages</hi> and <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations,</hi> though the <hi>LORD</hi> viſited with <hi>Judgements, Deſtruction, Mercies,</hi> and wonderful <hi>Deliverances,</hi> and ſent his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> the <hi>Prophets,</hi> ariſing up <hi>early,</hi> and lying <hi>down late,</hi> with <hi>Precept</hi> upon <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33625:7"/>
and <hi>Line</hi> upon <hi>Line,</hi> ſpeaking as <hi>afar off,</hi> by <hi>Signes,</hi> and <hi>Figures,</hi> and <hi>Parables;</hi> and as <hi>at hand,</hi> by <hi>Iudgement</hi> and <hi>Mercy:</hi> And always ſhewed how that he <hi>is GOD,</hi> and altogether <hi>unlimited,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bound unto <hi>Words,</hi> nor <hi>Wonders,</hi> nor limited in <hi>Sea</hi> or in <hi>Land;</hi> but ſtill <hi>Man</hi> made <hi>marks</hi> for <hi>GOD,</hi> and ſet <hi>bounds</hi> for the <hi>Arm</hi> of <hi>his Power,</hi> who in no wiſe is <hi>meaſured</hi> as the <hi>waters</hi> in the <hi>Wells,</hi> nor <hi>contained</hi> as the <hi>Rivers</hi> with the <hi>banks,</hi> who was not <hi>conceived</hi> as the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> nor <hi>born</hi> as the <hi>Babe</hi> of the <hi>Womb;</hi> who is not <hi>comprehended</hi> as the <hi>graſs</hi> with the <hi>ground,</hi> nor as the wide ſwelling <hi>Seas</hi> with the <hi>ſands</hi> of the <hi>ſhores;</hi> who is not <hi>known</hi> as he <hi>knoweth</hi> all fowls, and calleth the <hi>Stars</hi> by <hi>name;</hi> who is not <hi>meaſured</hi> as the <hi>Earth</hi> with the <hi>Moon,</hi> nor as the <hi>Heavens</hi> with the courſe of the <hi>Sun;</hi> and therefore <hi>Man</hi> alwayes <hi>loſt</hi> the knowledge of the eternal <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>God-head,</hi> and ſtill ſettled in his <hi>own will,</hi> which at firſt <hi>rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> againſt <hi>GOD,</hi> and in the ſame <hi>Will</hi> made <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Statutes,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> for <hi>Government,</hi> for <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and for <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> though even from the dayes of the firſt man <hi>Adam,</hi> unto this <hi>day,</hi> the hand of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33625:8"/>
the <hi>LORD GOD</hi> was turned againſt that work, as witneſs the <hi>preaching</hi> of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of <hi>Abel, Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Noah, he who hath <hi>an ear</hi> let him <hi>hear;</hi>
               </hi> witneſs alſo <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> among the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> among the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> yea, witneſs the Spirit of <hi>Moſes</hi> among <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> by <hi>Preaching,</hi> by <hi>Power,</hi> by <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Deliverance.</hi> What may I more ſay? They would build a <hi>Tower</hi> to reach unto Heaven, and <hi>Arks,</hi> and <hi>Cities,</hi> and <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> and <hi>Temple;</hi> And all for <hi>GOD</hi> to be <hi>constrained</hi> in their <hi>Works,</hi> and when they had <hi>Commandments</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> as appointed by the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>LORD,</hi> the Spirit ſheweth, when in all theſe things, they would have <hi>forced</hi> the <hi>Reſt</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> the <hi>LORD</hi> aroſe alwayes <hi>against them,</hi> and ſent his <hi>Servants</hi> the <hi>Prophets</hi> to cry againſt thoſe <hi>things,</hi> with the ſame <hi>Word</hi> which commanded <hi>them,</hi> whom they did <hi>beat, impriſon, wound</hi> and <hi>torture,</hi> yea, and put to <hi>death.</hi> And thus it alwayes was, <hi>He that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the Spirit, even as it is now; and in like manner, it hath been from the dayes of</hi> Abel, <hi>until the</hi> Heir <hi>came, and him they ſhamefully ſlew to poſſeſs the Vineyard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33625:8"/>Moreover, of <hi>his dayes</hi> I may alſo ſpeak, even in the dayes of the <hi>LORD CHRIST,</hi> when he was <hi>transfigured</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> at the glorious appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of <hi>Moſes, Eliah,</hi> and the <hi>LORD,</hi> the Diſciples would build them <hi>Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles;</hi> but <hi>mercy</hi> appeared unto them in a <hi>Rebuke,</hi> and they were inſtructed in the <hi>Way</hi> of <hi>GOD;</hi> but yet (and notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding alſo, that <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> taught a preſſing on from one <hi>degree</hi> of Faith unto <hi>another,</hi> until all ſhould be <hi>perfected</hi> unto the fulneſs of the meaſure, of a compleat ſtature, ſhewing alſo in the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> [who himſelf was <hi>riſen</hi> with <hi>Chriſt</hi>] the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities of the meaſures of the Glories which were revealed, and every meaſure as gathered into God in his fulneſs, were reſpectively full, ſhewing it by the figure of the Glories, of the Lights, of the <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars;</hi> and wrote to the <hi>Church,</hi> how that he was caught up into the <hi>third Heaven,</hi> and ſaw things which were <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful</hi> to be <hi>uttered.</hi> And <hi>John,</hi> in the <hi>LORD</hi>'S <hi>Day,</hi> [in the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the Lord from Heaven] ſaw the <hi>great things</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> yet ſaid the Angel unto him, <hi>Come up hither:</hi> I ſay, notwithſtanding <hi>all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33625:9"/>
this,</hi> the doctrine of <hi>GOD,</hi> that he might be known to be <hi>GOD,</hi> and not in any wiſe to be limited) <hi>Man</hi> in his <hi>wilfulneſs</hi> and <hi>preſumption</hi> unto this day, hath ſet <hi>marks</hi> againſt him, and made <hi>meaſures</hi> of words in their <hi>Wills,</hi> as Cords of <hi>restraint</hi> to bind him; yea, the <hi>Heavens</hi> and the <hi>Earth,</hi> and the depth of the <hi>Seas,</hi> and all the <hi>increaſe</hi> of the <hi>Plant</hi> of the <hi>field,</hi> and her ſeeding Seed, the <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> the <hi>Clouds,</hi> the <hi>Winds,</hi> the <hi>Hail,</hi> and the <hi>Rain-bow</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> ſhall witneſs againſt the <hi>Nations</hi> of the world in this <hi>matter;</hi> They <hi>limit</hi> not <hi>God</hi> in their pleaſure; but do <hi>bow</hi> in ſubjection to his <hi>Will:</hi> but the <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> in the <hi>crookedneſs</hi> of their hearts, have made <hi>walls</hi> againſt the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O <hi>Man,</hi> lift up thine head, and <hi>look,</hi> and <hi>behold,</hi> how the People and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Earth do <hi>limit</hi> the <hi>LORD</hi> to their <hi>luſts:</hi> O open thine <hi>Eye,</hi> and <hi>ſee</hi> how they make <hi>GOD</hi> as a <hi>Tranſgreſſor</hi> in the Earth, even as the <hi>Cattle</hi> of a <hi>Stranger,</hi> which have fed in the fields of their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture,</hi> and as the <hi>hand</hi> of a <hi>Thief</hi> and <hi>Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> which hath ſtolen the <hi>labour</hi> of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Look thorow the Earth among the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33625:9"/>
               <hi>Nations</hi> thereof, and thou mayeſt read all their <hi>Profeſſions</hi> as <hi>Priſons;</hi> for the <hi>Reign</hi> of of <hi>GOD</hi> in the <hi>Conſcience</hi> is limited by the <hi>forms</hi> of their Words; and one <hi>cryeth <hi>Here,</hi>
               </hi> and another <hi>ſaith <hi>There;</hi>
               </hi> and another <hi>ſaith theſe are <hi>the Laws</hi> and the <hi>Precepts,</hi> and he that will not</hi> Reſt <hi>in this, he is out of the</hi> Way <hi>of GOD, and he that ſpeaks againſt</hi> our Law, <hi>and the Manners of</hi> our Worſhip, <hi>he must bear the puniſhment thereof.</hi> Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all which, if the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of GOD ſhould demand, Are your Words GOD? or, Are your <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> the <hi>Arm</hi> of GOD? yea, I ſay, if that <hi>Conſcience</hi> in whom <hi>GOD liveth</hi> and <hi>reigneth,</hi> ſhould ask of them all, Are your <hi>Words,</hi> or <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> or <hi>Forms</hi> of Worſhip, the <hi>immediate</hi> Commandment of the <hi>LORD GOD</hi> from Heaven, which ſhall endure for ever? not <hi>one</hi> of a <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> either <hi>could,</hi> or <hi>would</hi> give a ready <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> thereunto; which if they would ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly anſwer <hi>negatively,</hi> concluding their words <hi>not to be GOD,</hi> nor their <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> the <hi>Arm</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> why then do they ſet <hi>their Words</hi> above <hi>GOD,</hi> as a <hi>limit</hi> and <hi>bound</hi> to the Spirit of <hi>GOD?</hi> And, why ſet they their <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> and <hi>Forms</hi> of Worſhip in the <hi>Seat</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> to <hi>judge</hi> in more Power than
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33625:10"/>
the <hi>Arm</hi> of <hi>GOD?</hi> To the ſons of men it may be fully ſaid, To <hi>whom</hi> is the <hi>Living GOD</hi> known, and the <hi>Arm</hi> of the <hi>LORD</hi> revealed? For, if GOD be a <hi>Spirit,</hi> and is only known <hi>in Spirit,</hi> to live <hi>in Spirit,</hi> and to dwell with men in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> How remaineth the <hi>knowledge</hi> of this <hi>true GOD</hi> among the ſons of men, who by the <hi>limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of their <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> and <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Words</hi> in the Will, out of the <hi>unlimited Spirit,</hi> do thruſt him the <hi>unlimited Spirit</hi> out of his <hi>true habitation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all the <hi>ſons</hi> of <hi>men</hi> upon the face of the Earth, who have <hi>reached</hi> as far as the <hi>Tradition,</hi> but <hi>want</hi> the <hi>Life,</hi> even unto all <hi>Sects,</hi> and among you all, I might <hi>largely</hi> and <hi>plentifully</hi> declare your <hi>Judgments</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> and not with that of <hi>GOD in the Conſcience,</hi> anſwers not that of <hi>GOD in the Conſcience</hi> of any man, and GOD hath no <hi>Unity</hi> with your <hi>Judgment,</hi> but his <hi>hand</hi> he turneth <hi>against</hi> it, even as in all <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> paſt; The <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of your <hi>Worſhips,</hi> and not <hi>in the Spirit,</hi> the Spirit turneth <hi>againſt you,</hi> and the Spirit will have <hi>glory</hi> over you; for, be you not <hi>ignorant,</hi> how that the <hi>Spirit</hi> created the <hi>Times,</hi> and in time <hi>Tradition</hi> and <hi>Cuſtom</hi> came forth; And
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33625:10"/>
the <hi>Spirit</hi> which <hi>changeth</hi> the <hi>Times,</hi> will <hi>change</hi> the <hi>Customs</hi> and <hi>Forms;</hi> and when GOD hath put all theſe things under foot, he will be known to be <hi>All <hi>in</hi> All,</hi> in the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> his own proper <hi>Seat</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion.</hi> What art thou O <hi>corruptible man</hi> [in whom God created a Conſcience] that ſits <hi>above GOD</hi> in thy <hi>Will,</hi> making <hi>a Law</hi> againſt GOD in the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of another? Knowſt thou not that GOD hath the <hi>whole Dominion</hi> there? Knoweſt thou not that GOD hath granted <hi>a Law</hi> againſt <hi>all Sin,</hi> and <hi>written</hi> it in the <hi>Conſcience [his own ſeat]</hi> where he cometh to <hi>Judgment</hi> of the whole World of <hi>Mankind,</hi> as well in it the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> who have not the Letter of the Law, by the ſame which he will <hi>judge</hi> both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> who have the <hi>Law,</hi> and in the <hi>Life</hi> are found <hi>tranſgreſſors</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> And makeſt thou <hi>a Law</hi> againſt the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>GOD?</hi> againſt that which thou makeſt and ſetteſt a <hi>bound-mark, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation,</hi> and <hi>Law,</hi> which is in another; in, and by the ſelf ſame thing in thy ſelf, ſhalt thou be <hi>judged</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> becauſe of thy Law; and the <hi>LORD GOD</hi> will be known to be the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Spirits,</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Lights,</hi> whoſe Spirit and Light by all the <hi>Cuſtoms,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33625:11"/>
Traditions, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> in the World, is not in any meaſure <hi>comprehended</hi> to be equally <hi>judged,</hi> or made in Righteouſneſs <hi>ſubordinate</hi> unto in the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of another; and that of GOD <hi>in you all</hi> ſhall <hi>witneſs</hi> this for <hi>ever,</hi> and <hi>bear</hi> its <hi>everlaſting Teſtimony</hi> againſt your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible <hi>corrupt wills,</hi> which make <hi>Laws,</hi> and conſtrain <hi>Customs</hi> and <hi>Traditions</hi> by <hi>Laws,</hi> againſt the incomprehenſible mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of GOD <hi>in another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>a Warning</hi> from the <hi>LORD GOD,</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Spirits</hi> and <hi>Lights,</hi> to you all is come, to give <hi>you</hi> to <hi>take heed</hi> in due ſeaſon, leſt you be found <hi>fighters againſt GOD</hi> your <hi>Creator,</hi> in the day that he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to <hi>Account,</hi> and draweth near unto <hi>Judgment</hi> in the Land; And lay it to heart with underſtanding, that for <hi>this cauſe <hi>only</hi>
               </hi> that he was <hi>fought againſt <hi>in the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi>
               </hi> by <hi>Customs,</hi> by <hi>Laws,</hi> by <hi>Judgment,</hi> by <hi>Life,</hi> by <hi>Traditions,</hi> by <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> by <hi>Sinners,</hi> by <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt the Power <hi>in the Conſcience,</hi> by <hi>Jews</hi> and by <hi>Gentiles,</hi> all the <hi>Overtures, Deſolations, Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Deſtructions, Captivities,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> of the <hi>Wrath, Indignation</hi> and <hi>Vengeance</hi> of GOD, from <hi>Age</hi> to <hi>Age,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:33625:11"/>
reaching unto this <hi>preſent Age,</hi> came to paſſe in the Earth; <hi>Witneſs <hi>the Flood;</hi>
               </hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah;</hi> witneſs the <hi>Red Sea;</hi> witneſs the <hi>Walls of Iericho;</hi> witneſs <hi>the Mulberry-trees;</hi> witneſs <hi>the Battels of Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>the Captivity of his Children;</hi> witneſs <hi>the Worms that ate Herod;</hi> witneſs <hi>the Deſtruction of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and <hi>the ſcattering of the Iews in the Earth;</hi> witneſs <hi>Greece, Germany, Scotland, England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and <hi>yet</hi> the LORD will call the whole Earth to <hi>witneſs,</hi> and bring <hi>heap</hi> upon <hi>heap,</hi> and <hi>deſtruction</hi> upon <hi>deſtruction,</hi> and <hi>deſolation</hi> upon <hi>deſolation,</hi> by <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Sword</hi> in every Land, that ſtandeth againſt <hi>the Word</hi> of the <hi>LORD GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>bleſſed</hi> is he that cometh to know the <hi>ground</hi> and <hi>root</hi> of a matter <hi>in him,</hi> to know the <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>Deſolations</hi> determined to be in the <hi>Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might ſay unto you, how that in the dayes of <hi>Luther,</hi> GOD moved in the <hi>Darkneſs</hi> upon the <hi>face</hi> of the <hi>deeps</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; but they which made <hi>him</hi> their <hi>Rest</hi> are <hi>confounded,</hi> and their <hi>head</hi> is <hi>broken</hi> as Clay. He appeared <hi>brighter</hi> by <hi>Behman</hi> and <hi>Brown;</hi> but they which built their <hi>Travels</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33625:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
as <hi>Towers,</hi> the LORD <hi>confounded</hi> with many <hi>Languages,</hi> and even running up to the height, <hi>Baptiſts, Seekers</hi> and <hi>Ranters,</hi> ſome made <hi>bounds</hi> for the <hi>pure,</hi> and others in their <hi>lusts</hi> revolted; wherefore GOD hath laid them one upon the <hi>other,</hi> as a <hi>heap</hi> of <hi>confuſion</hi> together: And thus he hath begun the <hi>work</hi> of his hand, decreed to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect his <hi>purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>LORD GOD</hi> will make the Nations to know, That he hath not ſent down <hi>his Word</hi> in the Earth, to be <hi>likened</hi> unto a <hi>breath</hi> of <hi>Vanity</hi> in the Air, and that he cauſed not his <hi>Prophets</hi> to run in <hi>vain,</hi> as him which <hi>comes ſhort</hi> of the <hi>mark;</hi> but that <hi>his Law</hi> which he wrote upon the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of Stone,</hi> he writeth upon the <hi>Table of he Heart;</hi> and both the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hets,</hi> no more as in the dayes of continual <hi>ranſgreſſion,</hi> ſhall be told as a <hi>tale</hi> of <hi>tatlers,</hi> and as a <hi>hiſtory</hi> of <hi>vain bablers,</hi> pointed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tongue of a <hi>deceitful mouth;</hi> but that they ſhal be <hi>fulfilled</hi> and <hi>witneſſed,</hi> yea, and <hi>perfected</hi> in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> in <hi>Life</hi> and in <hi>Power,</hi> as by the <hi>Spirit</hi> in <hi>Life</hi> and in <hi>Power</hi> they were <hi>revealed,</hi> and <hi>given forth</hi> to this only end of GOD in his Creature: For which cauſe (laſtly) <hi>JESUS</hi> the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:33625:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
was <hi>revealed,</hi> to <hi>perfect</hi> that which was <hi>lacking,</hi> and to compleat the <hi>Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in fulneſs.</p>
            <p>Therefore all you <hi>dwellers</hi> in the <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of the Earth, <hi>Awake</hi> from the <hi>dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of your <hi>Forms</hi> and <hi>Worſhips,</hi> and <hi>draw near</hi> unto the <hi>quickning Power</hi> of the <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> which leads to <hi>Life</hi> in the <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> from <hi>all Sin:</hi> To which end, GOD ſent the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> a <hi>LIGHT</hi> unto the World, that <hi>all men</hi> through <hi>belief</hi> in the <hi>LIGHT</hi> might have <hi>Everlaſting Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You that are in the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> of a <hi>dead hope</hi> in a <hi>Saviour <hi>without you,</hi>
               </hi> and are not in the <hi>Life</hi> of the <hi>Faith</hi> of the <hi>Subſtance, CHRIST</hi> the <hi>living hope <hi>in you,</hi>
               </hi> which clenſeth the Soul from <hi>Sin,</hi> and waſheth the Heart from <hi>Iniquity;</hi> Wait in the <hi>Silence</hi> for the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the <hi>LORD</hi> from Heaven <hi>[who unto us is come]</hi> that <hi>[in you alſo]</hi> he may be <hi>known</hi> and <hi>witneſſed,</hi> and <hi>teſtified</hi> to be <hi>come,</hi> (according to the Promiſe) <hi>the ſecond time without ſin unto Salvation.</hi> Wait for his <hi>Appearance</hi> in the <hi>Clouds,</hi> to come <hi>breaking</hi> thorow the <hi>thickneſs</hi> of the <hi>blackneſs</hi> of the long night; to come down <hi>in the Earth</hi> as a <hi>burning fire,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:33625:13"/>
and to <hi>darken</hi> the <hi>Air</hi> with the <hi>ſmoak;</hi> to ſet the <hi>Heavens</hi> in <hi>fire,</hi> and to <hi>melt</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> before him; that you may come to know the <hi>Wonders</hi> of <hi>GOD fulfilled;</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> to be <hi>darkned,</hi> and to become <hi>black</hi> as <hi>ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath of hair,</hi> the <hi>Moon</hi> turned into <hi>blood,</hi> and the <hi>Stars</hi> to fall from <hi>Heaven,</hi> in the <hi>ſame ſubſtance</hi> to ſee and know theſe things come to paſſe, and with the <hi>ſame eye</hi> by which the Glories of the Heavens were created, and ſaw that it was good; I ſay with the <hi>ſame Spirit</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> which ſpake forth the <hi>Prophecy</hi> (which unto learned and unlearned, is become as a Book that is ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and hid from the Vultrous eye) to witneſs the <hi>Propheſie</hi> fulfilled. Wait for the <hi>Revelation</hi> of <hi>GOD's Plough</hi> in the Earth, for the <hi>tearing up</hi> of the <hi>Ground,</hi> and breaking the <hi>Clods</hi> thereof; for a due <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi> to receive <hi>the Seed</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that you may become as <hi>GOD's Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry</hi> in the Earth, and no longer remain as the <hi>barren Mountains</hi> thereof, which never bear <hi>Plough</hi> thereon, nor yeelded <hi>increaſe</hi> of <hi>good;</hi> nor as the <hi>Woods</hi> of the <hi>Forreſts,</hi> whoſe Trees were <hi>never pruned,</hi> which ſpread their unfruitful branches as thickets that cumber the ground. Settle not your ſelves in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33625:13"/>
               <hi>ſluggards Rest,</hi> nor as a <hi>wounded Fool</hi> with his <hi>putrified fleſh,</hi> who is rather willing to periſh <hi>in death,</hi> than to cut off his Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>for life:</hi> Be ye not alwayes <hi>as Moab,</hi> ſetled upon the <hi>ſcent</hi> of the <hi>old lees,</hi> for it <hi>ſtinks</hi> in the <hi>noſtrils</hi> of <hi>GOD;</hi> but wait for the <hi>Remove</hi> of the <hi>Ground,</hi> and yeeld unto the <hi>hewings</hi> of GOD; the <hi>Ax</hi> to be laid to the <hi>Root</hi> of the <hi>Tree,</hi> and the <hi>Sword</hi> to the <hi>Soul</hi> that <hi>ſinneth,</hi> to know <hi>Judgment</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the <hi>Houſe</hi> of the <hi>LORD,</hi> to cut off the <hi>Wicked</hi> in the <hi>Land.</hi> And ſeek not to <hi>eſcape</hi> the day of <hi>GOD's Wrath,</hi> but bear his Indignation <hi>within you,</hi> as the <hi>juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> of your <hi>ſins,</hi> which are called up unto <hi>Judgment</hi> againſt you; And wait in <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> until it be <hi>over</hi> and <hi>past,</hi> that you may know his <hi>acceptable year</hi> to be <hi>come:</hi> And when <hi>theſe things</hi> you know, and witneſs fulfilled <hi>within you,</hi> even as they are <hi>known</hi> and <hi>teſtified</hi> in the <hi>Life of GOD's Heritage,</hi> you ſhall bear me Teſtimony in the Holy Ghoſt, That although the <hi>Judgement <hi>be weighty,</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>Ax <hi>burthenſom,</hi>
               </hi> and the <hi>flaming Sword of the LORD <hi>a moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous thing;</hi>
               </hi> all the <hi>burden,</hi> the <hi>weight,</hi> the <hi>grief,</hi> and the <hi>travel</hi> is but of the <hi>carnal</hi> and <hi>ſinful part;</hi> And to <hi>it</hi> only is the <hi>irkeſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33625:14"/>
thereof, until it be utterly <hi>cut off</hi> and <hi>ſlain</hi> upon the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> even of <hi>that part</hi> which is this day the cauſe of the <hi>cry</hi> of the <hi>Juſt</hi> in the Land; and then you ſhall <hi>be one</hi> with the <hi>Judgement, one</hi> with the <hi>Sword, one</hi> with the <hi>Ax, one</hi> with the <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Burning of GOD,</hi> to <hi>dwell</hi> in its glory for ever. Here the true <hi>Purgatory</hi> is come, and the <hi>ſin</hi> is <hi>waſhed</hi> away, thorow which the <hi>entrance</hi> is made into the <hi>habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Peace of GOD,</hi> and there is no true Reſt without it: Then there is <hi>no more ſin,</hi> no more <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> in the Land, the <hi>curſed Earth</hi> is conſumed with all her <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe,</hi> the <hi>evil Ground,</hi> and the <hi>Works</hi> which were wrought therein <hi>are burnt up together,</hi> the <hi>New-Creation</hi> is come, <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> is created anew, the <hi>old Heavens,</hi> and the <hi>old Earth</hi> is paſſed away, there is no more <hi>remembrance</hi> of them, and <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> is created an <hi>habitation</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>LORD</hi> is in her; and this is the <hi>holy City,</hi> into which the <hi>Hebrews</hi> were entered, which <hi>John</hi> propheſied ſhould in theſe latter dayes come down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven [without whoſe gates are the <hi>Dogs, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, Witches, Whoremongers, Murderers,</hi> and whatſoever <hi>loveth</hi> or <hi>maketh a Lye</hi>] in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33625:14"/>
which we in the <hi>Kingdom</hi> are entered; whoſe <hi>Kingdom</hi> is not of this World; and you coming <hi>hither</hi> will enter into the way of the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Counſel</hi> of the <hi>Moſt High,</hi> to ſee all <hi>things, purpoſes, Statutes</hi> and <hi>Judgments,</hi> by that of GOD ordered and brought forth, in the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Counſel</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> and your <hi>own</hi> caſt under foot as a <hi>corruptible thing</hi> for ever: Then the <hi>whole Creation</hi> of GOD which <hi>travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in pain</hi> until the <hi>Redemption cometh,</hi> will <hi>joy</hi> in the <hi>approach</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> for then ſhal you uſe the <hi>Creatures</hi> ſingly to the <hi>proper end,</hi> in the <hi>ſame Wiſdom,</hi> by the which they were created: The burning deſire of <hi>Lust</hi> ſhall <hi>dye,</hi> and the <hi>evil appetite</hi> be taken <hi>away; Increaſe</hi> ſhall fill the <hi>houſe,</hi> and <hi>Bleſſing</hi> overflow the <hi>heart;</hi> the <hi>Land</hi> ſhall be preſerved in <hi>Peace,</hi> and the <hi>City</hi> become a Sanctuary of <hi>ſafety; Invaſion</hi> ſhall never proſper; For <hi>Wiſdom</hi> ſhall confound the <hi>work</hi> of the <hi>Wicked,</hi> and bring to nought the <hi>counſel</hi> of the <hi>Ungodly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eye of <hi>GOD</hi> is his <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> which pierceth the <hi>Depths</hi> of the <hi>Earth;</hi> to be in <hi>his Wiſdom,</hi> is <hi>ſafety,</hi> true <hi>ſafety,</hi> ſure <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> from <hi>all Snares, Plots, Conspiracies, Deſigns</hi> and <hi>Intentions</hi> of the VVorld, <hi>Hell,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33625:15"/>
and the <hi>Devil;</hi> For by the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> all fleſh was made, and that which warreth againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> its Maker, by the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> it ſhall be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded:</hi> Wherefore all [for everlaſting ſafety] draw near unto <hi>Wiſdom's gates,</hi> and wait for the <hi>Counſel</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of <hi>GOD<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> to receive <hi>VViſdom</hi> in the <hi>Counſel</hi> of <hi>GOD<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and growing in the <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and dwelling in the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Counſel</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> his <hi>eye</hi> comes to be with you, as manifeſtly revealed <hi>in you,</hi> which ſearcheth and ſeeth into the <hi>depths</hi> of a <hi>matter:</hi> This is that Spirit <hi>of a man</hi> that knoweth the mind <hi>of a man;</hi> and by the <hi>ſame</hi> the way of the <hi>wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> comes to be <hi>manifeſt,</hi> and is a <hi>true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi> againſt a <hi>thouſand Armies.</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the <hi>poor man</hi> which was in the City, who by <hi>Wiſdom</hi> delivered it from the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> of the <hi>Enemy;</hi> And make not the <hi>ſeat</hi> of <hi>Treachery</hi> your Truſt, nor <hi>polliſhed ſubtilty upon the head of Iniquity,</hi> your Fort of Refuge for ſafety; For it ſhall be as a <hi>rotten ſtring</hi> in your <hi>right hand,</hi> which ſhall <hi>break</hi> with the <hi>bent</hi> of the <hi>Bow;</hi> For <hi>delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> is <hi>only</hi> of <hi>GOD;</hi> And the <hi>purpoſe</hi> of the <hi>perverſe</hi> ſhall <hi>periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things I have written, if haply you may get hear to be led unto the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33625:15"/>
of the Knowledge of GOD, to partake of his Treaſure of Wiſdom, and whilſt the poor man moves you, to liſten unto Counſel; if you reſiſt and will not, beware: Beware, leſt in the time of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, you cry, and gladly would, and then he be not to anſwer.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>From the Inquiſition-Priſon in</hi> Rome.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To <hi>Fabius Guiſius</hi> Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY <hi>Meſſage</hi> is not unto any part of the <hi>natural,</hi> either <hi>Wit, Will,</hi> or <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> it is neither <hi>meat</hi> for <hi>Serpents,</hi> nor <hi>air</hi> for <hi>Camelions;</hi> But the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>Lord God</hi> is to the Seed, which ſhall be <hi>witneſſed</hi> by the next <hi>Generation,</hi> whether this which now is will <hi>hear</hi> or <hi>forbear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the <hi>Meſſage</hi> which I have <hi>heard</hi> and <hi>received,</hi> and do <hi>declare</hi> unto thee: <hi>GOD</hi> is <hi>Light,</hi> and in him is no <hi>darkneſs</hi> at all, who hath ſent his Son a <hi>Light</hi> into the World, that all that <hi>believe</hi> in him who
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33625:16"/>
is <hi>the Light</hi> of the World, may have ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life; unto which <hi>Light</hi> thou muſt <hi>bow,</hi> and oughteſt to lay down thy <hi>Crown,</hi> at the feet of him who cometh in the <hi>Cloud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> thorow the <hi>thickneſs</hi> of the <hi>Night,</hi> and breaking thorow the <hi>blackneſs</hi> and <hi>darkneſs</hi> of the <hi>black</hi> and <hi>gloomy day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which <hi>Daniel</hi> [the greatly beloved of GOD] <hi>ſaw</hi> afar off, I <hi>ſee</hi> at hand; the <hi>little ſtone</hi> is cut out of the <hi>Mountain</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a hand, and is already become a <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> which the whole Earth is not able to <hi>remove,</hi> and will become a <hi>Mountain</hi> which ſhall fill the <hi>whole Earth,</hi> which ſhall throw down every <hi>Image</hi> before him, as ſaith the Prophet; <hi>GOD</hi> will <hi>confound</hi> the <hi>Image</hi> and the <hi>Image-maker,</hi> and him which <hi>boweth</hi> before it: Behold! <hi>Overturn</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, and <hi>Overturn</hi> followeth, until the laſt <hi>Overture</hi> be fulfilled, and <hi>He</hi> come whoſe <hi>Right</hi> it is to Reign, and his <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> which is an <hi>Everlaſting Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> be ſet up, and his <hi>Dominion</hi> unto the utmoſt <hi>Ends</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> of which there ſhall never be end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>GOD</hi> hath looked over the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> and hath heard the <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> thereof; They profeſs <hi>my Name</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33625:16"/>
the Lord) of whom I am made but as a <hi>curſe</hi> in their mouth: And my <hi>Name</hi> is but made the <hi>grievous Oath</hi> of the Land, ſaith the Jealous God: And from the <hi>head</hi> to the <hi>tayl,</hi> there is none amongſt them that have made the <hi>Separation</hi> betwixt the <hi>Juſt</hi> and the <hi>Vile;</hi> but as a <hi>Cage</hi> of unclean <hi>Birds,</hi> they are all <hi>common,</hi> as in <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> ſo alſo in their <hi>Iniquity</hi> and <hi>Tranſgreſſion;</hi> for which things I will <hi>viſit</hi> ſaith the Lord of Hoſts. As <hi>David</hi> complained, <hi>I am made the ſong of Drunkards;</hi> Even ſo now is <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> by every <hi>unclean tongue</hi> in the <hi>corners</hi> of the <hi>ſtreets,</hi> in the <hi>Temples,</hi> and in the <hi>High-ways</hi> of this Land of <hi>Whoredoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>Pull down the High-way marks of Idolatry,</hi> that the <hi>ſtranger</hi> may not <hi>ſtumble</hi> before me. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe thy Power <hi>for me,</hi> and <hi>not againſt me,</hi>
               </hi> ſaith the Lord; And <hi>throw down</hi> the <hi>great <hi>Image</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Idol</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> leſt I quickly tumble down <hi>two</hi> at <hi>once,</hi> ſaith the Lord of Hoſts. Plant not <hi>Bryars</hi> in the <hi>Way,</hi> neither <hi>ſet Thorns</hi> in the <hi>Gap;</hi> For lo, I am <hi>ariſen</hi> to <hi>ſmite</hi> the <hi>whole Earth,</hi> and to make <hi>breaches</hi> in the <hi>fenced places</hi> thereof; For <hi>now,</hi> even <hi>now,</hi> for mine
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33625:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
holy <hi>Name ſake,</hi> and my <hi>Seeds ſake,</hi> I am <hi>jealous</hi> ſaith the Lord of Hoſts; <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs <hi>ſhall run down like a Stream,</hi>
               </hi> and the <hi>Knowledge <hi>of the Lord ſhall cover the Earth, as waters cover the Seas;</hi>
               </hi> which is found <hi>ſcant</hi> in thy <hi>Land.</hi> Be thou henceforth no more called <hi>POPE,</hi> for that was never <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed</hi> nor <hi>propheſied</hi> of by the Word of the Lord; I am <hi>Peter's Succeſſor</hi> who am of <hi>his Spirit,</hi> whoſe Kingdom is not of this World, and ſo are <hi>we all</hi> who are made <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers</hi> of the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> which was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Chriſt, who when the <hi>Jews</hi> would take him <hi>by force,</hi> and make him a <hi>King,</hi> he departed into a <hi>Mountain</hi> alone, and was <hi>hid</hi> from them all; but thou maieſt keep the name of one of the <hi>Princes</hi> of this <hi>World,</hi> and in thy place as <hi>a Ruler,</hi> rule with the Judgment of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> not turning the <hi>ſtranger</hi> out of his <hi>way,</hi> nor condemning the <hi>Juſt</hi> by a <hi>Law,</hi> which <hi>David</hi> in his day complained of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rob not God of his Glory, <hi>For he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveth Sin;</hi> Repent, <hi>for thy Sin is not yet forgiven;</hi>
               </hi> Neither <hi>watch</hi> for any man's <hi>halting,</hi> for that is <hi>Iniquity;</hi> but <hi>cheriſh</hi> all that <hi>cry</hi> againſt <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and lift thou up thy <hi>voice</hi> with them that are <hi>redeemed</hi> out
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33625:17"/>
of the <hi>nature</hi> of <hi>Tranſgreſſion</hi> and <hi>Sin,</hi> that <hi>bear witneſs</hi> and <hi>cry</hi> againſt <hi>all Sin;</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes waſh thy <hi>hands,</hi> and keep thy <hi>heart</hi> clean from <hi>their blood,</hi> and the <hi>innocency</hi> of their <hi>ſufferings.</hi> Say not, <hi>that I came to deceive the People of thy Nation,</hi> whoſe <hi>life</hi> is as a <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Tranſgreſſion,</hi> who have not <hi>anything</hi> to be <hi>deceived</hi> of in that nature, but <hi>Prophaneſs, Sin,</hi> and <hi>Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> I came to declare the <hi>Meſſage</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> unto thee, and ſo to paſs as a <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim</hi> and a <hi>Stranger</hi> out of thy Land. I came not with <hi>any thing</hi> in my Veſſel unto <hi>thee,</hi> or any of this <hi>City,</hi> which is <hi>new,</hi> ſave only as it is <hi>new</hi> unto the <hi>old nature</hi> of all <hi>Tranſgreſſors</hi> and <hi>ſeed</hi> of <hi>Corrupters,</hi> which is the <hi>new Wine</hi> of the Kingdom of GOD. Do not ask, how thou ſhalt know? For in <hi>Judgment</hi> thou ſhalt know, that this is the <hi>Meſſage</hi> of the <hi>LORD GOD</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> unto thee.</p>
            <p>I have born <hi>a burden</hi> for thee, and now I bear <hi>thy yoak</hi> under thee; Yet <hi>much more</hi> could I ſuffer in the exerciſe of the <hi>long patience</hi> of the <hi>LORD,</hi> That this Nation <hi>might drink</hi> of the <hi>Cup</hi> of the <hi>Everlaſting Bleſſing</hi> of the <hi>LORD,</hi> and the <hi>Curſe</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from their <hi>head,</hi> to eat the <hi>bread</hi> of <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>gladneſs</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:33625:18"/>So having thus far cleared my ſelf unto thee, did it ſtand in my own <hi>freedom</hi> I ſhould <hi>depart</hi> thy Coaſts; but being not <hi>mine own,</hi> but the <hi>LORD's</hi> Witneſs againſt <hi>all Ungodlineſs;</hi> For this <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> with <hi>gladneſs</hi> I wear the yoak of bonds; and not only yet, but what elſe may follow, in his content and patience that hath called me:</p>
            <p>Who by the ſons of men am called</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN PERROTT.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the Inquiſition-Priſon in</hi> Rome.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the Governour of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>COme to know the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> the Power of GOD to be <hi>highest <hi>in thee,</hi>
               </hi> and let that be the <hi>Judge</hi> of all <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> and <hi>cauſes</hi> which ſhall come before thee; Let the <hi>Sword</hi> of the <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> be ſet up <hi>in thy houſe <hi>within,</hi>
               </hi> that the <hi>Tranſgreſſor</hi> may be <hi>ſlain <hi>within;</hi>
               </hi> then the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33625:18"/>
               <hi>Eye</hi> will be <hi>opened,</hi> the <hi>Ear</hi> will be <hi>unſtopt,</hi> the groſſneſs of the <hi>Heart</hi> will be taken away, and thou wilt have the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the root of a matter <hi>in thee,</hi> and wilt alway <hi>judge</hi> for <hi>GOD,</hi> and every <hi>end</hi> will be ſhaken off; No man ſhall at any time ſee his <hi>end</hi> over thee, by <hi>gifts</hi> or <hi>preſents, deceitful ſpeeches</hi> or <hi>flattering titles</hi> of that <hi>honour</hi> which comes from <hi>man;</hi> but ſo thou wilt ſtand in the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> which comes from <hi>GOD only,</hi> which is the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving ſtate;</hi> but the ſeeking of the other is the <hi>unbelieving,</hi> ſaith Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>come</hi> to the <hi>Light,</hi> and <hi>dwell</hi> in the <hi>Light,</hi> with thy <hi>mind</hi> and <hi>heart</hi> ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed and fixed <hi>in it,</hi> which ſhews thy own <hi>tranſgreſſion <hi>within,</hi>
               </hi> to have feeling of the <hi>Judgment</hi> of GOD upon the <hi>tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor <hi>in thee:</hi>
               </hi> And come to the <hi>love</hi> of the <hi>Light,</hi> and <hi>follow</hi> the <hi>Light,</hi> by it to be led out of <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> and then with the <hi>Light,</hi> by which all things are made manifeſt, in all <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Judgment,</hi> thou wilt reach that of <hi>GOD in all,</hi> which in all will <hi>juſtifie</hi> thee in the <hi>ſight</hi> of <hi>GOD;</hi> and ſo thou wilt ſtand girded with <hi>Juſtice</hi> in the ſeat of <hi>Equity</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> a <hi>terror</hi> to <hi>evil-doers,</hi> and <hi>a praiſe</hi> to them <hi>that do well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:33625:19"/>
               <hi>GOD</hi> is coming to <hi>ſearch</hi> the <hi>whole Earth,</hi> who looketh for the fruit of <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> from all that <hi>ſit</hi> in the <hi>ſeat thereof: <hi>Mercy</hi>
               </hi> to the <hi>Poor, <hi>Relief</hi>
               </hi> of the <hi>Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;</hi> The <hi>Poor</hi> hath <hi>cryed,</hi> and the <hi>Oppreſſed</hi> hath <hi>groaned,</hi> and <hi>GOD</hi> hath <hi>heard</hi> it, and he who <hi>heareth</hi> will <hi>anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> thou alwayes in thy place <hi>for the LORD,</hi> leſt the <hi>LORD GOD</hi> make thee to anſwer for thy ſelf before Him. Though I am but as a <hi>ſuckling</hi> of the <hi>Lords Flock,</hi> nevertheleſs in the <hi>ſimplicity</hi> and <hi>tenderneſs</hi> of my life, as one that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>Mercy</hi> at the <hi>Judgment ſeat</hi> of God, according to the lowlineſs of my meaſure, I <hi>counſel thee</hi> in his pure fear, That thou doſt look over the <hi>Books</hi> of the <hi>Regiſters</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> of thy <hi>Nation,</hi> and ſee if <hi>any one Statute</hi> be there written, which may ſtand as <hi>a Law</hi> to <hi>condemn</hi> the <hi>Juſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> David</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of that in his day; for he ſaw the <hi>iſſue</hi> of what came to paſſe, though it was <hi>afar off</hi> from his dayes: <hi>We have a Law</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Jews) and by our Law he ought to dye;</hi> by which they in their wilfulneſs put the <hi>LORD CHRIST</hi> to death. And ſo it was in all Ages, that <hi>tranſgreſſors</hi> (for whom, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> the Law was made) did
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33625:19"/>
make ſuch to <hi>ſuffer</hi> under <hi>the Law,</hi> and put them to <hi>death</hi> by a <hi>Law,</hi> in whoſe mouth <hi>guile</hi> was not found, which was the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Judgment.</hi> Friend, Draw thou thy hand <hi>from that;</hi> And though the people <hi>do cry,</hi> even as it was complained of in <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> concerning the Prophet, <hi>The Land is not able to bear all his words,</hi> yet of a truth the <hi>Word of the LORD</hi> will come to <hi>paſſe</hi> and be <hi>fulfilled.</hi> And truly I ſay unto <hi>thee,</hi> as <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſaid unto the <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with the life of that Prophet: <hi>Do with me as ſeemeth good in thy ſight;</hi> but aſſuredly <hi>know</hi> I am of God. And I alſo deſire, that the <hi>LORD GOD</hi> in <hi>Mercy,</hi> may not lay <hi>this thing</hi> to your <hi>charge</hi> in the day of his <hi>Judgments,</hi> foraſmuch as you <hi>do</hi> you know <hi>not what.</hi> I ſit not in the ſeat of the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous,</hi> in any meaſure apt to <hi>judge</hi> any thing before the <hi>true time;</hi> wherefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the <hi>fruit</hi> in this matter did ſhew the <hi>Tree,</hi> I ſhall not at the preſent accuſe the <hi>Romans</hi> with our <hi>detainment</hi> under their <hi>Yoak</hi> of <hi>Captivity,</hi> to provoke words from us, whereby the Prophet's words might become fulfilled upon your heads, in this your Age, <hi>in making a man an offender for a word;</hi> but I am rather in <hi>expectation</hi> of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33625:20"/>
               <hi>Appearance</hi> of the <hi>Nobility,</hi> of that which hath been <hi>reported</hi> and <hi>written</hi> concerning the <hi>Romans;</hi> If we have <hi>tranſgreſſed</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> of GOD, Try us by the <hi>Law,</hi> and give us <hi>our puniſhment</hi> according <hi>to the Law;</hi> For the <hi>LORD GOD</hi> knows I delight in <hi>Righteous Judgment:</hi> If we are not found <hi>tranſgreſſors,</hi> why are we <hi>innocent ſtrangers</hi> and <hi>pilgrims</hi> ſtopped of our Voyage? if our Bonds hold us by you, onely upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>ſuspition,</hi> we blame you not; but prove us, and ſatisfie your ſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning us; only if we have found the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of <hi>Juſtice</hi> before you, which the living God <hi>requires</hi> of you, ſhew us the <hi>Cauſe</hi> in truth why we are detained, that according to <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Equity</hi> before your ſeat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Judgment, we may make our <hi>open Defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am a Friend of thy ſoul, <hi>J. P.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the Inquiſition-Priſon in</hi> Rome.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:33625:20"/>
            <head>To all in the Colledges of <hi>Rome,</hi> that have any zeal or deſire to anſwer Truth for the Lord and Truths ſake.</head>
            <p>MEn fearing GOD are not <hi>raſh</hi> nor <hi>heady,</hi> neither will they <hi>judge</hi> a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before the time: Wherefore for the better <hi>information</hi> of your ſelves, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> the <hi>Way</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> I have in plain-heartedneſs <hi>queried,</hi> for you (in the honeſty of ſober minds) to give me <hi>your Anſwer</hi> in writing, plainly and pertinently to <hi>each</hi> of <hi>them,</hi> without renting any part of my <hi>words;</hi> For which, in <hi>expectation,</hi> I ſhall wait in <hi>Rome</hi> whilſt theſe Bonds hold me, until <hi>it</hi> come to my hands; which you ought to <hi>anſwer,</hi> as you profeſs the name of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity</hi> among the ſons of men, for the ſake of ſouls.</p>
            <p>Query 1. <hi>What is that <hi>one thing need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful unto Salvation,</hi> which with the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereof a man poſſeſſeth all things? And, whether can a man</hi> poſſeſs it, <hi>and not</hi> know it, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:33625:21"/>Que. 2. <hi>What is <hi>that</hi> by which</hi> Paul <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the Brethren to,</hi> to try the ſpirits, whether they were of God, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 3. <hi>Whether are any of you <hi>now</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by CHRIST to a further eſtate of</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>than the</hi> Diſciples <hi>were <hi>then</hi> when</hi> Chriſt <hi>ſaid unto them,</hi> You know not of what ſpirits you are, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 4. <hi>If by</hi> Chriſt <hi>you are</hi> called further, <hi>ſhew me</hi> how? <hi>And, whether you have really heard the</hi> Voice <hi>of</hi> Chriſt? <hi>but if</hi> not called <hi>unto, or beyond that</hi> eſtate <hi>which they were</hi> then in, <hi>not knowing your own</hi> ſpirits, <hi>by what ſpirit would you truly judge of my Spirit who am of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the Way of God.</p>
            <p>Que. 5. <hi>Whether are you</hi> in the way of God, <hi>which is but <hi>one?</hi> and, How was that</hi> one <hi>unto</hi> Enoch, <hi>and now but</hi> one <hi>and the ſame unto you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 6. <hi>Whether is not CHRIST the <hi>Light</hi> of the World, that <hi>one way,</hi> yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 7. <hi>Whether are</hi> ſinners <hi>in CHRIST, who is the <hi>narrow way?</hi> or, are they under the power of</hi> Satan <hi>in the <hi>broad way,</hi> yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 8. <hi>Whether are you</hi> in that way <hi>which was prophefied of, and is</hi> now manifeſt,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33625:21"/>
               <hi>which the</hi> way-faring men, though fools, cannot erre therein, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 9. <hi>Whether are you in any other</hi> way, <hi>but in</hi> that <hi>in which an Hypocrite can walk? and, whether can an</hi> Hypocrite <hi>walk in CHRIST, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 10. <hi>Whether are not <hi>all</hi> that are in the Church of</hi> Chriſt, in the true way of God, <hi>where the</hi> way-faring men, though fools, cannot erre therein?</p>
            <p>Que. 11. <hi>Whether is the <hi>Spirit</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>Truth <hi>come unto</hi>
               </hi> you, <hi>which leadeth the Members of Chriſt's Church <hi>into all Truth?</hi> But if you have not a Member that in life is</hi> led out of all Error <hi>into</hi> all Truth, <hi>How can you ſay that you</hi> have the Spirit of Truth?</p>
            <p>Que. 12. <hi>If <hi>all</hi> be in</hi> Sin <hi>and</hi> Error <hi>in the Life, How ſhall I conclude <hi>any one</hi> to be of the</hi> true Faith, <hi>ſeeing the Apoſtle ſaith,</hi> Shew me thy Faith by thy Works? <hi>Can the</hi> Faith <hi>be</hi> perfect, <hi>except the</hi> Works <hi>be</hi> perfect, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 13. <hi>Whether had not the</hi> Jews <hi>all <hi>the words of the</hi>
               </hi> Prophets, <hi>and yet when</hi> Chriſt <hi>came <hi>ſlew</hi> Him, who was the Virtue, Sum, Substance, the Beginning and End of the life of the Prophets? And, whether you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> out <hi>of the Spirit of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>are not</hi> under
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33625:22"/>
               <hi>the</hi> judgement <hi>of</hi> Jeremiah's <hi>words, viz</hi> Though they ſay, the LORD liveth, ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly they ſwear falſly?</p>
            <p>Que. 14. <hi>Whether did</hi> Adam <hi>loſe <hi>mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> in</hi>
               </hi> his <hi>life, than</hi> CHRIST <hi>came to <hi>reſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> unto Man in</hi> this <hi>life? Which is the greater the</hi> living ſoul, <hi>or the</hi> quickning ſpirit <hi>And, whether is any</hi> one <hi>or</hi> more <hi>of you Members reſtored unto either, or not in the life of either of theſe two ſtates, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 15. <hi>Whether is not <hi>all Sin</hi>
               </hi> of the <hi>Devil, <hi>and he that</hi>
               </hi> commits Sin, <hi>of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the true Church.</p>
            <p>Query 16. <hi>Whether is not the <hi>Trut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Church</hi> the</hi> Body of CHRIST <hi>which is</hi> in GOD? <hi>And, when</hi> Paul <hi>ſpake of</hi> Chriſt <hi>and the</hi> Church, <hi>whether did he not ſpeak of a</hi> Myſtery, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 17. <hi>Whether are the Members of Chriſt's Body <hi>evil?</hi> And if</hi> ſinners <hi>be Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſts Body, tell me if any</hi> other ſpirit <hi>be the</hi> ſinnews <hi>of that body, beſides the ſpirit of the Devil, which leads into ſin and evil, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 18. <hi>Whether is not the <hi>perfection</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:33625:22"/>
of the Glory of GOD</hi> in his Church? <hi>And whether doth that</hi> remain among ſinners, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 19. <hi>Whether hath not Chriſt, ſaid,</hi> Without exception God heareth not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? <hi>and therefore ſaith</hi> James, You ask, and have not. <hi>And, whether doth not God hear the</hi> Prayers <hi>of</hi> his Church, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 20. <hi>Whether doth not</hi> Paul <hi>ſay, That Chriſt's Church is without</hi> ſpot <hi>or</hi> wrinkle? <hi>to bring it into which ſtate, he</hi> purged every branch, <hi>and the</hi> unfruitful <hi>he</hi> cut off; <hi>And tell me ſince the laſt two hundred years, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your Members have encreaſed, in</hi> more Sin, <hi>or in</hi> more Holineſs, <hi>in outward ſhew and practice in their converſation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 21. <hi>Whether <hi>all</hi> that</hi> commit Sin <hi>are not in the</hi> Apoſtacy from the Spirit, <hi>which is the life of the Church, and leads out of all ſin, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 22. <hi>Whether is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the <hi>Father?</hi>
               </hi> [The Seed of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhall bruiſe the Serpent's head.] <hi>And did he come to do leſſe than was promiſed? Now ſearch you the Prophets, and ſee what was</hi> promiſed, <hi>and alſo</hi> anſwer me: <hi>When the Serpents head is</hi> bruiſed, <hi>is not Man as he was in the day that he was created, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:33625:23"/>Que. 23. <hi>What is <hi>Salvation</hi> and <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> and <hi>Reſtauration,</hi> and from</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and unto</hi> what, <hi>and</hi> when?</p>
            <p>Que. 24. <hi>Whether the <hi>evil works</hi> all men, is not Teſtimony of the <hi>falſe fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of all ſuch men? And if</hi> Adam <hi>for</hi> one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>loſt ſo glorious an Eſtate, How think you wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> your</hi> ſo many ſins <hi>ſhall you be made Inheri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tors of his firſt ſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 25. <hi>Whether can any of you juſt ſay,</hi> That Chriſt is the end of the Law f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Righteouſneſs unto you, <hi>who never came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the beginning of the Righteouſneſs thereof Did Chriſt come to</hi> deſtroy <hi>the Law, or</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fulfil <hi>the Law? Do you believe</hi> Paul's <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtimony of</hi> Chriſt <hi>(in whom he was reveale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> who therefore teſtified) That</hi> the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs of the Law might be fulfilled in them that walk nor after the <hi>fleſh,</hi> but after the <hi>Spirit? <hi>And, whether is any one of you, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> entred into the Spirit, yea or nay?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 26. <hi>Is any <hi>one</hi> or <hi>more</hi> of you</hi> truly in the Faith <hi>to witneſs unto</hi> John's <hi>Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who ſaid,</hi> As Chriſt is, ſo are we in this preſent world; <hi>and whether were they the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in ſin, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 27. <hi>Whether did not Chriſt</hi> rebuke Hypocrites, <hi>when he ſaid,</hi> Why call you me,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33625:23"/>
               <hi>Lord,</hi> and do not the things which I ſay? <hi>And, Did not Chriſt ſay unto his Diſbiples,</hi> Be ye <hi>perfect,</hi> as your Father which is in Heaven is <hi>perfect? <hi>And, Whether do you think that he was an unequal Lord, and his Commandments grievous, which could not be born, yea or nay?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 28. <hi>What are the <hi>Clouds,</hi> and the <hi>time of the Night,</hi> and the <hi>cauſe</hi>
               </hi> of the <hi>Darkneſs, Blindneſs <hi>and</hi> Ignorance? <hi>And what are the</hi> Vails <hi>which cover the</hi> Heart, <hi>and the</hi> underſtanding part? <hi>And how is the</hi>
               </hi> World <hi>ſet in</hi> man's heart, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by man cannot find out the Work which GOD maketh, from the beginning to the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 29. <hi>What is that which</hi> removes the <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> breaks thorow the <hi>Clouds,</hi> rents <hi>the <hi>Vails,</hi> and</hi> drives <hi>back the</hi> miſt <hi>and</hi> thickneſs <hi>of the <hi>Night?</hi> And, whether is not <hi>that</hi> which is the</hi> Cauſe, <hi>and that which removes the</hi> Cauſe, <hi>theſe</hi> two <hi>ſtill the ſame ſince the Fall, unto this day of man's remaining under the Curſe in the Fall? And whether any thing redeems out of the</hi> Curſe, <hi>but that which redeems out of the</hi> Fall? <hi>and is not</hi> every ſinner <hi>in the</hi> Fall, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 30. <hi>What is</hi> that <hi>which takes away
<pb facs="tcp:33625:24"/>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:33625:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:33625:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:33625:26"/>
the <hi>Original</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>Sin? <hi>and if the</hi>
               </hi> Original <hi>which is the</hi> root <hi>and</hi> off-ſpring, <hi>be take away, the</hi> root <hi>not left in</hi> ground, <hi>how ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> a</hi> branch <hi>grow, or</hi> fruit <hi>be brought forth GOD ſaith,</hi> the ſoul that ſinneth ſhall die <hi>And, Whether do you otherwiſe believe,</hi> Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> if you live in ſin until death, <hi>but you ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> receive (as</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith) the</hi> wages <hi>of</hi> ſin, <hi>whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> is</hi> death, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things are but that, which ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> lead unto an entrance of ſomewhat mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to follow, which I offer (as hereby directe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Substance</hi>) to all ſuch as deſire to know the <hi>new birth;</hi> And when the <hi>Learne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> have <hi>anſwered</hi> them, as the liberty of <hi>Pen, Ink</hi> and <hi>Paper</hi> is afforded me, I may <hi>expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> your <hi>Replications,</hi> and ſhew the <hi>groun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> thereof, and withall try, if the <hi>key</hi> of the underſtanding all <hi>Myſteries</hi> is among you, which <hi>is</hi> in the Church of Chriſt, and any thing concerning the Kingdom of God; Call your <hi>Councils</hi> together, I am an <hi>alone Child;</hi> propound your <hi>Queries,</hi> and let me <hi>anſwer</hi> them; for in <hi>GOD</hi> is my truſt, and not in <hi>ſelf,</hi> who am his <hi>Servant,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the Inquiſition-Priſon in</hi> Rome.</dateline>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:33625:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THe <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> this day ſtands in the Doctrine of <hi>Christ.</hi> They are <hi>in</hi> the <hi>Life</hi> which cannot <hi>recompence</hi> unto any man <hi>evil</hi> for <hi>evil,</hi> but <hi>good</hi> for <hi>evil:</hi> but you I find <hi>recompencing evil</hi> for <hi>good,</hi> which is contrary to all <hi>good.</hi> You are in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and practice of the <hi>Scribes, Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> which Chriſt cryed Wo againſt; You call men <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Maſters,</hi> and are called of men <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Masters;</hi> You love <hi>Greetings</hi> and <hi>Salutations</hi> in the <hi>Market-places,</hi> and in theſe things love to be <hi>ſeen of men;</hi> And you are in the delight of the <hi>uppermoſt Rooms</hi> and <hi>Places</hi> at <hi>Feaſts,</hi> and love the <hi>honour</hi> which comes <hi>from men:</hi> All which is contrary to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Christ:</hi> But the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> ſpeaks not more of <hi>Christ,</hi> than as they <hi>live</hi> and <hi>walk</hi> in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Number over your <hi>Traditions,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>them</hi> with what <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>holy Apoſtles</hi> delivered, that you may ſee in how much you are <hi>ſhort</hi> on the <hi>one hand,</hi> and in how much you have ſpun a thrid beyond the <hi>ſtaple</hi> on the <hi>other,</hi> that you may ſee how you have loſt the <hi>end,</hi> your line not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33625:27"/>
leading to <hi>Perfection,</hi> nor your life <hi>out of ſin</hi> and <hi>corruption; Preach, write</hi> and <hi>ſpeak</hi> to the end of your dayes and time, you ſhall never <hi>beget,</hi> but by your <hi>own ſeed</hi> none other <hi>likeneſs,</hi> but of your <hi>own nature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> You may come as far as the <hi>ſhadow, ſhell,</hi> and <hi>husk;</hi> You may have the <hi>words,</hi> but your <hi>nature</hi> cannot receive the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Power;</hi> the <hi>Croſſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is the <hi>Power of GOD to Salvation,</hi> is too hard a thing for you to bear: You have the <hi>Image</hi> which is the <hi>loſs</hi> of the <hi>Subſtance;</hi> for where <hi>CHRIST,</hi> who is the <hi>Subſtance,</hi> is come, there the <hi>end</hi> is come, unto all <hi>Shadows, Types</hi> and <hi>Figures,</hi> which <hi>ſhadowed</hi> and <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured</hi> out the <hi>Subſtance</hi> before it came.</p>
            <p>Concerning Opinions, I blow over them all as Chaff, in as many as are in diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, lyes, hypocriſie, ſwearing or curſed ſpeaking. <hi>Repent, God's day is at hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Rome, <hi>dispenſed from the Inquiſition-Priſon.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>I Could ſay many things unto you, but you are not able to bear a little (as the Prieſt concerning the Prophet complained,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33625:27"/>
ſaying, <hi>The Land is not able to bear all his words</hi>) you being not yet come unto the <hi>Charity</hi> (which is in the Church of Chriſt) which can <hi>bear all things,</hi> and <hi>endure all things;</hi> Wherefore at preſent I <hi>query</hi> a little further; expecting firſt an <hi>Anſwer</hi> of the former, and after that, of <hi>theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concerning the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Query 1. <hi>What is the <hi>loſt groat,</hi> and the ſweeping of the houſe</hi> to find it? <hi>And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have you</hi> found it, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 2. <hi>What is <hi>a Virgin's-ſtate,</hi> and, are you</hi> in it? <hi>and, In which of the</hi> two, <hi>the</hi> wiſe <hi>or the</hi> fooliſh? <hi>What is <hi>the Lamp,</hi> and <hi>the Oyl in the Lamp,</hi> and do you</hi> poſſeſs it, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 3. <hi>Whether is not the</hi> Kingdom of Heaven <hi>as really <hi>in you,</hi> as it was in the</hi> Scribes <hi>and</hi> Phariſees? <hi>And, whether are you</hi> in the Kingdom, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 4. <hi>Whether is any one of you</hi> a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Prophet <hi>than</hi> John Baptiſt, <hi>who was the greateſt Prophet born of Women, which went before him; ſeeing he that is leaſt</hi> in the Kingdom, <hi>is greater than he?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 5. <hi>If not <hi>one of you</hi> be in the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33625:28"/>
                  <hi>Kingdom of God;</hi> Are not <hi>all</hi>
               </hi> in the <hi>kingdom of Satan; <hi>which are not</hi>
               </hi> in the Kingdom of God, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 6. <hi>What is the <hi>firſt Principle</hi> which leads to the</hi> underſtanding <hi>and</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>of the</hi> Oracles of GOD? <hi>And, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are you</hi> in it, <hi>and doth your life</hi> anſwer it, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 7. <hi>What is <hi>the Key of David,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> who keeps it, <hi>and whether is any thing</hi> open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>or</hi> ſhut <hi>in</hi> Heaven <hi>or in</hi> Earth <hi>without it yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 8. <hi>What is <hi>the Book which is ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſeven Seals,</hi> and what are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Seals thereon <hi>which</hi> John <hi>ſaid</hi> no man i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Heaven, nor in Earth, was found worth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to open? <hi>Whether was</hi> Peter <hi>then in</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>or in</hi> Earth, <hi>or neither in</hi> Heaven <hi>nor</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Earth? <hi>And, whether any</hi> now <hi>in your day is found</hi> worthy <hi>in</hi> Earth <hi>to do</hi> that, <hi>which</hi> John <hi>in the</hi> Lord's day <hi>ſaw</hi> no man <hi>in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or Earth</hi> was found worthy to do, <hi>ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 9. <hi>VVhether is not <hi>the Priſon</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Priſon-houſe,</hi> the</hi> ſeat of Sin, <hi>and</hi> habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Corruption? <hi>Or, Is</hi> darkneſs <hi>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the</hi> ſhadow of death <hi>the</hi> Purgation from Sin, <hi>for the</hi> Redemption <hi>out of</hi> Death? <hi>Do
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33625:28"/>
you not know that the Seed is</hi> in Priſon <hi>under the Clouds of</hi> darkneſs, <hi>through</hi> Sin <hi>and</hi> Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, <hi>in each one of you, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 10. <hi>VVhether have you <hi>Salt</hi> and <hi>Savour</hi>
               </hi> in your ſelves? <hi>If you know not that it is</hi> in you, <hi>are you otherwiſe</hi> fit <hi>but to be</hi> caſt out <hi>and</hi> trodden under foot <hi>of men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 11. <hi>VVhat are the <hi>two Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> of whom it was ſaid,</hi> That they ſhould again propheſie? <hi>Whether are they not yet</hi> come, <hi>or, how know you but they</hi> be come?</p>
            <p>Que. 12. <hi>VVhether is</hi> the Creation <hi>of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>anew unto you in</hi> Rome, <hi>in the old Age of your ſins, which the</hi> Hebrews <hi>ſhall enter</hi> into, <hi>according to</hi> Iſaiah's Prophecy, <hi>and which the</hi> Saints <hi>of the</hi> Moſt High <hi>are now</hi> entred into, <hi>according to</hi> John's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, <hi>where nothing that</hi> defiles <hi>can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? And, whether is</hi> this <hi>any other than that which the Apoſtle ſaid,</hi> the Hebrews <hi>were entred into, who were come</hi> unto the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Prophecy</hi> is become unto all (ſaith <hi>Iſaiah</hi>) as <hi>a Book that is ſealed.</hi> Friends, ſpur up your <hi>Colledges</hi> to <hi>anſwer me;</hi> For, if once your <hi>Chariot wheels</hi> are <hi>clogged</hi> in the ſand, and your <hi>Hoſt troubled,</hi> know, that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33625:29"/>
               <hi>Judgment is nigh,</hi> and the <hi>Floods</hi> will ſoon <hi>cloſe</hi> and <hi>joyn hands</hi> over your heads.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dispenſed from the Inquiſition-Priſon in</hi> Rome.</dateline>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>THat which is done <hi>in ſecret,</hi> ſhall be <hi>preached</hi> upon the <hi>houſe top;</hi> For the Bed is <hi>too ſhort,</hi> the Covering is <hi>too narrow,</hi> the Nakedneſs <hi>is ſeen;</hi> ſtrip off the <hi>Fig-leaves,</hi> they hide not; the Line <hi>is ſtretched,</hi> but yet the Stone <hi>is ſealed.</hi> Nevertheleſs, if you will <hi>come forth, <hi>come forth;</hi>
               </hi> if you will <hi>enter, <hi>enter; come</hi>
               </hi> and be as a <hi>Roe</hi> and <hi>Hart</hi> upon the Mountains, to <hi>run</hi> and <hi>read me,</hi> to grow to the underſtanding of a <hi>Proverb,</hi> and the <hi>Interpretation</hi> thereof; the words of the <hi>Wiſe,</hi> and their <hi>dark ſayings:</hi> For behold, <hi>there cometh a Nation of a deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſpeech than ye can perceive, of a ſtammer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tongue, that you cannot understand; they ſhall break over Walls, and climb upon the tops of Houſes, and enter in at the Windows of the Cloſets; A fiercer People hath not been,</hi> ſaith the Spirit of the Prophet.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:33625:29"/>
               <hi>The Trumpet of the Lord of Hoſts is ſounding the Alarm; his dreadful day is at hand; the dead in Chriſt have heard, and are partakers of the firſt Reſurrection: <hi>He that hath an Ear to hear, let him hear, and Repent.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Rome, <hi>diſpenſed from the Inquiſition-Priſon.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the Pope, and Governour, and the reſt ruling in the City of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN your places it is neceſſary, that you <hi>conſider</hi> that which is indeed above all things <hi>honourable.</hi> I crave not the <hi>break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off</hi> the yoke of my <hi>bonds</hi> at your hands, as being aſſured, that your hands were bound of the Lord, thus far unto my Impriſonment, that you by the means thereof might have knowledge how you are <hi>bound</hi> with the <hi>Chain of Satan,</hi> under the <hi>Curſe</hi> through <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Tranſgreſſion;</hi> the <hi>LIGHT</hi> being <hi>come, declared</hi> and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33625:30"/>
               <hi>teſtified</hi> unto you; henceforth you have no more <hi>cloak</hi> for your <hi>ſin.</hi> This I deſire, not <hi>of you,</hi> but concerning you <hi>of Him,</hi> which <hi>openeth,</hi> and no man <hi>ſhutteth,</hi> that the Priſoner <hi>in you,</hi> in the Priſon-houſe <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,</hi> which ſits in <hi>darkneſs,</hi> under the ſhadow of death, may be ſet <hi>at liberty,</hi> and <hi>come forth</hi> with the <hi>high praiſe of GOD</hi> in his mouth; This I offer unto you, that I migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> know either by your <hi>willing,</hi> or <hi>nilling,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you <hi>exceed,</hi> or <hi>fall ſhort</hi> of the <hi>Nobility</hi> of the <hi>Bereans,</hi> who ſearched <hi>the Scriptures</hi> to know the truth of the matter; and the <hi>Athenians</hi> in hearing <hi>Paul,</hi> though firſt they called him <hi>babler?</hi> either to let your <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges</hi> give me a <hi>Publick Diſpute,</hi> or to give me a <hi>Meeting</hi> by way of <hi>audience,</hi> of the <hi>Ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance</hi> which GOD may give me; or at leaſt, to provoke them to <hi>anſwer</hi> the 31, and the 12 other laſt <hi>Queries,</hi> which I gave forth of this Priſon, elſe you may be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as truly as I know, although all the former were granted, that <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>prick</hi> which was <hi>too hard</hi> for <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>kick againſt,</hi> and ſo is <hi>now</hi> unto <hi>all Nations, you,</hi> as well as <hi>others;</hi> But of a truth I tell you, though you may ſay that <hi>you will not hear,</hi> the next Generation <hi>ſhall preach my Teſtimony in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33625:30"/>
the Streets,</hi> and <hi>not withhold their Cry in the Gates of the High places.</hi> And this is the <hi>Word of the Lord God</hi> to you all.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the Inquiſition-Priſon in</hi> Rome.</dateline>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To <hi>Fabius Guiſius</hi> Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Fabius Guiſius,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe <hi>Outſtretched Arm,</hi> and exerciſe of the <hi>Hand</hi> of <hi>Cruelty</hi> unto <hi>Death,</hi> is not able to make me to daub a <hi>dirty Wall</hi> with <hi>untempered Mortar.</hi> The impudent <hi>wicked carriages</hi> of the <hi>Prieſts Instruments</hi> under thee, which are ſet <hi>to watch over me,</hi> do not in the leaſt <hi>move me,</hi> ſave only to <hi>tell thee,</hi> therein they are not an <hi>honour</hi> unto thee; but on them I may not altogether lay the weight of the matter, as knowing, that they are but as <hi>ſaudred Pipes of Lead,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the <hi>Vent</hi> and <hi>running forth</hi> of the ſtinking corrupted <hi>waters,</hi> of the <hi>Priests malice, wrath</hi> and <hi>envy,</hi> foraſmuch as the <hi>Truth</hi> hath <hi>reproved</hi> their <hi>Iniquity;</hi> And as for the others, they are not worth the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33625:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
naming. But as touching <hi>thy Prieſts,</hi> ſome I have found in <hi>ſwearing,</hi> others in <hi>lying</hi> and <hi>diſſembling, flatteries</hi> and <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> which all are ſheltred under the ſhadow of thy skirt.</p>
            <p>Now conſider what thy Power doth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, a <hi>Lyar</hi> and <hi>a Priest,</hi> a <hi>Priest</hi> and a <hi>Lyar;</hi> a <hi>Diſſembler,</hi> a <hi>Flatterer,</hi> a <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite,</hi> and a <hi>Prieſt.</hi> Doth thy Law preſerve <hi>ſuch</hi> in <hi>liberty</hi> and <hi>out of Priſon</hi> (who are in Death's Priſon) to <hi>watch over</hi> the <hi>Just,</hi> which cannot <hi>lye</hi> unto thee, nor <hi>diſſemble,</hi> nor <hi>flatter</hi> with thee, though <hi>in Priſon?</hi> If thou be <hi>Peter's Succeſſor,</hi> ſhew me <hi>Chriſt's Command</hi> unto him for ſuch a <hi>practice?</hi> elſe be thou <hi>aſhamed</hi> of it, and deny <hi>thy Prieſts</hi> in their <hi>wicked practices:</hi> For <hi>Truth</hi> is aſhamed of all <hi>rottenneſs</hi> and <hi>wickedneſs, deceit, lyes,</hi> and <hi>corruption;</hi> but it is not <hi>aſhamed</hi> to ſtand before thy face, neither doth it <hi>fear</hi> the frowns of all the <hi>wicked Powers</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of the whole Earth; but in <hi>Priſons, Perſecutions, Tortures, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments,</hi> or <hi>Death,</hi> it ſtands over them <hi>all,</hi> and rejoyceth over them <hi>all,</hi> and treads upon the head of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> which ſeeks to bring to paſſe his vain imagination <hi>in</hi> or <hi>by</hi> them all. Wherefore I would not that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33625:31"/>
thou ſhouldſt be a <hi>Fool,</hi> to ſit in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of the number of the <hi>Crafty</hi> and <hi>VViſe;</hi> but rather <hi>be wiſe,</hi> and bow to the innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>Fools,</hi> and then thou wilt diſcover the ground of the works of the others mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Now let me reaſon with thee concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>my Impriſonment,</hi> which if thou an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereſt <hi>Nay;</hi> ſaying, <hi>VVe have it under thy Hand, and it is enough unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I reply, It's true, I have given under my hand the Declaration of a <hi>VVitneſs</hi> and <hi>Teſtimony for GOD</hi> againſt <hi>Iniquity;</hi> for which <hi>cauſe,</hi> if God hath <hi>foreſeen it,</hi> that the periſhing of this <hi>Tabernacle</hi> under thy Bonds of <hi>Cruelty</hi> ſhall be my <hi>Crown,</hi> when the day comes that <hi>Inquiſition</hi> ſhal be made after my <hi>innocent blood,</hi> let this, with the reſt, be produced, that the Action may be openly <hi>remonſtrated. <hi>Truth, Honeſty,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Wiſdom</hi> would <hi>implead, act, judge,</hi> and <hi>execute</hi> the Judgment of the Law of God, in <hi>Form, Manner</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> and to the <hi>proper end</hi> that it was given forth; and not in blind <hi>holes</hi> and <hi>corners,</hi> and dark <hi>Cells,</hi> as are wrought the works and deeds of the Devil; but <hi>openly</hi> and <hi>manifeſtly</hi> unto, and <hi>before all,</hi> as in the Righteouſneſs of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33625:32"/>
               <hi>Him,</hi> which rippeth open the <hi>ſecrets</hi> of <hi>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> hearts,</hi> and bringeth <hi>every man's actions to be diſcovered by the Light,</hi> in which the <hi>Magiſtrate, Judge</hi> and <hi>Ruler,</hi> which <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> and <hi>ruleth for GOD,</hi> ſtandeth in the honour of the <hi>true Dominion,</hi> a Praiſe unto the living GOD, and <hi>openly</hi> to the Glory of GOD, <hi>reigneth</hi> in the <hi>Righteouſneſs of GOD,</hi> in dealing and executing his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>juſt Judgment,</hi> through the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincement</hi> of the <hi>Tranſgreſſor, openly</hi> by the Law; and ſo he ſtands <hi>a terror to evil-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and <hi>a praiſe to them that do well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I have written, or ſpoken <hi>any thing,</hi> which I cannot ſufficiently <hi>prove (openly</hi> in the Court of Juſtice, where Truth reigns) to that of GOD <hi>in every man's Conſcience,</hi> then (as I have ſaid) as the Law of GOD was given forth for <hi>due</hi> and <hi>publick im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleading</hi> and <hi>execution,</hi> through open Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincement) let me bear the <hi>everlaſting open ſhame,</hi> and ſpare not by due <hi>puniſhment,</hi> to make me a <hi>publick Example</hi> in the face of this Nation, as a ſlanderer.</p>
            <p>For again, I ſay, I delight in the <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> of the Righteouſneſs of <hi>true Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but if thou wilt not in Equity <hi>hear this,</hi> Then hear thou moreover <hi>the VVord
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33625:32"/>
of the LORD GOD;</hi> GOD by the execution of his Juſtice upon thee, will ſhorten thy dayes upon the face of the Earth, and give thee for an example of his Wrath before men. <hi>Therefore whilſt thou haſt time, Repent.</hi> This is the day of thy Viſitation.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as at ſeveral times I have given forth <hi>Fourty two Queries,</hi> or more, to be <hi>anſwered</hi> by the Members of the Colledges in <hi>Rome,</hi> or others; And having ſufficiently expected, foraſmuch as conſiderable time ſince that hath paſſed away, which in leſſe time, yea, much leſs, Truth would have anſwered ſo plain a matter; but having not received anſwer from any of them, I now <hi>query</hi> to thee, who art reputed as the <hi>Angel</hi> over them, as him which hath the <hi>Keys of the Kingdom,</hi> which I would firſt try (becauſe of the diverſity of Voices in the Earth, crying, <hi>Lo here,</hi> and <hi>lo there</hi>) and in ſpirit be convinced of the ſame, before I would (as a fooliſh raſh hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite) confe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s without knowledge or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; as knowing that when Truth hath convinced, the mouth of the Gain-ſayer is ſtopped, and that of God in the Conſcience is anſwered, and the meaſure
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33625:33"/>
of the Manifeſtation of the Spirit of Tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> beareth witneſs <hi>within</hi> unto the Truth, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> which all are left without excuſe; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> therefore in thy thoughts, by thy Anſwers leave me without excuſe; or elſe know That hereby thou art left (even as all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> reſt that will not anſwer Truth, for Trut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and the Lord's ſake, are) without excuſe.</p>
            <p>Query 1. <hi>What is the <hi>Goſpel of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>the Light of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> glorious Goſpel,</hi> which giveth the Ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of the Knowledge of the Glory of GOD in the face of Jeſus Chriſt? <hi>And, what i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the everlaſting Goſpel of God,</hi>
               </hi> which ſhall be preached to all Nations of the Earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>And, whether hast thou</hi> immediate Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from God, <hi>to ſend forth any</hi> to preach it; <hi>or, if knowing what the Gospel is, Is it any thing leſſe</hi> than thy duty to go forth and preach it, <hi>yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 2. <hi>What is that <hi>flaming Sword</hi> which is ſet at</hi> Edens <hi>Gate, to keep the Way of the Tree of Life, that not any in the ſtate of</hi> Tranſgreſſion, <hi>and nature of</hi> Corruption <hi>may taſte thereof; which he that eateth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in this Life, ſhall periſh unto everlaſting Death, at the end of his Life? And declare,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33625:33"/>
whether there is no</hi> difference, <hi>or, what is the</hi> difference <hi>in the</hi> nature, ground, <hi>and</hi> ſubſtance <hi>between that</hi> Sword, <hi>the</hi> Blood <hi>of the</hi> Lamb, <hi>the</hi> Croſſe of Chriſt, Purgatory, <hi>and the</hi> Fountain which is ſet open for <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to bath and to waſh in?</p>
            <p>Que. 3. <hi>Whether they who have bathed</hi> in the Fountain of God, <hi>and waſhed</hi> in the Blood of the Lamb, <hi>that have born</hi> the Croſs of Chriſt, <hi>unto the</hi> crucifying <hi>of the</hi> nature of the Corruptible <hi>and</hi> Mortal, <hi>and that have paſſed thorow the</hi> flaming Sword, <hi>ſhall enter into any other</hi> Purgatory? <hi>And what did</hi> Enoch <hi>paſſe thorow, to attain to the perfection of living and walking with God? And, whether was, or is Salvation more than</hi> one <hi>ſince the Fall; ſeeing the matter thereof is but</hi> one, <hi>and God the <hi>All,</hi> but</hi> one, <hi>and his Promiſe</hi> one, <hi>and unchangeable to ſave out of the Fall, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 4. <hi>Whether did Chriſt come to work</hi> Salvation for Souls, <hi>through</hi> the impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Juſt, <hi>or</hi> captivating Souls; <hi>ſeeing the Scriptures ſay, that</hi> he came to open the Priſon doors, and to bring forth the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner? <hi>How may it honeſtly be ſaid that thou art</hi> Peter's Succeſſor, <hi>in the Truth, or the</hi> Vicegerent of Chriſt; <hi>who contrary to the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33625:34"/>
end of the Coming of Chriſt, the Life, Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice and Example of Chriſt, dost</hi> profeſs <hi>and</hi> practiſe <hi>that which brings</hi> diſhonour <hi>to the</hi> Name <hi>of CHRIST? And, anſwer, By what wouldſt thou have me to know a</hi> Vine branch <hi>from a</hi> Thorn-tree?</p>
            <p>Que. 5. <hi>VVhether is</hi> thy Nation <hi>grow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in</hi> Righteouſneſs <hi>unto the Age of the Beaut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of</hi> Holineſs? <hi>or, Are they even</hi> ripe <hi>unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Judgment, <hi>in the multitude of</hi> their Oaths Curſes <hi>and</hi> Blaſphemies, Pride, Whore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doms <hi>and</hi> Adulteries, Lyes, Envy <hi>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Hypocriſies, <hi>in the full growth of all manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of</hi> Abominations <hi>and</hi> Iniquity? <hi>Canſt tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſhew me</hi> one Member <hi>of thy whole Bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> which now is as</hi> Nehemiah <hi>the Captain of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Lord's People, and as</hi> Nathaniel, <hi>the</hi> tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Iſraelite, <hi>was, that I may have</hi> unity wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> him? <hi>elſe,</hi> who, what, <hi>and</hi> where <hi>thinkest thou is the Church of</hi> Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Que. 6. <hi>Whether, and in what</hi> manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>haſt thou paſſed from under the</hi> Reign <hi>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Dominion <hi>of</hi> Death, <hi>unto</hi> Moſes's houſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>And, ſhew me the</hi> teſtimony <hi>of thy</hi> Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>in his houſe, and the</hi> ſeal <hi>of thy</hi> paſſage <hi>thorow his houſe into the way of the</hi> Prophet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> life, <hi>and the</hi> mark <hi>of the</hi> way, <hi>and</hi> ſignet <hi>of the</hi> Prophets life <hi>leading to</hi> John Baptiſt's
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33625:34"/>
cry <hi>in the</hi> Wilderneſs, <hi>and the</hi> Record <hi>of his</hi> Baptiſm <hi>to be of God</hi> in thee; <hi>and how thou haſt been emptied from</hi> Veſſel <hi>to</hi> Veſſel, <hi>unto the perfect loſſe of the</hi> ſcent <hi>of the</hi> old lees? <hi>which if thou canſt not ſhew me the true effect of this work in thy life, whether in thy beſt profeſſion of all the writings of thy dead fathers, and the confeſſion of the Scriptures of the holy Prophets and Apoſtles, Art thou any other than (as</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith) a boaſter in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man's line, made ready to thy hand, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 7. <hi>Whether haſt thou the</hi> true Eye of diſcerning, <hi>to trace the way of</hi> a Serpent <hi>over a</hi> Rock? <hi>Doſt thou know the</hi> courſe <hi>of a</hi> Dolphin <hi>in the</hi> Deeps, <hi>or the</hi> path <hi>of a</hi> young Dolphin <hi>in the</hi> ſhallow Waters? <hi>And, by what</hi> line <hi>wouldſt thou meaſure</hi> their way? <hi>And, with what</hi> Inſtrument <hi>canſt thou meaſure the path of the</hi> firſt flight <hi>of a</hi> young Dove <hi>thorow the Air and ſhadow of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens? If thou knoweſt not this, how knoweſt thou to take the Wings of the Morning, to meet the Sun in the South, to be at reſt with the Children of the Day,</hi> where the light of the Moon is as the light of the Sun, and the light of the Sun as the light of ſeven dayes, the everlaſting Sabbath of God?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:33625:35"/>Anſwer theſe with the Life of Truth, if thou wilt have me believe that thou art <hi>Peter's Succeſſor</hi> in the true Faith; But wherein thou art <hi>unable,</hi> honeſtly <hi>confeſs it,</hi> hear me, and <hi>come out of Priſon</hi> and I will inſtruct thee in the way of God more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly. Let all thy men of Learning take heed of high obſtinate perverſe wills and froward hearts; And take you all heed, leſt a root of bitterneſs, and ſpirit of envy be in you; and learn this, Where-ever you ſee a <hi>perſecuting ſpirit,</hi> know alwayes <hi>that that ſpirit is not of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Rome, <hi>given forth of the Inquiſition-Priſon.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>TO all in <hi>ROME,</hi> from the <hi>highest</hi> to the <hi>lowest,</hi> that are ſetled <hi>in ſin,</hi> and will not hear to come out of the way and nature <hi>thereof,</hi> who walk in the path of <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> in the love of <hi>Tranſgreſſion,</hi> and ſay in your hearts, <hi>Who is of God that we ſhould hear him?</hi> whoſe liberty is in the <hi>luſt</hi> and <hi>pleaſure,</hi> in <hi>perſecuting the Juſt,</hi> walking in the <hi>broad way,</hi> which leads <hi>to endleſs deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:33625:35"/>
under the ſeal of <hi>everlaſting wrath;</hi> and will not hear to know and enter into the <hi>ſtrait path of life,</hi> in which <hi>the way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring men, though fools, cannot erre therein;</hi> And in your hardneſs againſt GOD you think that you are <hi>above all men,</hi> wiſe in your <hi>ſinful wayes;</hi> you are wiſe <hi>unto evil,</hi> but not in <hi>the good</hi> which cometh <hi>from God;</hi> who will not hear, to be turned from <hi>all evil;</hi> but ſhut <hi>your eyes,</hi> and ſtop <hi>your ears,</hi> and make <hi>Vows</hi> as <hi>ſealed Bonds</hi> together, crying, <hi>Away with it, Away with it, We will have none of it;</hi> not conſidering the dayes of old, how the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> came accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Prophets,</hi> yet <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Jews expectations,</hi> and in croſs to all their <hi>Luſts</hi> and <hi>Inquities;</hi> Wherefore they took counſel of their own <hi>Wills,</hi> and <hi>ſlew Him.</hi> And now I do but in the <hi>Subſtance</hi> teſtifie unto you, That <hi>CHRIST</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> is <hi>come</hi> and <hi>coming</hi> (according to the Apoſtles Teſtimony of Him) <hi>the ſecond time without ſin unto Salvation,</hi> which is <hi>contrary</hi> to your <hi>Expectations,</hi> under the blackneſs and darkneſs of the clouds of <hi>your ſins</hi> and <hi>tranſgreſſions,</hi> under which you cry, <hi>We will not, We will not;</hi> And every man in his hardneſs utters his ſentence
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33625:36"/>
ſaying, <hi>Perſecute, perſecute, Impriſon, im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>priſon;</hi> as it was in all Ages, <hi>He that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> born after the Spirit, even ſo it is now;</hi> and thus rendring <hi>evil</hi> for <hi>good,</hi> you plat the Crown of the Thorns of the cruelty of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> hearts upon the head of the <hi>Innocent</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This therefore is your <hi>Condemnation LIGHT is come into the World; but ye ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the Light, and love Darkneſs rather tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Light, becauſe your deeds are evil:</hi> For who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoever loves the <hi>LIGHT,</hi> brings his deed to the <hi>LIGHT,</hi> that by the <hi>LIGHT</hi> the may be made <hi>manifeſt.</hi> The LIGHT is all your Conſciences is your <hi>Condemnation</hi> within, who hate the <hi>Light,</hi> and will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> come to the <hi>Light,</hi> by the <hi>Light</hi> which <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vinceth of ſin,</hi> to be led out of <hi>all ſin:</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rily I ſay unto you, neither <hi>Wit, Craft</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Guile,</hi> the <hi>Horſe</hi> nor his <hi>Rider, Sword, Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> nor <hi>Battle,</hi> nor <hi>Angels,</hi> nor any othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>creatures,</hi> but the <hi>Light</hi> (which you hate and perſecute the Witneſs of it) ſhall <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver</hi> in the day of <hi>Wrath</hi> which is <hi>near you</hi> And this is the <hi>Word of the LORD GOD to you all,</hi> Remember you are <hi>warned</hi> Therefore whilſt you have time, <hi>Repent</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:33625:36"/>
and henceforth blot out the <hi>vain imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of your minds, and let it be written upon the table of your hearts. If God's <hi>Everlaſting Covenant</hi> be <hi>changeable,</hi> then may our <hi>cruelty</hi> change them from the Lord their God.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given forth in fear and trembling, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the God of all dreadful Power.
<hi>From the Inquiſition-Priſon in</hi> Rome.</dateline>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>THeſe are to this blind-hearted Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which are <hi>ſmooth</hi> to the <hi>rough,</hi> and <hi>rough</hi> to the <hi>ſmooth;</hi> and cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the <hi>rough</hi> from the <hi>ſmooth,</hi> the <hi>crooked</hi> from the <hi>ſtreight,</hi> the <hi>right</hi> from the <hi>left;</hi> Your <hi>love,</hi> the love of the everlaſting Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holdeth in an <hi>irreconcileable hatred;</hi> for ye love the <hi>ſmooth words</hi> of the <hi>men</hi> of this world, which ſtand in the <hi>rough places of the Earth;</hi> Ye love <hi>their Titles, Daubings, Flatteries, Diſſimulations</hi> and <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſies,</hi> and your ſelves <hi>ſmooth</hi> in the ſame nature, unto this their nature of <hi>roughneſs;</hi> But ye are <hi>rough</hi> to the <hi>ſmooth,</hi> which deal with you <hi>in honeſty</hi> and <hi>plaineſs,</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:33625:37"/>
which are not <hi>ſmooth</hi> to your <hi>rough nature</hi> of <hi>diſſimulations;</hi> Wherefore you are <hi>rough</hi> in your <hi>conſultations, ſecret reports</hi> and <hi>acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and bend your ſelves in <hi>crookedneſs,</hi> againſt the <hi>ſtreightneſs</hi> of the <hi>ſmooth things of Gods Kingdom;</hi> Your <hi>hatred</hi> the <hi>LORD despiſeth,</hi> even as your <hi>love</hi> he <hi>hateth;</hi> For the thing which you <hi>hate,</hi> is the ſeal of the <hi>love</hi> of the <hi>Father,</hi> to be holden in love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>death,</hi> as a teſtimony againſt the <hi>rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>crookedneſs</hi> both of the <hi>love</hi> and <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred</hi> of your <hi>Life;</hi> you love not to come unto the <hi>ſmooth ſtone</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> which ſank into the forehead of the <hi>Philiſtine;</hi> The <hi>Philiſtine</hi> liveth <hi>in you,</hi> and <hi>curſeth</hi> the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the <hi>GOD</hi> of <hi>David;</hi> he ſpake <hi>roughly</hi> to the <hi>ſmooth thing</hi> in the Stripling; but the <hi>ſmooth</hi> did ſmite his <hi>roughneſs:</hi> even ſo muſt it be by the Philiſtine <hi>in you,</hi> ere the GOD of <hi>David</hi> be known, to be God among you. And this is to you all, that the <hi>ſmooth,</hi> which is <hi>rough</hi> to the <hi>ſmooth thing</hi> of God, may dye <hi>in you,</hi> that the Lord's <hi>ſmooth thing</hi> may live, in domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over the <hi>rough things</hi> of the Earth.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Rome, <hi>dispenſed from the Inquiſition-Priſon.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:33625:37"/>
            <head>To a <hi>Franciſcan</hi> of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Convent in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Iriſh Prieſt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou haſt deſired ſomething from me, that thou mayeſt anſwer it; And I hereby propoſing, let thy <hi>own words</hi> ſtand thy own <hi>obligation,</hi> to be as faithful in <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering,</hi> as thou wert forward in <hi>promiſing.</hi> I have ſometimes born witneſs unto divers of you <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the <hi>Roman Catholick Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies,</hi> manifeſtly ſhewing unto you, <hi>how that CHRIST is the LIGHT of the World, which lighteth every man that cometh into the World;</hi> and unto that <hi>LIGHT in all your Conſciences,</hi> approving my <hi>Meſſage,</hi> and the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>JESUS</hi> (which I hold in a pure Conſcience) to be of <hi>GOD,</hi> which in you all ſhall ſtand a Witneſs for me everlaſtingly unto Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though now you riſe up as falſe witneſſes againſt it; and ſo bear falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt me, and will not come unto the Light, that you may have Life; but do chuſe to your ſelves the antient path of the Serpent's way, ſetling your ſelves in the inventions of your own hearts, lurking in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33625:38"/>
the ſecret dens of craft and ſubtilty, ſtretching out your hands in the corrupted fallen, apoſtatized Policy, and ſo what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is brought forth by you, is but the birth or age of Iniquity. Divers of you have confeſſed unto me, and laſtly, as next unto this preſent time, Thou didſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <hi>that there is <hi>not one</hi> of all your Catholick Church, which is reſtored unto <hi>Innocency,</hi> or redeemed <hi>from ſin,</hi> and the <hi>daily</hi> act of tranſgreſſion;</hi> and then I ſhewed thee, if not <hi>one <hi>in Innocency,</hi>
               </hi> then <hi>all</hi> in the contrary, which is <hi>Iniquity;</hi> If <hi>all</hi> in the <hi>daily act</hi> of <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> then <hi>all</hi> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in the <hi>miry place</hi> in the <hi>apoſtatized ground,</hi> fallen from the <hi>Life</hi> of the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> who leads out of ſin.</p>
            <p>Now therefore underſtand, you who are ſetled in the obſtinacy and perverſneſs, and hardneſs of heart; Read your <hi>unbelief</hi> and the deſperate end thereof, who will not that the <hi>Devil's kingdom</hi> ſhould come to <hi>an end</hi> in you; you may have all the words of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> had <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and yet periſh in the <hi>ſame desperation,</hi> through re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to come unto Him, who is the <hi>Life;</hi> You may ſay, <hi>The Lord liveth,</hi> and yet
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33625:38"/>
therein be <hi>falſe ſwearers,</hi> as ſaid <hi>Jeremiah;</hi> You may have <hi>all tongues</hi> and <hi>many gifts,</hi> you may give <hi>all your goods</hi> to the <hi>Poor,</hi> and your <hi>bodies</hi> to be <hi>burnt,</hi> and yet want the <hi>Charity,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul:</hi> You may (as the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi>) ſhew <hi>many Signs,</hi> yea, and in the Name of <hi>CHRIST, Preach in the Streets,</hi> do many <hi>wonderful things,</hi> and <hi>caſt out Devils,</hi> and at the laſt day ſay, <hi>Lord, theſe things have we done in thy Name:</hi> But not coming unto the LIGHT and LIFE of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> which leads out <hi>of Iniquity,</hi> and to dwell in the LIGHT unto the End, above Iniquity; Unto ſuch I will profeſs unto them, <hi>I know you not, depart from me ye curſed workers of Iniquity,</hi> ſaith Chriſt: What therefore availeth your Doctrine? what alſo hath it profited any of you, in confeſſing ſo much of Truth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, ſaying that my words are <hi>true</hi> and <hi>juſt,</hi> and are as <hi>Jewels</hi> and <hi>Diadems,</hi> and <hi>Precious Stones,</hi> and ought exceedingly to be <hi>owned</hi> and <hi>honoured,</hi> Except you come to the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>Subſtance</hi> from which they were offered unto you? not that you ſhould catch at the <hi>ſhadow</hi> and <hi>ſhell,</hi> as the Hypocrites in the whole Earth, who are ſmooth in <hi>confeſſing</hi> and <hi>ſaying,</hi> but
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33625:39"/>
curſed in <hi>doing;</hi> for know ye, that it is <hi>one</hi> thing to be <hi>enlightned,</hi> and to walk <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to the <hi>Light,</hi> in ſuch the <hi>Light</hi> is their <hi>condemnation;</hi> and <hi>another</hi> thing to <hi>dwell</hi> and <hi>walk in the Light,</hi> in which God <hi>dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,</hi> in ſuch the <hi>Light</hi> is their <hi>juſtification:</hi> You may read the declaration of another man's ſtate <hi>without you,</hi> but cannot read more than your own ſtates, with a true witneſs <hi>within you;</hi> you may dream of <hi>ſweet Wine,</hi> but be awakened unto a potion of <hi>Wormwood.</hi> There cannot be plainer proof than the Witneſs of your own <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions,</hi> to conclude your <hi>Profeſſions</hi> of God <hi>vanity;</hi> your wicked <hi>ſinful life,</hi> a ſcandal to <hi>Honeſty</hi> and all <hi>Truth,</hi> and of <hi>Christ,</hi> but an occaſion of the <hi>contempt</hi> of the <hi>reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſhame</hi> and <hi>ignomy,</hi> which ſometime paſt I have in my underſtanding read among the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Jews.</hi> Ponder theſe things, and be awakened, and in ſpirit be provoked unto <hi>Holineſs,</hi> which ſtands not in the <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful afflictions</hi> and <hi>penance,</hi> heaped upon the veſſel of the creature, Man, or by <hi>hanging down the head</hi> like a Bulruſh for a day, but by a <hi>due</hi> and <hi>diligent ſearch</hi> of the <hi>hidden man,</hi> coming unto the <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>revelation</hi> of the <hi>Indignation</hi> and <hi>Wrath</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:33625:39"/>
of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> which is ſlaughtered in the ſtreets of <hi>Myſtery Sodom,</hi> That you may come to the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the DAY of <hi>Vengeance,</hi> and the <hi>acceptable Year</hi> of the <hi>LORD;</hi> until which, the <hi>works</hi> of your <hi>wills</hi> in all your daily <hi>ſervices,</hi> are but as the offering of the <hi>ſacrifice</hi> of <hi>Cain,</hi> who killed the <hi>Just.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And furthermore, hereby I give you to underſtand, That there are but <hi>two <hi>Seeds</hi>
               </hi> known unto all in the Subſtance, <hi>two <hi>Wills,</hi> two <hi>Natures,</hi> two <hi>Spirits,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>each</hi> of <hi>them</hi> the ground and root which yeelds the fruit of <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evil</hi> in all, whether <hi>Prayers, Preaching, Plowing</hi> or <hi>Planting,</hi> even all which is brought forth <hi>within,</hi> or <hi>without,</hi> by either of them; the <hi>one,</hi> the <hi>Redemption</hi> out of the <hi>Fall,</hi> and from the <hi>ground</hi> of the <hi>firſt Apoſtacy</hi> in loſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and the <hi>Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> unto the <hi>first ſtate</hi> of <hi>Innocency;</hi> the <hi>other,</hi> the Plant of <hi>Perdition,</hi> which holds in the <hi>Captivity,</hi> even all the Profeſſors of the Name of Chriſt, who are <hi>alienated</hi> from the <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>ground</hi> of the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Apoſtacy,</hi> under which you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded your ſelves, as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>The Tree is known by the fruits;</hi> which thing well <hi>understood</hi> by you <hi>in heart,</hi> and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33625:40"/>
               <hi>owned</hi> in <hi>life,</hi> would put <hi>a ſtop</hi> to all your <hi>vanity</hi> of enquiring after <hi>more things,</hi> until firſt you have <hi>found,</hi> and do come to <hi>live</hi> in the <hi>one thing,</hi> which is <hi>only needful</hi> unto <hi>Salvation,</hi> with which all things elſe come to be poſſeſſed.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, to thee I <hi>query</hi> a little concerning your <hi>Doctrine, Practice,</hi> and <hi>Example,</hi> to be plainly and particularly <hi>anſwered</hi> in writing, by the words of the Declaration of the <hi>Doctrine, Life,</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or any of his <hi>holy Apoſtles,</hi> as written in the Record of their Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, of which ſome were given forth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Apostacy</hi> came in, and others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it fully entred and came in, prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying the full ſucceſſion thereof: What ſince them is brought forth among you, thou mayeſt omit to mention in thy <hi>Repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:</hi> for I know your ſpirit, and do alſo know what you can, and do live unto; and this (as the former to your Body) for the Truth's ſake ſimply I give forth, that if haply, thou and the reſt may come down from your Mountain into the Valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> unto the Righteouſneſs of the Judgments of the LORD of the whole Earth, who elſe with <hi>Vengeance</hi> will daſh
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33625:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
you in pieces <hi>as a Potter's Veſſel. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you are warned to prize your time, and Repent.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Query 1. <hi>Why call ye <hi>Chriſt,</hi> LORD, and do not the things which he ſaith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 2. <hi>Why delight ye Prieſts <hi>to wear long Robes,</hi> like as the</hi> Scribes <hi>and</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees?</p>
            <p>Que. 3. <hi>Why delight ye in <hi>Salutations,</hi> and <hi>Greetings</hi> in the Market-places, and love the Uppermoſt Rooms at Feaſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 4. <hi>Why love ye to be called of men <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Maſters,</hi> or to call men <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Maſters?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 5. <hi>How can ye believe in</hi> Chriſt, <hi>who ſeek the honour which comes from man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 6. <hi>Why teach ye for</hi> Doctrine <hi>the <hi>Traditions</hi> of men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 7. <hi>What</hi> Precept <hi>of CHRIST, or</hi> Preſident <hi>of the</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>have you to warrant your worſhiping before <hi>graven Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi>
               </hi> or <hi>painted Figures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 8. <hi>What</hi> Precept <hi>of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>or</hi> Preſident <hi>of the</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>have you to warrant the owning and conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſſing of more than ONE <hi>Interceſſor, Advocate,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Mediator?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:33625:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>Que. 9. <hi>By whom was it</hi> propheſied <hi>or</hi> practiſed, <hi>as in the Declaration of Truth, and Record of the Scriptures, That, beſides</hi> Prayers <hi>for all Saints in the Churches,</hi> Prayers <hi>ſhould be made unto</hi> any Saints <hi>in Heaven, ſeeing CHSIST taught,</hi> Not unto Himſelf henceforth, <hi>but</hi> only to the Father in his Name?</p>
            <p>Que. 10. <hi>VVhat</hi> Precept <hi>of CHRIST, or</hi> Preſident <hi>of the</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>have you to warrant <hi>often Repetitions,</hi> and <hi>vain Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings?</hi> and to yeeld unto God in your manner, but <hi>one Prayer</hi> of <hi>eleven?</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Ten</hi>
               </hi> Ave Maries, <hi>and but <hi>One</hi>
               </hi> Pater No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            <p>Que. 11. <hi>What</hi> Precept <hi>of CHRIST, or</hi> Preſident <hi>of the</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>have you to keep count of the</hi> tale <hi>of your</hi> Prayers, <hi>by</hi> Bracelets, <hi>or</hi> Beads <hi>upon ſtrings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 12. <hi>VVhat Word of the Record of Truth have you to warrant a place of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory for Sin after this life,</hi> under that cloak granting liberty to your ſelves to ſin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 13. <hi>VVhat</hi> Word <hi>of GOD, or</hi> Precept <hi>of CHRIST, have you to warrant unto any ſoul which requireth a reaſon of you, to ſhew how poſſibly can any one of you ſanctifie</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:33625:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Bread <hi>and</hi> Wine, <hi>to diſpenſe it under the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of a</hi> Sacrament; <hi>ſeeing you are all confeſſed to be of</hi> corrupt hearts <hi>and</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean hands, <hi>which never could touch the holy thing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 14. <hi>VVhat</hi> Precept <hi>or</hi> Preſident <hi>recorded in the Scriptures of Truth, have you to warrant the Adminiſtration of</hi> Water, ſprinkled upon Infants <hi>with unclean hands, in the corruption of your hearts, to be the</hi> Baptiſm <hi>which taketh away the</hi> Original Sin? <hi>How is the</hi> Original <hi>taken away from any one, whilſt the life of you all is a continual iſſue, and open fountain of all ſin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 15. <hi>How can an <hi>evil heart</hi> bleſſe any thing? or the <hi>ſpirit of Satan</hi> make</hi> Holy Water? <hi>Which of you being daily waſhed in that Water, will it clenſe from the Corruption and rottenneſs of his heart?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 16. <hi>VVhat</hi> Precept of CHRIST, <hi>or</hi> Doctrine <hi>of the</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>is your Warrant to deny the general uſe of the</hi> Scriptures <hi>of Truth among your Church-members; and to allow</hi> Books <hi>of</hi> lying Stories, and Tales, <hi>and</hi> beaſtly Songs, <hi>and</hi> bewitching Playes <hi>and</hi> Sports, <hi>and ſuch abominable beaſtly things openly in the Streets, and in Houſes, as are not meet to be named?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:33625:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>Que. 17. <hi>What</hi> Precept <hi>of</hi> CHRIST <hi>have you to call men <hi>Fathers</hi> upon Earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 18. <hi>What Prophecy is there recorded in the Scriptures of Truth, for the ſucceſſion of <hi>Popes, Cardinals, Chaplains, White-Fryars, Black-Fryars, Gray-Fryars, Ieſuites, Nuns,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Queriſters, <hi>to come in the Truth?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 19. <hi>What</hi> Precept <hi>or</hi> Preſident <hi>have you in the Scriptures of Truth, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in</hi> Idols Temples, <hi>made with hands, there ſeeking GOD, where GOD dwelleth not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 20. <hi>What Scripture is it, that war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants your</hi> going Proceſſions?</p>
            <p>Que. 21. <hi>What Scripture-Example have you for your</hi> Begging Brothers <hi>going about</hi> (hood-wink'd and diſguiſ'd, with Money-Boxes, and others with great Wallets and Wine-bottles) <hi>from houſe to houſe a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 22. <hi>What</hi> Example <hi>in Scripture have you, which ſheweth that the</hi> Saints <hi>and</hi> Apoſtles <hi>in the</hi> Primitive times <hi>did live in the obſervation of the</hi> Dayes <hi>or</hi> Times <hi>of</hi> CHRIST's Conception, <hi>and with his, alſo of</hi> one another's Day <hi>yearly of</hi> Births <hi>or</hi> Deaths?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:33625:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>Que. 23. <hi>What Commandment of GOD have you, for the time called <hi>Lent,</hi> and in it the abſtinence from <hi>fleſh;</hi> and ſo in like manner <hi>ſixth</hi> and <hi>ſeventh</hi> dayes of the Week alwayes beſides, commanding it under the Judgment of Penalty?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be brief, I would draw to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Root of a Matter, which ought in Wiſdom principally to be known in you all, that you may know your Root, of which I have ſeen much, as ye daily bring forth the fruit thereof.</p>
            <p>Que. 24. <hi>Whether the ſpirit of <hi>Oaths, Envy, Luſt,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Lyes, <hi>is not of the ground and original root of Hereſie, yea or nay?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 25. <hi>Whether <hi>that Spirit</hi> hath not an abſolute and inſtant Ground, and Root uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally</hi> (according to Confeſſion) <hi>in your Body, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 26. <hi>Whether is not all things, which are contrary to the Doctrine and Life of CHRIST and his</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>abſolutely and undeniably</hi> Hereſie, <hi>and that</hi> (aſſuredly) <hi>Opinion, which is the leſſer, as practice, which makes it greater, and they both but one in the Ground and Nature, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 27. <hi>What</hi> Rule of Truth, <hi>or</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>in the Scriptures of Truth, have you to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33625:43"/>
condemn any man as an</hi> Heretick, <hi>which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth your</hi> evil ſpirit, <hi>and in the Life utterly abhorreth all your</hi> beaſtly works, <hi>and</hi> wicked words, <hi>brought forth by the ſpirit of Hereſie? And, to what purpoſe, think you, ſtandeth the judgment of your ſpirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do thou mind thy blind-hearted brother, <hi>Thomas Courtney,</hi> of theſe things, who told me, <hi>that Hereſie</hi> (ſpeaking of ſome Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) <hi>was a worſer ſin than Murder;</hi> which weighed in the deeps, lets to ſee, that it breaks <hi>a gap</hi> for more <hi>evil</hi> than a <hi>thouſand</hi> of the like his <hi>lines</hi> is able to reconcile: the which was his <hi>ignorance;</hi> as if <hi>Murder</hi> were not the <hi>moſt abominable desperate act of wilfulneſs</hi> againſt <hi>GOD,</hi> and a <hi>man's Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> brought forth by the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Hereſie?</hi> which <hi>ſpirit</hi> abounds in all your <hi>Coaſts,</hi> which is the <hi>real cauſe</hi> of all the <hi>Oaths, Curſes, Lyes, Diſſimulations, Hypocriſies, Drunkenneſs, Gluttony, Adulteries, Pride, Covetouſneſs, Envy,</hi> all <hi>Uncleaneſs,</hi> and <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> brought forth <hi>innumerably</hi> in your Land; For which cauſe, if you had <hi>all Words,</hi> and underſtood <hi>all Myſteries,</hi> yet the <hi>Saints,</hi> intereſted in the <hi>ſimplicity</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> dwelling in <hi>GOD,</hi> cannot <hi>joyn hands</hi> with
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33625:43"/>
you, to partake of your <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and ſo of your <hi>evil deeds,</hi> and laſtly of the <hi>Wrath</hi> to be <hi>revealed,</hi> which the Lord God in his Counſel hath determined ſhall <hi>ſweep</hi> a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Land.</p>
            <p>When laſtly thou wert with me, I ſaw that thy viſage was none of thine own, as always unto thy own, I deſire not to judge thee raſhly; but let me exhort thee, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Carry not a <hi>Bears Paw</hi> under thy <hi>long Gown,</hi> nor a <hi>Lion's Tooth</hi> within thy <hi>mincing Lips;</hi> thy words, many of them, were as <hi>ſmooth</hi> as <hi>ſweet Butter</hi> and <hi>freſh Oyl,</hi> but ſee thou that under thy tongue there be not hid the <hi>poyſon of Aſps,</hi> in ſuch things, as in the reſt of the <hi>dead works, ſigns, ſhews,</hi> and <hi>noiſes,</hi> as the <hi>Magicians</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> about the <hi>Walls</hi> of the <hi>Priſon,</hi> and elſwhere; you may (as they themſelves did) <hi>deceive your ſelves</hi> alſo, but by all theſe things, neither in my ſelf, nor in you, am I at all <hi>deceived.</hi> Settle your ſelves in <hi>Council,</hi> I am bound within <hi>Walls,</hi> yet, bleſſed be the <hi>LORD GOD,</hi> I ſavour the deeds of darkneſs, and many of them would not be of good report to be told among your ſelves: You know that I bear all the folly, as being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſſal</hi> to that end; but you know
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33625:44"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:33625:44"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:33625:45"/>
not how I <hi>trample</hi> upon the <hi>fruit,</hi> and the <hi>ſpirit</hi> which yeelds it.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the Inquiſition-Priſon in</hi> Rome.</dateline>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the Inhabitants of the <hi>bloody City,</hi> the Mother of Cruelties and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</head>
            <p>REad the <hi>Declaration</hi> of the <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of <hi>this Cauſe,</hi> let it be <hi>ſpread</hi> in an <hi>open Parchment</hi> upon the <hi>Standard</hi> of <hi>your Hoſt,</hi> and let it be <hi>marked</hi> in your <hi>Enſign,</hi> as a <hi>perpetual ſhame</hi> in the face of <hi>your Camp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was a certain <hi>Meſſage</hi> ſent by the hand of a <hi>Servant,</hi> by the <hi>LORD</hi> of a ſtrong <hi>Army,</hi> who treated for the <hi>Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> of the <hi>City:</hi> He came not as a <hi>Coward</hi> to hide in a <hi>hole,</hi> nor as <hi>treacherous</hi> to ſlay in ſecret; but to deliver his <hi>ſervice</hi> to the <hi>Chief,</hi> to depart with the <hi>Anſwer</hi> of the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Land.</hi> He was <hi>fooliſhly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated</hi> by the hands of the <hi>jealous,</hi> and <hi>il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> handled</hi> by the <hi>doubtful</hi> and <hi>timerous hearted;</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:33625:45"/>
they <hi>bound</hi> a Man of War in <hi>Chains,</hi> and <hi>rejoyced</hi> often to <hi>ſmite him</hi> with <hi>rotten ſticks;</hi> they <hi>chuſed</hi> not to plead with him in <hi>open field,</hi> nor to deal with him, as do the <hi>Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant</hi> and <hi>Honourable;</hi> they <hi>bound</hi> him in their <hi>ſeat</hi> of <hi>contempt,</hi> and ſent <hi>Scorners</hi> to view him in <hi>ſecret;</hi> he looked at the <hi>works</hi> of <hi>their hands,</hi> and wrote them in the <hi>ſoals</hi> of his <hi>feet;</hi> he ſetled his heart in the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>Meſſage</hi> of his <hi>LORD,</hi> and rather choſe the <hi>Chain</hi> of his <hi>Enemies Yoak,</hi> than to yeeld unto <hi>Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Flattery;</hi> he was <hi>faithful</hi> to his <hi>Enemy</hi> in what he was <hi>ſent,</hi> as he was to his <hi>LORD</hi> that <hi>ſent him;</hi> he waſhed his <hi>hands</hi> of the <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>City,</hi> and <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> the <hi>Peace</hi> of his <hi>LORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What will you ſay for your ſelves when this <hi>Servant's Cauſe</hi> ſhall be publickly pleaded to your <hi>faces?</hi> I know your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe concerning the <hi>Heir,</hi> and the purpoſe alſo of the <hi>LORD</hi> of the <hi>Vineyard,</hi> as the Reward of your wilful works: You have been <hi>well warned,</hi> but you have not <hi>well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,</hi> but have <hi>ill rewarded</hi> and <hi>requited:</hi> Yet in all I deſire not that God may <hi>requite you,</hi> as ye have <hi>requited me;</hi> and therefore I have <hi>Conſolation,</hi> and you know not my
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33625:46"/>
               <hi>Crown.</hi> The <hi>putrified head</hi> of the <hi>corrupted body</hi> and <hi>rotten tayl,</hi> yea, the <hi>whole body,</hi> even from <hi>head</hi> to <hi>tayl,</hi> I tread upon for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
               <dateline>Rome, <hi>from the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition-Priſon.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> appointed as <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> and Keepers of the Inquiſition-Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thereunto belonging, A Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord God to you all is come.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ARiſe, ariſe,</hi> It is high time to <hi>Awake</hi> and <hi>Ariſe</hi> from the <hi>Seat</hi> of <hi>Blood;</hi> For the <hi>LORD GOD</hi> is <hi>ariſen</hi> to make <hi>Inquiſition</hi> for the <hi>Blood</hi> of every <hi>Innocent Soul,</hi> which hath been <hi>ſtarved</hi> and <hi>ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered</hi> upon the face of the whole Earth; <hi>Indignation</hi> flyeth with him as a <hi>pointed Arrow; <hi>Vengeance</hi>
               </hi> is in his <hi>Right hand</hi> as a <hi>Spear</hi> for the <hi>Battel,</hi> and <hi>Wrath</hi> as a <hi>Dart</hi> to pierce the Liver of the <hi>Wicked;</hi> The <hi>LAMB</hi> is <hi>ariſen</hi> for <hi>Slaughter,</hi> as a Lion to devour the Prey; a <hi>Burning fire</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:33625:46"/>
proceedeth out of his mouth, The <hi>Ungodly</hi> ſhall be <hi>conſumed</hi> before him; and becauſe <hi>Iniquity</hi> is plentiful in the Land, he haſteth the <hi>Iudgment</hi> of the Day; neither <hi>Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> nor <hi>Cloud</hi> ſhall hide the <hi>Wicked;</hi> nay, nor the <hi>Clifts</hi> of the <hi>craggy Rocks</hi> from the <hi>fierceneſs</hi> of his provoked <hi>Fury;</hi> He will ſmite <hi>ſuddenly,</hi> even in a <hi>moment,</hi> in the Land, and bereave the <hi>habitation</hi> of the <hi>Dweller;</hi> He will <hi>catch,</hi> as a <hi>ſnare</hi> in the <hi>night,</hi> and none ſhall deliver from his <hi>Wrath;</hi> He will abide as <hi>burnings</hi> in the Earth, <hi>Corruption</hi> ſhall not dwell in his Preſence; the <hi>Evil-doer</hi> is for the <hi>Wine-preſs</hi> of his <hi>Wrath,</hi> but the <hi>Juſt</hi> ſhall dwell in his Pleaſures: <hi>It is <hi>at hand,</hi> It is <hi>at hand,</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Vengeance</hi> of the LORD, according to the <hi>Prophecy:</hi> The <hi>abundance</hi> of <hi>Iniquity</hi> in the Land, yea, the <hi>fulneſs</hi> of the meaſure <hi>of Sin,</hi> hath dragged the <hi>fulneſs</hi> of the <hi>determination</hi> of <hi>Time,</hi> for the <hi>Revelation</hi> of <hi>Woe</hi> in the <hi>Earth,</hi> and <hi>Vengeance</hi> upon the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>Long have you made <hi>Inquiſition</hi> after <hi>evil</hi> for <hi>evil,</hi> &amp; baniſhed the <hi>good</hi> from your Preſence, and ſhut it up in the <hi>Dens</hi> of <hi>Dragons. <hi>Ariſe</hi>
               </hi> and draw out of the <hi>ground</hi> of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33625:47"/>
the <hi>Curſe,</hi> where the <hi>righteous Blood</hi> of <hi>Abel</hi> was ſpilt; For your <hi>ſin</hi> is as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and your <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> as the <hi>evil</hi> of <hi>Gomorrah.</hi> Your <hi>Glory</hi> is the Kingdom of this World; your <hi>Seats</hi> are as the dwellings of Princes: You have <hi>fulneſs</hi> and <hi>eaſe</hi> in your houſes, you eat not the <hi>bread</hi> of <hi>carefulneſs.</hi> You make the <hi>miſeries</hi> of others your <hi>mirth,</hi> and their <hi>mourning</hi> your ſong of <hi>rejoycing.</hi> You ſtretch your <hi>Carcaſſes</hi> upon the burden of their <hi>ſorrows,</hi> and take pleaſure to heap <hi>weight</hi> upon <hi>weight:</hi> You make the <hi>ſimple</hi> to bend at your Bow, and the <hi>wayfaring man</hi> to bow at your beck. You ſtretch forth your <hi>necks</hi> in <hi>pride,</hi> and bend your <hi>brows</hi> in <hi>preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> You have <hi>ſlain the <hi>Lamb</hi>
               </hi> in your ſtreets, and <hi>trampled</hi> on his <hi>blood</hi> in your ſecret habitations. You <hi>crucifie</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> afreſh, and put him to <hi>open ſhame.</hi> You are not aſhamed to ſay, <hi>Lord,</hi> though your <hi>lyes</hi> and your <hi>lightneſs</hi> abound. You have <hi>provoked</hi> the LORD unto <hi>Jealouſie,</hi> and raiſed his <hi>Anger</hi> by conſtraint. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, behold, he <hi>cometh,</hi> as with <hi>Voices</hi> and <hi>Lightning,</hi> and will ſearch your <hi>dark cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> as with <hi>Candles:</hi> He will <hi>rent</hi> the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings</hi> of your <hi>body,</hi> and ſet you as in the <hi>day</hi> wherein you were <hi>born,</hi> and place you
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33625:47"/>
as <hi>Butts</hi> for his <hi>Shafts;</hi> even as you made the <hi>Innocent</hi> your <hi>mark</hi> to ſhoot your <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows</hi> at in ſecret: You are planted the <hi>Judges</hi> of the <hi>Citadels,</hi> as the Chief of the <hi>Munitions</hi> in the Land, and as the <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Caſtle</hi> of Refuge among all the <hi>Forts</hi> of the <hi>City:</hi> But the <hi>LORD</hi> will make the <hi>Staff</hi> of your <hi>Truſt</hi> as for a <hi>ſhout</hi> in <hi>Battel</hi> againſt you; your <hi>Wallings</hi> he will make as a <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and your <hi>houſes</hi> as an <hi>habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Bitterneſs;</hi> your <hi>pleaſant Dreams</hi> ſhall have their end in <hi>ſorrows,</hi> and your <hi>Divinations</hi> of <hi>gladneſs</hi> be finiſhed with the compaſs of <hi>trouble; <hi>Vnbelief</hi>
               </hi> haſteth the <hi>Wo,</hi> becauſe <hi>Iniquity</hi> waxeth <hi>ripe</hi> in the Land. And the <hi>LORD</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Jonah, Go down unto</hi> Niniveh, <hi>and preach: And</hi> Jonah <hi>cryed in the City, Yet forty dayes, and</hi> Niniveh <hi>ſhall be deſtroyed:</hi> And when Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings came to the King, he queſtioned not the matter, but conſidered the ſins of the Land, and through <hi>Faith</hi> there was <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> found among them, and the Lord <hi>turned back his Anger,</hi> and <hi>ſpared the City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember your <hi>Viſitation</hi> which is come from the LORD, in the day that you cry, <hi>Peace, peace</hi> in the Land, ſaying, <hi>none evil ſhall happen unto us;</hi> had I turned to another
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33625:48"/>
Land, the Lord would have had followed me with <hi>Storms,</hi> even as he did <hi>Jonah</hi> with <hi>displeaſure;</hi> And God, who ſaid, <hi>Go unto Rome,</hi> ſaid alſo, <hi>Thus ſhalt thou ſay:</hi> which things I have given forth among you, and am <hi>clear</hi> from your works of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> and from the <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>City,</hi> which elſe, as the Lord liveth in <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> he would have required the thing at my hand.</p>
            <p>Concerning your <hi>Judgment</hi> I have this at leaſt-wiſe to ſay: You ſit as <hi>Lords</hi> in the Land, and your <hi>Wills</hi> are the <hi>Precepts</hi> of the People; You conſtrain your <hi>words</hi> for a Law, and make <hi>Envy</hi> the Judge thereof; The mouth of <hi>Malice</hi> dealeth the Sentence, for the inſtruments of <hi>Cruelty</hi> to execute your Wrath; You will not that your <hi>Judgment</hi> be <hi>judged,</hi> for you deal it in <hi>craft</hi> among the ſimple: but this the LORD <hi>willeth,</hi> although you <hi>will not;</hi> I ſay the Lord willeth it, and it ſhall come to paſſe: For the <hi>LORD GOD</hi> will enquire after <hi>Judgement,</hi> and bring <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> as a ſpoyler of your Seat; You will ſeek to eſcape the <hi>Day,</hi> which cometh as a <hi>Thief</hi> in the <hi>night;</hi> But the LORD will compaſs you as <hi>Fiſh</hi> in the <hi>Net,</hi> and <hi>entrap</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:33625:48"/>
you as <hi>Birds</hi> in the <hi>ſnare;</hi> and you that have digged a Pit for <hi>another,</hi> ſhall fall your <hi>ſelves</hi> therein: <hi>Iudge, judge</hi> the <hi>ſin</hi> of your <hi>own hearts,</hi> and the <hi>liberties</hi> of your own <hi>luſts,</hi> and make <hi>inquiſition</hi> after <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> for the ſake of the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>Judgement</hi> of Truth, which ſtandeth againſt the <hi>Iniquities</hi> of your life; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it be perfected in you, <hi>Judge not, leſt you be judged;</hi> For ye have not received the meaſure in <hi>love,</hi> for <hi>Judgment</hi> to <hi>juſtifie</hi> you in the ſight of <hi>GOD;</hi> and wanting the meaſure in your <hi>ſelves,</hi> you heap up <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion</hi> upon the head of <hi>another;</hi> and, wherein you judge <hi>another,</hi> you are left in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable your <hi>ſelves;</hi> for, wherein you judge <hi>another,</hi> you ſtand guilty of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in the <hi>ſelf-ſame nature;</hi> yea, you <hi>judge</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> judged <hi>Jeſus,</hi> whom they blindly accuſed for <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly <hi>condemned</hi> his <hi>Innocency,</hi> to cover their Seat of <hi>Iniquity.</hi> O man, <hi>Judgest</hi> thou <hi>another</hi> as an <hi>Heretick,</hi> and haſt thou <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Curſes</hi> in thy mouth? Judgeſt thou another for <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and thou an <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite</hi> and <hi>Lyar</hi> in thy life? Thou ſhalt bear the burden of thy <hi>Judgment,</hi> for thy own ſpirit gave the <hi>entrance,</hi> and yeelded
<pb facs="tcp:33625:49"/>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:33625:50"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:33625:50"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:33625:51"/>
the encreaſe of <hi>Hereſie</hi> in the Earth, and thou ſhalt not be <hi>excuſed</hi> in the ſight of the <hi>LORD GOD;</hi> And you ſhall all know, That the <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> is according to Truth, againſt every one that doth <hi>evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning your <hi>Reſtraints,</hi> let me ſhew you the general <hi>Iſſues</hi> and <hi>Effects</hi> thereof: A man that breaks the <hi>Covenant</hi> of your <hi>Wills,</hi> as having eaten <hi>Fleſh</hi> upon a <hi>ſixth day</hi> of the week (which you call <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus day,</hi> after the manner of aſcribing glory to a <hi>Heathen Goddeſs</hi>) for ſo <hi>doing,</hi> or otherwiſe you <hi>offending,</hi> though not againſt <hi>GOD</hi> tranſgreſſing, he is judged by you as a <hi>ſinner</hi> againſt your <hi>Church,</hi> and therefore receives the ſentence for <hi>reſtraint</hi> in your <hi>Inquiſition-Priſon-houſe;</hi> and then he is yours, as the <hi>wild Aſs</hi> that is caught in the <hi>Coller;</hi> and knowing the nature of your own <hi>luſts,</hi> you work upon the ſtrength of the <hi>ſame</hi> in another; you are experienced to deal with your <hi>own,</hi> as the <hi>Falkoner</hi> to bring <hi>Hawks</hi> to the waving of the <hi>Leuer.</hi> Man in the <hi>Fall</hi> (as your Members have ſaid, not one of you reſtored unto the <hi>firſt Adam's</hi> eſtate in <hi>Paradiſe</hi>) dwells in the curſed ground of <hi>Corruption,</hi> Luſt ſtanding
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33625:51"/>
head over the whole Life, which being a little <hi>curbed</hi> with your bridle of <hi>Reſtraint,</hi> quickly languiſheth in the Creature, and with it alſo the mind of the Creature, unto the bereaving and robbing the <hi>falſe Rest;</hi> which, through the ſubtilty of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> was planted in the Creature. A Sea of <hi>miſery</hi> then floweth into the <hi>heart,</hi> and the mind gathers up the remembrance of the <hi>delight</hi> of every pleaſure that is <hi>paſt,</hi> and painfully pleadeth in it ſelf; I have loſt the <hi>fulneſs</hi> and choice of the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> which I had in my liberty; here is no <hi>vent</hi> for the performing of what my heart <hi>deſireth,</hi> either <hi>fulneſs</hi> or <hi>want</hi> doth but heap <hi>Wo</hi> upon <hi>Wo,</hi> in the <hi>Creature,</hi> which knoweth not <hi>a ſtay</hi> to the heart, nor a <hi>guide</hi> to the affection of the mind; and then there is an <hi>out-cry,</hi> according to the Writings in the Walls, <hi>O Liberty, Liberty, without Liberty all is nothing; yea, the fulneſs of all without Liberty, is but the Addition of Fuel to the Flame of the Miſery;</hi> Wherefore, ſaith the Serpent, <hi>Thou knoweſt the Redemption, <hi>do this,</hi> and thou reapeſt thy <hi>Freedom;</hi> for it is better to paſſe under the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> and <hi>Penance,</hi> which is but as it were for a <hi>moment,</hi> than to languiſh in this
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33625:52"/>
Gulph of Affliction <hi>for ever:</hi>
               </hi> And then the <hi>Hypocrite</hi> ariſeth in the heart, and cometh to the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of deceit, with <hi>watry eyes,</hi> and <hi>wringing hands,</hi> and <hi>ſtrong ſupplications</hi> to the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and makes the moan of a <hi>burdened</hi> and <hi>troubled Conſcience</hi> and <hi>wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Spirit,</hi> becauſe of the Tranſgreſſions; and then it ſaith, <hi>Yea, with all my heart,</hi> Saint <hi>Mary,</hi> St. <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> St. <hi>Francis,</hi> St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> and the <hi>reſt</hi> of the <hi>Saints, <hi>which are written in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon-walls, I will take for my</hi> Advocates, <hi>and</hi> holy Purgatory, <hi>and all the</hi> reſt; <hi>I believe as the Church believes, and gladly will I bear</hi> my Penance, <hi>that my Conſcience may be eaſed.</hi>
               </hi> Whilſt all this is but the <hi>out-cry</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> even of that <hi>wicked one,</hi> for the purchaſe of <hi>Liberty;</hi> I ſay, to purchaſe <hi>liberty</hi> for the full exerciſe of the <hi>Luſt;</hi> and when the <hi>Liberty</hi> is come, and the <hi>Lust</hi> fulfilled therein, in <hi>Meats,</hi> and <hi>Muſick,</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> and <hi>Women,</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> and <hi>Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and <hi>Lyes,</hi> and <hi>vain Jeſting,</hi> and <hi>Idle-talking,</hi> and <hi>cheating,</hi> and <hi>double-dealing,</hi> and <hi>ſwearing,</hi> and <hi>curſing,</hi> and all manner of <hi>miſchief</hi> and <hi>abominations;</hi> then the <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> is <hi>full,</hi> and the <hi>peace</hi> is <hi>poſſeſſed,</hi> the <hi>delights</hi> are <hi>fulfilled,</hi> no <hi>ſorrow</hi> remains, no
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33625:52"/>
               <hi>conſcience</hi> laden, nor ſpirit burdened with <hi>affliction,</hi> becauſe of <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> but all is accounted <hi>well,</hi> and he reckoned <hi>a good Roman Catholick:</hi> And then, what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of the <hi>good</hi> of the <hi>Prieſts?</hi> and what commendations do the <hi>Prieſts</hi> give of that <hi>Convert?</hi> Thus all <hi>rottenneſs</hi> is daubed up with <hi>dirt,</hi> and this is the ſum and fruit of the whole work; which things the <hi>LORD GOD</hi> will aſſuredly and that moſt ſtrongly <hi>plead,</hi> in the faces both of <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> unto the utter confuſion of all hands, and deceitfulneſs of all corrupt hearts; who knoweth how to deal with his <hi>own,</hi> and to deliver from the ſnare of the wicked, whom you know not how to handle, to bring under the bent of your Bow: You are warned of <hi>Gods mighty day, <hi>wherefore prize your time, and repent.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>I alſo propound a few <hi>Queries</hi> unto you, to the end that you may give me ſome plain and diſtinct <hi>Anſwer</hi> to each of them <hi>particularly,</hi> under your hand-writing.</p>
            <p>Que. 1. <hi>Whether are there</hi> more grounds <hi>in the nature, than <hi>two</hi> in the Earth</hi> (that is to ſay) <hi>the <hi>good</hi> and the <hi>evil,</hi> the</hi> bleſſed <hi>and the</hi> curſed? <hi>And whether the fruits of each
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33625:53"/>
ground, according to their nature, are not</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>or</hi> curſed <hi>in the ſight of God,</hi> yea <hi>or</hi> nay?</p>
            <p>Que. 2. <hi>In what ground were your <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition Offices</hi> and <hi>Priſons,</hi> and the <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers</hi> thereunto belonging, brought forth? and in which do they ſtand; whether in the ground, as the fruit of the ground of the many inventions, which brought the flood of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the dayes of the generation of</hi> Noah, <hi>or abſolutely in the righteouſneſs of the ground of</hi> God's Law, <hi>as given by the Lord from Heaven,</hi> yea <hi>or</hi> nay?</p>
            <p>Que. 3. <hi>In what ground is <hi>Perſecution</hi> brought forth, which any man ſuffereth for the real ſake of a conſcience of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 4. <hi>Whether can any ſuch <hi>Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> truly diſcern, and conſequently judge the real conſcience of God which is in another,</hi> yea <hi>or</hi> nay?</p>
            <p>Que. 5. <hi>By what teſtimony of Truth, can you ſhew me, That your <hi>Penance</hi> or <hi>Priſons</hi> do mortifie the fleſh without Murder, or quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the mind from every motion of corruption, as freedom from the lusts of tranſgreſſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 6. <hi>Whether have you made inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion after the <hi>Hypocrite</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Heretick</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you? <hi>and ſhew me how you have laid his
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33625:53"/>
Life unto the ſuffering of the Penance of Chriſt's Croſs, with the teſtimony of the effects thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 7. <hi>What was the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> which CHRIST made after the Offence of the accuſed</hi> Harlot, <hi>and the</hi> Judgement <hi>of the</hi> Harlot's <hi>Tranſgreſſion? and, whether do you judge with that, or contrary to that Judgment in your</hi> Inquiſitions?</p>
            <p>Que. 8. <hi>With what confidence can you judg the</hi> pure conſcience <hi>of another in the preſence of the Lord,</hi> yea, <hi>or caſt a</hi> ſtone <hi>at a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor, whilſt you your ſelves are found ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Que. 9. <hi>What is that <hi>Vnjuſt,</hi> in whoſe Eye is the <hi>Beam?</hi> and what is the <hi>Beam</hi> in the Eye? and whether is not the <hi>Beam</hi> in your Eye,</hi> yea <hi>or</hi> nay?</p>
            <p>Que. 10. <hi>What is the cauſe that a <hi>mote</hi> is judged by the</hi> Eye <hi>that is <hi>beamed?</hi> And, what is the</hi> ground, root, original <hi>and</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal cauſe of mens calling <hi>good <hi>evil,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>evil <hi>good?</hi> And, whether is not your fruit in the general a teſtimony that you are in that</hi> ground, <hi>and that</hi> root <hi>in you in the ground which yeelds the fruit of calling <hi>good</hi>
               </hi> evil, <hi>and</hi> evil <hi>good, <hi>in the particular,</hi>
               </hi> yea <hi>or</hi> nay?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:33625:54"/>I love the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Souls;</hi> but do hate a <hi>Lye</hi> and <hi>Deceit,</hi> with every <hi>evil way.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Rome, <hi>diſpenſed from the Inquiſition-Priſon.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the Seed which is yet unborn in <hi>Rome,</hi> Salutation.</head>
            <p>TO the <hi>Seed</hi> of that <hi>Woman</hi> which the <hi>Dragon</hi> drove into the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> over whoſe <hi>ſufferings</hi> many Generations have paſſed, which viewed them with an eye of <hi>contempt.</hi> O <hi>Seed,</hi> I ſee thy travel of <hi>ſorrows,</hi> and the <hi>ſighings</hi> that compaſs thee in the <hi>deeps;</hi> thou art ſwadled in the womb of <hi>affliction,</hi> and bound in the belly of <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> thou lyeſt in the <hi>deeps</hi> of the <hi>raging Seas,</hi> the weeds are wrapt about thy head; thou art as the <hi>blood-ſhed</hi> of <hi>Abel</hi> in the Earth, and groaneſt in her bowels to the <hi>LORD</hi> thy Creator; thou dwelleſt in the <hi>ſolitary places,</hi> as hid in the hole of the <hi>Aſp;</hi> thou art conſtrained in the Den of the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> and forced in the <hi>Cockatrice's</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; thou art as a <hi>Pelican</hi> in the <hi>Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:33625:54"/>
and an <hi>alone Sparrow</hi> ſitting on the <hi>houſe top;</hi> thou art as a <hi>Bee</hi> in the holes of the Rocks, driven from the <hi>Hive</hi> of the <hi>Swarm;</hi> thou lyeſt as a <hi>Lark</hi> in the <hi>heaths</hi> of the <hi>Mountains,</hi> and as a <hi>Quail</hi> in the <hi>Stubble-fields;</hi> thou art as a <hi>Wren</hi> in a <hi>Buſh</hi> of <hi>Thorns,</hi> the <hi>Vulture</hi> ſoars over thee to devour; when thou lifteſt up thine <hi>head</hi> for a flight the <hi>Kite</hi> doth ſtrike at thy life, the <hi>Hawk</hi> doth watch for thy <hi>riſing,</hi> and the <hi>Gier-Eagle</hi> to devour the prey; <hi>Wo! wo! wo</hi> is me for thee in this thy hour of <hi>Tribulation!</hi> for I bear thy wound in my <hi>body,</hi> my <hi>ſoul</hi> is pained with thy <hi>grief;</hi> my belly is as a <hi>bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>k of bitterneſs,</hi> thou art laden with the <hi>Hills</hi> of the Earth, and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the <hi>Mountains</hi> of the Wilderneſs; heaps of ſtones are laid for thy <hi>weight,</hi> and Rocks for the <hi>weight</hi> of thy <hi>burden;</hi> thou art ſhut up in <hi>Priſon,</hi> in the <hi>Priſon-houſe,</hi> and ſitteſt <hi>ſolitary</hi> in darkneſs, in the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death; the <hi>bonds of death</hi> have bound <hi>thee,</hi> and the <hi>Covenant</hi> with <hi>Hell</hi> hath capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated <hi>thee;</hi> many do look at thee with the countenance of <hi>mirth,</hi> and wag their heads at thy <hi>mourning;</hi> thou art as a <hi>Lamb</hi> among <hi>Lions,</hi> and as a <hi>prey</hi> to the <hi>devouring beaſts;</hi> thou art as a <hi>ſpoyl</hi> to the mouth of the <hi>Fox,</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:33625:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:33625:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:33625:56"/>
and as a <hi>deſtruction</hi> to the teeth of the <hi>Wolf,</hi> the <hi>wild Aſſe</hi> is offended at thy <hi>moving,</hi> and ſnuffeth up the wind in <hi>ſcorn</hi> of thy <hi>breathing;</hi> the <hi>Bulls of Baſhan</hi> do purſue thee with <hi>roaring,</hi> and puſh with their <hi>horns</hi> at thy dwelling; thou art caſt in the ſide of the <hi>way,</hi> and the <hi>Chariot wheels</hi> run over thee; thou art placed as a <hi>But</hi> in the field, for the <hi>Arrows</hi> and <hi>Darts</hi> to pierce thee; thou art the <hi>despiſed</hi> in the Earth, and <hi>mocked</hi> of men of the World; thou art ſold as a <hi>Slave</hi> into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and counted the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſts</hi> of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> though I have heard thy <hi>cry</hi> in the Land, and bear <hi>marks</hi> of the <hi>bleeding</hi> of thy <hi>grief</hi> in my <hi>boſome,</hi> yet I want the greatneſs of the <hi>weight</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> to meaſure the <hi>depths</hi> of thy <hi>miſery;</hi> thou <hi>mourneſt</hi> as a <hi>Dove</hi> in the <hi>Deſerts,</hi> which hath loſt her <hi>only mate;</hi> thou <hi>weepeſt</hi> as the wayling of a <hi>Widow,</hi> and <hi>Mother</hi> bereaved of her <hi>Children;</hi> thou cryeſt with the <hi>grief</hi> of the <hi>fatherleſs</hi> and <hi>comfortleſs Child</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Mother;</hi> thy <hi>mourning</hi> is as the <hi>cry</hi> of the Voice of the <hi>Orphan,</hi> left without help in the Land; thy <hi>groans</hi> are as the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing of the <hi>Poor</hi> in the Earth, which wanteth the daily <hi>bread;</hi> thou lyeſt in the <hi>fields</hi> like a <hi>yeaned Lamb,</hi> by the ſide of a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33625:56"/>
               <hi>dead Sheep;</hi> ſore are thy <hi>cryes,</hi> as a <hi>ſtrugling Babe</hi> at the breaſts of a <hi>dead Mother:</hi> Eye hath not <hi>ſeen,</hi> neither hath ear <hi>heard,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath it entred into the heart of vain man to <hi>conceive</hi> the <hi>weight</hi> of thy <hi>Wo</hi> and <hi>Paſſions,</hi> in all the dayes of thy <hi>Wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVherefore, <hi>O Seed,</hi> becauſe thou haſt born the <hi>Indignation</hi> of the <hi>LORD</hi> for a ſeaſon, and waiteſt until it be <hi>over</hi> and <hi>paſt,</hi> and haſt not ſlipt thy <hi>ſhoulder</hi> in the <hi>heat</hi> of the <hi>day,</hi> nor thy <hi>neck</hi> from the yoak in the <hi>ſtormy time;</hi> Therefore hath thy <hi>GOD,</hi> thy <hi>Creator</hi> determined the <hi>good</hi> of thy <hi>travel</hi> in the Earth; He hath ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not always be as barren in the Land, but ſhalt yeeld thy increaſe in the Nations.</hi> O thou <hi>afflicted</hi> with the <hi>troubles</hi> of the <hi>deeps</hi> which <hi>tempeſts</hi> have rouled to the <hi>bottoms!</hi> lift up thy <hi>head</hi> in the <hi>Joy</hi> of the <hi>LORD,</hi> and be <hi>ſtrong</hi> in the Power of his <hi>Might;</hi> for the <hi>Word <hi>of the LORD</hi>
               </hi> is come down in the Earth, which was ſpoken by the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> of GOD; the LORD of the Heavens hath <hi>reſtored</hi> thy <hi>Mother,</hi> and pitched <hi>her</hi> as a <hi>Sanctuary</hi> in the Earth; the <hi>Daughter</hi> of <hi>Sion</hi> is her Name, the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> is with her; He hath given her a <hi>new threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33625:57"/>
Instrument</hi> with Teeth, to <hi>threſh</hi> the <hi>Mountains</hi> to duſt, and to <hi>beat</hi> the <hi>Hills</hi> to powder; to <hi>ſeive</hi> the <hi>Vanity</hi> of the <hi>Nations,</hi> and to <hi>fan</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> with her ſtrength; to be as a <hi>wound</hi> to every <hi>Wild-beast,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> to the life of the <hi>Deſtroyer;</hi> to be a <hi>ſnare</hi> to the <hi>Fowls</hi> of the Air, and a <hi>fire</hi> to devour the <hi>Devourer;</hi> to find out the <hi>Dens</hi> of the Earth, and to open the <hi>holes</hi> of thy hiding; to break the <hi>bolts</hi> of the <hi>Priſon-doors,</hi> and the <hi>Chains</hi> of <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> to make thee as <hi>free-born</hi> in the Land of the Living, to <hi>poſſeſs</hi> an Inheritance therein: And it ſhall be no more with thee, as in the dayes that all men ſought after thee for <hi>evil,</hi> and hunted thee for a <hi>purpoſe</hi> of <hi>miſchief</hi> and <hi>cruel end;</hi> for the LORD hath <hi>ſworn</hi> thy <hi>Salvation,</hi> and <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted <hi>thy Peace for ever;</hi> ſighing</hi> and <hi>ſorrow</hi> ſhall fly away from thee, and thy <hi>tears</hi> ſhall be wiped from thine eyes, and the LORD will poſſeſs thee with the <hi>Joy</hi> of Conſolation, and thou ſhalt reap <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing</hi> as ripe Corn in the Harveſt; He will give thee <hi>Beauty</hi> for <hi>Aſhes,</hi> the <hi>Oyl of joy</hi> for <hi>mourning,</hi> and the <hi>garments of praiſe</hi> for the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>heavineſs;</hi> he will ſtay thee with <hi>Flaggons,</hi> and comfort thee with <hi>Wine,</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:33625:57"/>
and fill thee with the <hi>greatneſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> his <hi>Love;</hi> thy habitation he wil <hi>compaſs</hi> with <hi>encreaſe,</hi> thy <hi>basket</hi> and thy <hi>ſtore</hi> ſhall <hi>abound;</hi> thou ſhalt eat the food of the <hi>Angels</hi> of God, and be reckoned as a <hi>Leader</hi> in the Land; thou ſhalt ſpring up as a <hi>plant</hi> in a <hi>fruitful ground,</hi> and thy <hi>branches</hi> ſhall over-ſpread the <hi>Nations;</hi> thou ſhalt be at the calling of the <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and the <hi>gathering</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> in the <hi>West;</hi> the Lord will enlarge thy <hi>borders,</hi> and make thy <hi>dwellings</hi> as the fulneſs of the Cities in the Earth; thou ſhalt be as the <hi>Lord</hi> of an <hi>Hoſt,</hi> and as the <hi>Captain</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> of <hi>GOD; <hi>Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels</hi>
               </hi> ſhall bend to thy <hi>Bow,</hi> and <hi>Hoſts</hi> ſhall <hi>tremble</hi> at the ſhout of thy <hi>Voice;</hi> thou ſhalt ſtand as <hi>a dread</hi> in the Land, and a <hi>ſign</hi> of aſtoniſhment in the Earth; <hi>Princes</hi> ſhall <hi>tremble</hi> in thy preſence, and the faces of <hi>Kings</hi> gather <hi>paleneſs;</hi> the <hi>dread</hi> of thy Countenance ſhall fill all with <hi>fear,</hi> the Heavens ſhall <hi>tremble</hi> before thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariſe, Ariſe</hi> my <hi>Love,</hi> why ſitteſt thou as <hi>dead</hi> in the night of ſlumber? And as <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep</hi> amongſt the <hi>Monuments</hi> of the <hi>Earth?</hi> Why ſhall <hi>Death</hi> be thy dwelling, and the <hi>Night</hi> a Watch unto thee? Why ſhall thy <hi>face</hi> be <hi>vailed,</hi> and the Clouds thus <hi>cover</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:33625:58"/>
thy <hi>Glory?</hi> Though thou art but that ſmall <hi>worm Jacob,</hi> and the Voice cryeth, <hi>Who ſhall raiſe him?</hi> Yet, <hi>Ariſe, Ariſe</hi> my <hi>Love,</hi> and being rais'd, thou art ſtronger than <hi>Armies,</hi> thou art more than the <hi>Camps</hi> of <hi>ten thouſand Hoſts</hi> prepared in order for the <hi>battel.</hi> O <hi>ariſe</hi> and ſpread forth thy <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> and raviſh the <hi>Virgins</hi> with thy <hi>Beauty,</hi> and fill their <hi>Lamps</hi> with the <hi>droppings</hi> of thy <hi>Locks,</hi> which wait until the morning for thee; thy <hi>Preſence</hi> is an Odor of <hi>Perfumes,</hi> thy <hi>Word</hi> as a ſtream of <hi>Honey.</hi> O whereunto, whereunto ſhall I <hi>liken thee,</hi> thou <hi>faireſt</hi> of <hi>ten thouſands!</hi> filled with the Glory of thy <hi>GOD?</hi> thy <hi>Feet</hi> are the <hi>Foundations</hi> of the Earth, and thy <hi>Legs</hi> the <hi>Pillars</hi> of the Heavens; thy <hi>Bowels,</hi> as a <hi>Ciſtern,</hi> hold the Waters of the Earth, and the <hi>Waters</hi> of the <hi>Heavens</hi> as a <hi>Well:</hi> Thou ſendeſt them forth as a <hi>run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning brook,</hi> and as <hi>ſtreams</hi> to refreſh the Plant; Thy <hi>Reins</hi> are as the Virtue of <hi>God,</hi> which made man in the glory of his Image; thy <hi>Belly</hi> is the Fountain of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> to waſh away <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Uncleanneſs;</hi> thy <hi>Thighs</hi> are as the Bats of the Fountains, and thine <hi>Arms</hi> as the ſtrength of GOD; thy <hi>Back</hi> is the Tower of <hi>Zion,</hi> and thy
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33625:58"/>
               <hi>Breaſts,</hi> the nouriſhment of her <hi>Children;</hi> thy <hi>Body</hi> is the <hi>Temple</hi> of GOD, and thine <hi>Head</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi> of his <hi>Saints;</hi> thy <hi>Hairs</hi> are as the <hi>Stars</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> for glory, and thy <hi>Beard</hi> as the <hi>bright Clouds</hi> thereof; at thy <hi>neeſing</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> is in <hi>fire,</hi> and the <hi>Heavens</hi> in a <hi>flame</hi> before thee; thy <hi>Soul</hi> is the Subſtance of the <hi>Creation</hi> of GOD, and thine <hi>Eyes</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> of the Day; thy <hi>Teeth</hi> are as the <hi>Angels</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> in the Heavens, to fight thy Battel on Earth; thy <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>outh</hi> is the <hi>Door</hi> of the <hi>Counſel</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> and thy <hi>Tongue</hi> the <hi>Teacher</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. O! the <hi>Earth,</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> is confounded before thee. I am as a <hi>Wren</hi> in the Earth, loſt under the ſtretching of thy <hi>Wing;</hi> I began in the <hi>ſhallow places,</hi> but am over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed as a <hi>Worm</hi> in the <hi>deeps</hi> of <hi>GOD;</hi> no man hath <hi>comprehended</hi> thy <hi>Glory;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let him bear his <hi>Judgement</hi> for ever, that faſhions thee like unto a <hi>graven thing,</hi> or that makes an <hi>Image</hi> of thy <hi>CHRIST;</hi> Let him bear the perpetual <hi>ſhame</hi> of his <hi>folly,</hi> and the <hi>judgment</hi> of thy <hi>dreadful Word;</hi> Let his own <hi>ſoul</hi> eat his <hi>confuſion,</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> up the <hi>dregs</hi> of his <hi>condemnation;</hi> for <hi>Glory</hi> is thine in the <hi>higheſt,</hi> who art only <hi>known</hi> to the <hi>pure</hi> in <hi>heart,</hi> and <hi>remembred</hi> of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33625:59"/>
               <hi>Upright</hi> in the Earth. An <hi>Image</hi> is a mark of the <hi>unmindfulneſs</hi> of thy <hi>Name,</hi> and a ſign of the <hi>forgetfulneſs</hi> of thy <hi>Preſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O <hi>Seed,</hi> ſtand up as <hi>a Sign</hi> to the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and as an <hi>Enſign</hi> to the <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> that they may be gathered to the Knowledge of the <hi>LORD</hi> thy <hi>GOD,</hi> to remember Him as <hi>a God</hi> that is preſent, even at hand, for <hi>Iudgment</hi> to the <hi>Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> of his own <hi>Elect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Call, call</hi> for thy <hi>Courage,</hi> and <hi>cry aloud</hi> for thy <hi>Strength,</hi> and <hi>cloath</hi> thy ſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, as in the dayes of old; <hi>ſtretch forth</hi> thine <hi>Hand</hi> in thy <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>draw back</hi> the Clouds of the <hi>Night;</hi> Appear thou <hi>Sun</hi> of the <hi>Morning,</hi> as ſetled in the <hi>Heavens</hi> above, that the <hi>Nations</hi> may flow to thy <hi>Light,</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> to the <hi>brightneſs</hi> of thy Riſing; that the <hi>Iſles</hi> may be <hi>gathered</hi> in <hi>one,</hi> to wait for the <hi>Law</hi> at thy <hi>Mouth;</hi> that the <hi>tongue</hi> of the <hi>Egyptian Sea</hi> may be dryed up, and but <hi>One</hi> pure <hi>Language</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the <hi>Earth;</hi> and that the <hi>Earth</hi> be filled with the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> as Waters <hi>cover</hi> the Seas.</p>
            <p>It was once <hi>ſaid,</hi> and the Voice anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Until how long?</hi> And the Spirit ſaid, <hi>Until the determination of the time appointed,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33625:59"/>
even until the fulfilling of the Abomination of Deſolation in the Earth, and it ſeen to ſtand in the Holy Place.</hi> Then ſaid the <hi>Angel, The mighty <hi>Dreadful Day</hi> of GOD is at hand. <hi>Awake, awake</hi> to the Judgment of the <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Day</hi> of the LORD. <hi>Fear GOD,</hi> and give Honour and Glory to his Name.</hi> O that thine <hi>Innocency</hi> were known in the Land, &amp; thy <hi>Love</hi> received in the Earth! Thou art as the <hi>Innocent Lamb</hi> of the Flocks, and as the <hi>New-born Babe</hi> at the <hi>Breaſt;</hi> thou art as the <hi>Turtle</hi> which flyeth in fear, and as her <hi>young</hi> in the Neſt without guile; thy <hi>Love</hi> is as the <hi>Mother</hi> to her <hi>comly Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and as the <hi>Father</hi> to his <hi>only Son;</hi> thy <hi>Love</hi> is as the <hi>Spouſe</hi> to her <hi>Welbeloved,</hi> and as the <hi>Bridegroom</hi> wedded to his <hi>beautiful Virgin;</hi> it paſſeth the <hi>love</hi> of <hi>Women,</hi> thy <hi>Bonds</hi> are ſtronger than <hi>Death;</hi> thou bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the <hi>greif</hi> of thy <hi>Love,</hi> for becauſe of thy <hi>Love</hi> thou art <hi>hated:</hi> I love the <hi>love</hi> of thy <hi>Love,</hi> and do bear the burden <hi>thereof;</hi> I love the <hi>bonds</hi> of thy <hi>Love,</hi> for becauſe of thy <hi>Love</hi> thou art <hi>bound;</hi> O make thy <hi>Love</hi> thy <hi>Battel,</hi> and the <hi>bent</hi> of thy <hi>Bow</hi> in the Earth, that he which hath <hi>pierced</hi> thee may <hi>mourn,</hi> and be <hi>broken</hi> in the bowels of <hi>Love;</hi> that the <hi>Mountains</hi> may be melted before
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:33625:60"/>
thee, and the <hi>Hils</hi> drop down like Wax; and gather to the Body of <hi>Love,</hi> where neither <hi>Envy</hi> nor <hi>Lyes</hi> have life: Spread forth thy <hi>Arms</hi> in <hi>love,</hi> that thy meaſure be filled in the Earth; For <hi>Scorners</hi> do hiſs at the <hi>kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of thine heart, and mock at the <hi>meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of thy mind; thine Arrows of <hi>Love</hi> be their <hi>wound,</hi> to pierce them to the heart in their ſeat; Overcome with the <hi>Love</hi> which <hi>created,</hi> and perfect the Glory of <hi>GOD;</hi> Make known thy <hi>Self</hi> as thou art, a <hi>Leader</hi> in the Righteouſneſs of GOD: Inſtruct the <hi>ſimple</hi> thy way, and <hi>confound</hi> the <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> thereby: Thy <hi>Way</hi> is the <hi>path</hi> of the <hi>Just,</hi> the <hi>ſinner</hi> cannot walk therein; it is a <hi>Guide</hi> to the <hi>Wayfaring-man,</hi> the <hi>Fools</hi> cannot erre therein; The <hi>Wiſe</hi> do <hi>ſtumble</hi> in their ſight, and the <hi>Subtil</hi> do <hi>fall</hi> before them; which maketh the <hi>Heathen rage,</hi> and all the <hi>Diviners mad:</hi> Open, open thy <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom</hi> to thy <hi>lovers,</hi> and thy <hi>Treaſure</hi> to the <hi>ſoul</hi> which <hi>ſeeks</hi> thee; which ſpareth not <hi>Life</hi> from the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> nor <hi>Lust</hi> from the <hi>flaming Sword,</hi> but layeth the Neck at the Yoak, to yeeld the <hi>Firſt-born</hi> unto Death: Thy <hi>Treaſure</hi> is the body of Wiſdom, more <hi>pure</hi> than <hi>refined Gold:</hi> Thy <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is as the <hi>Oracles of GOD,</hi> and <hi>Counſel</hi> of the Moſt
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33625:60"/>
High: Thou <hi>feedeſt</hi> thy own with the <hi>Life,</hi> with <hi>Wiſdom</hi> the ſubſtance of <hi>Life:</hi> The <hi>Swine</hi> feed on <hi>husks</hi> as a prey, and run to a <hi>ſhadow</hi> for ſhelter: In <hi>Winter</hi> they wander in the <hi>Woods,</hi> and in <hi>Summer</hi> they wallow in the <hi>Mire:</hi> The <hi>Serpent</hi> licks up the <hi>duſt</hi> of the ground, and <hi>hideth</hi> in a hole of the Earth; But thou buildeſt a <hi>Nurſery</hi> for <hi>Babes,</hi> and a <hi>Dwelling</hi> for the Sons of <hi>God;</hi> Thou makeſt <hi>a Bed</hi> for the <hi>Virgin,</hi> and ſhe is kept as <hi>a Bride</hi> for the Lamb: Thou makeſt the <hi>ſimple</hi> as an <hi>Hoſt,</hi> to battle with the <hi>Armies</hi> of <hi>Gog;</hi> thou giveſt thy <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> in the Day, and the <hi>weak</hi> is made ſtrong for the War: The <hi>Philiſtine</hi> flouriſheth his <hi>Sword,</hi> but it is kept for the <hi>wound</hi> of his body: The <hi>weak</hi> turneth back the force of the <hi>Giant,</hi> and <hi>ſlayeth him</hi> with his <hi>own Sword;</hi> he takes not <hi>Glory</hi> to his hand, but yeeldeth his <hi>heart</hi> to his <hi>GOD:</hi> By <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> the Kingdom is <hi>created,</hi> and <hi>folded</hi> in <hi>ſecret</hi> from the <hi>Wicked;</hi> he which caſteth his <hi>Crown</hi> at thy <hi>feet,</hi> thy <hi>Glory</hi> ſhall cover his <hi>head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is without <hi>respect to any man's per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> whether <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> A <hi>Viſitation</hi> of the <hi>Love</hi> of GOD to the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33625:61"/>
               <hi>Seed;</hi> And be it his <hi>Woe</hi> for <hi>ever</hi> and <hi>ever</hi> that keeps it back.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dispenſed from the Inquiſition-Priſon in</hi> Rome.</dateline>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Righteous REASON, written as a <hi>REMONSTRANCE</hi> to <hi>Romes</hi> Rulers, Touching the <hi>Impriſonment</hi> and <hi>Perſecution</hi> of the Servant of <hi>JESUS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>ROME</hi> being called of her Inhabitants, <hi>The Head of the World,</hi> and <hi>Holy City;</hi> and her Church, <hi>the Mother of many Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> cryed up as <hi>the moſt famous</hi> (in Faith, Doctrine, Life, and practice of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of the Lord Jeſus) <hi>of all Peoples upon the face of the Earth;</hi> To her <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> therefore I am willing to offer this <hi>entrance</hi> of the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> of my <hi>Cauſe,</hi> in a <hi>compendious Tract,</hi> by the <hi>repreſentation</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> the <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>holy Judges,</hi> the <hi>Commandments, Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Example</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:33625:61"/>
of the <hi>LORD JESUS,</hi> with what elſe occaſionally may be <hi>intervenially</hi> inſerted in the ſame; to be placed as a <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> of <hi>Equity</hi> in all the Courts of <hi>Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory</hi> in her City.</p>
            <p>I <hi>John</hi> the Servant of <hi>JESUS</hi> [in the holy and bleſſed Calling of the <hi>Quaking</hi> and <hi>Trembling</hi> at the <hi>Word</hi> of the LORD GOD] upon the ſixth day of the fourth moneth, in the year, 1658, arrived in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> with humble deſire of attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſight</hi> and <hi>ſpeech</hi> with the <hi>Pope;</hi> the which not <hi>fooliſhly,</hi> or <hi>preſumptuouſly</hi> did I ſeek; but in all <hi>ſobriety</hi> and <hi>modesty,</hi> made orderly <hi>proceed,</hi> in as many ſteps as I trod in the path of this progreſs; the which is well known unto divers of <hi>Eminent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> of your own Sect, within your City Walls.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch as firſt of all, I opened my deſired <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> and ſaid <hi>End,</hi> unto <hi>Thomas Courtney,</hi> Jeſuite, and <hi>Engliſh Confeſſor</hi> of <hi>Peters,</hi> from whom I received <hi>Advice,</hi> and, in due order thereunto, made exact <hi>progreſs,</hi> by paſſing, next and immediately from him, to <hi>John Crey,</hi> Iriſhman, and Chaplain to the <hi>Pope;</hi> before whom in like manner I ſpread my ſaid <hi>Deſire,</hi> as an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33625:62"/>
ſheet</hi> upon a ſmooth floor. At which time ſeveral words paſſed between us, of which I retain a full remembrance, though not eſteemed of ſuch weight, but may be waved at preſent, to the end, <hi>Lines</hi> of more <hi>conſequence,</hi> and more <hi>properly pertinent</hi> to the <hi>inſtant purpoſe,</hi> may rule the ſide of my Paper; and therefore do proceed, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</p>
            <p>That upon the eighth of the ſaid month and year, I was (by the Chief <hi>Marſhal</hi> of the City, and his Guard) taken out of Bed, in my Lodging, at the ſign of the <hi>Cock</hi> in <hi>Piazza Fornaſe,</hi> ſtripped of all things, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Apparrel which I wore; and ſo at a late hour of the night was led bound to one of the <hi>New Priſons,</hi> where the <hi>ſecond day</hi> I was briefly <hi>interrogated</hi> by the <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> of the City, who at the ſame time, verbally conceaded me <hi>conſent</hi> to my <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> of a ſudden, fair and publick Tryal at <hi>Tribunal</hi> of <hi>Law;</hi> the which <hi>Equal deed</hi> mine Eye never ſaw put in execution and practice, unto this inſtant day of my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it came to paſs, that before <hi>ſix days</hi> were <hi>expired,</hi> with a <hi>ſecond Guard</hi> I was taken from thence, bound in a <hi>Coach,</hi> and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33625:62"/>
tranſported to the <hi>Inquiſition-Priſon;</hi> at which Office and Priſon, divers of your <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Orders</hi> came to <hi>ſeek,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>full</hi> and <hi>plain ſpeech</hi> from me: And after that a ſhort ſpace of time had <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,</hi> there was adhibited me a <hi>free</hi> and <hi>lawful Priviledge, (viz.) <hi>The ſolid, clear, and incontradicted Licence, to write my mind in whatſoever thing I would;</hi>
               </hi> to which purpoſe, and as an <hi>Authentick te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony</hi> of the ſame, him called the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Commiſſary</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed me <hi>Pen, Ink,</hi> and <hi>Paper;</hi> with the uſe whereof I faithfully forwarded the matter of clearing my Conſcience, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a naked <hi>Explication</hi> of the <hi>words of Righteouſneſs,</hi> in ſundry <hi>Manuſcrips,</hi> and an <hi>Epiſtle general to the Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover it came to paſs, that I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been about 18. <hi>weeks</hi> cloſe <hi>Priſoner,</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> was the third time <hi>bound,</hi> and again in a <hi>Coach</hi> tranſported from thence unto this <hi>Priſon</hi> of <hi>Mad-men;</hi> where I have reſted (in the Peace and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of the Lord Jeſus, as one of his Innocent Lambs) under much <hi>hardſhip</hi> and ſeverity; the which I over-paſs, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on in the <hi>Progreſs,</hi> and <hi>ſuccedently</hi> to ſhew forth, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:33625:63"/>Concerning my more than <hi>two years <hi>Perſecution,</hi>
               </hi> under <hi>Authority</hi> of your ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction.</p>
            <p>Known be it unto you, O all ye <hi>Heads, Rulers,</hi> and <hi>Judges</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> That there was not an <hi>act</hi> done by me in your City (for which I am perſecuted) which any <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Precept</hi> of his Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> doth condemn; and am ſure, where Righteous <hi>Judges</hi> perſpicuouſly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the matter, from no <hi>righteous ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Law</hi> could <hi>judge,</hi> either worthy of <hi>Bonds</hi> or of <hi>blame;</hi> for the things which your Sect do call <hi>Hereſies,</hi> which were the <hi>Writings</hi> that were found with me, though of a truth my <hi>Intention</hi> was naked to <hi>God</hi> (the which (when apprehended) I hid not from you) to <hi>diſpenſe</hi> them, as they were <hi>directed</hi> to you, ſome <hi>folded,</hi> and others <hi>ſealed;</hi> yet not any of the ſaid Papers, being <hi>actually diſpenſed</hi> in this your City, before I was <hi>Apprehended;</hi> conſequently <hi>not matter of Fact</hi> to be charged upon me, as <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> of a <hi>Law,</hi> and ſo not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of theſe <hi>Bonds;</hi> the which you may plainly <hi>perceive</hi> alſo by the ſucceeding <hi>il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> From the word of <hi>Affirmation</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:33625:63"/>
of one of your <hi>Fathers</hi> (a Confeſſor) unto me, ſhewing the Erection of the <hi>Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> by a <hi>Law,</hi> was not to <hi>perſecute,</hi> but purpoſely and properly to <hi>ſtop</hi> the in-cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of ſuch <hi>things,</hi> as the ſaid my <hi>Writings,</hi> (which he reputed none other, but as a dangerous Impreſs of Hereſies,) the which <hi>when ſtopt,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> was <hi>fulfill'd,</hi> and in Equity, had its <hi>uttermoſt end;</hi> and ſo much the clearer, becauſe the matter was not <hi>a Fact actual,</hi> but a <hi>purpoſe Intentional,</hi> the which no Righteous <hi>Law</hi> calleth <hi>criminal,</hi> ſeeing not any word therein was <hi>carnally evil,</hi> or, relating to any mans perſon, <hi>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally treaſonable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe that whereas in the <hi>Inquiſition-Office</hi> (declared to be erected for the prevention of the influences of Heretical and Schiſmatical Opinions) was <hi>adhibited me,</hi> the <hi>free</hi> and lawful <hi>Licence</hi> and Priviledge to <hi>Write</hi> whatſoever <hi>things</hi> I would; the Righteous <hi>Judge</hi> in his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, will not impute that <hi>thing</hi> unto me, as <hi>Tranſgreſſion</hi> of the Law, in the City, which is a licenced <hi>Priviledge</hi> adhibited me, by the <hi>Ruling Power</hi> over the City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe it is well <hi>known,</hi> that not in any of my <hi>Papers,</hi> (which were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33625:64"/>
from me) there were words, (which your particular Judgements do eſteem Hereſies) which you could call <hi>more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Hereſies,</hi> than <hi>in them</hi> which I had <hi>free</hi> and <hi>lawful admiſſion of Writing;</hi> whence the palpability of Reaſon, <hi>infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth</hi> the infallibility of <hi>Concluſion,</hi> not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy (as precited) either of <hi>Bonds,</hi> or of <hi>Blame;</hi> for before an entrance of the <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> of <hi>Condemnation</hi> might judiciouſly <hi>approach me</hi> herein, it would firſt take its proper <hi>Stage</hi> rationally, to reach your <hi>own Members;</hi> and thereby, if the Law could implead <hi>any</hi> at the <hi>Bar</hi> as a <hi>Tranſgreſſor,</hi> me, in mine <hi>Innocency,</hi> it would <hi>acquit,</hi> and charge the <hi>guilt</hi> on the <hi>heads</hi> of them <hi>Heads,</hi> which at the laſt <hi>adhibited</hi> me the <hi>free Liberty</hi> to <hi>Write,</hi> and ſo to <hi>diſpence</hi> to you whatſoever I <hi>would;</hi> without which I the <hi>Priſoner</hi> could not have <hi>done</hi> the thing <hi>acted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Becauſe the ſaid <hi>later Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,</hi> whilſt I was <hi>a Priſoner,</hi> being <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledged,</hi> do in the perſpicuity of Reaſon <hi>hold forth,</hi> That the former, <hi>written whilſt I was at Liberty,</hi> do ſtand with ſuitable <hi>aſſent</hi> of one of theſe three, <hi>(viz.)</hi> firſt, <hi>Either according to your Law;</hi> or ſecondly,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:33625:64"/>
               <hi>Not contrary to the rule of your Law</hi> (that is to ſay) <hi>a Law not ſtanding in potential record againſt them;</hi> and to that, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Where there is <hi>no Law,</hi> there is <hi>no Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion;</hi>
               </hi> or otherwiſe, at utmoſt, you conſtantly <hi>avouching</hi> that they <hi>were againſt your Law.</hi> Finally, the <hi>Rule of Equity</hi> ſtandeth to <hi>test,</hi> that of a truth, it was <hi>your ſelves,</hi> which by the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Aſſent,</hi> firſt <hi>nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led that Law,</hi> and ſo no more ſtands in <hi>force</hi> of a <hi>Law,</hi> to <hi>judge</hi> me <hi>now</hi> as a <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſour;</hi> for, except that it were not <hi>againſt a Law,</hi> or that you had made <hi>void</hi> and <hi>null</hi> that <hi>Law,</hi> which you may ſay, that my <hi>Writings</hi> were againſt; then, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, could not I have <hi>written</hi> the <hi>things</hi> which I have <hi>written</hi> in your <hi>Inquiſition-Priſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Becauſe that all <hi>Righteous Laws</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> in Nations, touching <hi>Facts <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Crimes <hi>Capital,</hi>
               </hi> are no more to <hi>one perſon <hi>particular,</hi>
               </hi> than unto <hi>all men in <hi>general;</hi>
               </hi> And therefore my <hi>adhibition</hi> at laſt, to <hi>write</hi> things of the ſame <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>purpoſe</hi> in <hi>Priſon,</hi> which at firſt I did in the <hi>fruition</hi> of <hi>Liberty,</hi> demonſtrates, that your ſaid <hi>ſelf-nulled Law,</hi> (Under which (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the tenure of GOD's righteous
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33625:65"/>
Law) I am yet <hi>irrationally</hi> and <hi>compulſively</hi> held in your <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>Captivity</hi>) was not at firſt ſo much a <hi>ſtable Law,</hi> as an <hi>aiery vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able nicity;</hi> for that which (in ſuch caſes) <hi>adhibits</hi> to <hi>one,</hi> and <hi>prohibits</hi> the ſame to <hi>another,</hi> is rather like a <hi>wind</hi> of <hi>vanity,</hi> than a <hi>body</hi> or <hi>pillar</hi> of <hi>ſolidity,</hi> ſeeing that it will admit of the <hi>respect of perſons</hi> in <hi>Judgement,</hi> and conſequently what equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity there is, in <hi>reſtraining</hi> of <hi>perſons,</hi> more than <hi>two years,</hi> upon the account of a <hi>chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable curioſity,</hi> and <hi>aiery nicity; <hi>judge thee, O thou righteous Iudge, in the high ſeat of ſuperiority.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Becauſe the <hi>Eternal Spirit</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> my Maker, which <hi>ſearcheth</hi> all hearts, and <hi>tryeth</hi> all reins; which is the <hi>greatest Witneſs</hi> of all <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> beareth <hi>teſtimony</hi> in my <hi>ſpirit,</hi> that in all which I have <hi>written,</hi> have <hi>ſtood,</hi> and do <hi>ſtand</hi> in my Conſcience, <hi>clear, naked</hi> and <hi>void</hi> of <hi>all</hi> and <hi>every part</hi> of a <hi>prejudicial mind,</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception</hi> of <hi>Envy, Wrath, Malice, Scorn,</hi> or <hi>despightful Contempt</hi> of any man's <hi>perſon;</hi> neither have I thereby wronged any <hi>man</hi> whatſoever; for all that is therein <hi>inſerted,</hi> is none other, but <hi>wholſom Admonitions,</hi> exciting to a more <hi>peculiar, holy,</hi> and <hi>bleſſed
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33625:65"/>
life,</hi> towards <hi>GOD</hi> and a man's <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour;</hi> with certain <hi>ſolid, ſober Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> which tend not to the cuſtom of <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh ſtrifes</hi> and <hi>conteſts</hi> in the <hi>envious</hi> and <hi>malicious ſpirit</hi> of <hi>bitterneſs;</hi> but purely, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely and reverently in the <hi>humble ſpirit</hi> of <hi>fear</hi> of the <hi>LORD GOD,</hi> to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and ſole end of the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> through the <hi>Salvation</hi> of <hi>Souls,</hi> by his <hi>heavenly enlightning</hi> of <hi>Understandings,</hi> with the <hi>Glory</hi> of his <hi>holy Spirit;</hi> And ſavoury <hi>reprehenſions</hi> of that <hi>ſpirit</hi> which <hi>ſinneth,</hi> and teſtimony againſt the <hi>Evils</hi> of the Land, and the inſertion of ſundry <hi>ſpiritual My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi> of the <hi>heavenly Kingdom,</hi> with the ſpiritual Witneſs of the <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>holy Ghoſt;</hi> and nothing therein contrary to the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> the <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>immaculate Life</hi> of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> nor any thing in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to that chaſt Spirit of Sanctity, which was in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> or any which was, or is, as that <hi>bleſſed Virgin was,</hi> which (upon further and due tryal) I am able (in the grace and power of GOD, and the Life of our Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi>) to make appear unto that of God in you, and all men whatſoever (which my Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage can underſtand) upon the face of the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:33625:66"/>
Earth; In which thing being juſtified, Firſt, <hi>by GOD which ſent me.</hi> Secondly, <hi>By example of the holy Prophets of old.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>By the practice of CHRIST and his Apoſtles, which at large</hi> (through the Mercy of the Lord God Almighty) <hi>I am alſo able to hold forth unto you</hi> (in the day of due tryal) <hi>according to the undeniable Record, and Witneſs of the holy Scriptures of Truth;</hi> And therfore Righteouſneſs ſaith, Becauſe that the nature of the matter was of a <hi>pure purpoſe,</hi> ſhould rationally have been <hi>recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced</hi> by you with none other than a <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian-like practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Becauſe the ſweet <hi>ſavour</hi> and good <hi>report</hi> of our <hi>Innocency</hi> came to your City before us, which God made divers of your <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Members</hi> to confeſs in plainneſs of ſpeech to my face.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Becauſe the <hi>Witneſs of GOD,</hi> which is greater than the <hi>Witneſs of Man,</hi> teſtified in my <hi>ſpirit,</hi> That all my <hi>honest Queries,</hi> ſweet and holy <hi>Admonitions,</hi> pure <hi>Advertiſments,</hi> &amp; godly <hi>Reprehenſions,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from no other, but as <hi>Cryſtal ſtreams</hi> from the <hi>fountain</hi> of the <hi>Father's Love,</hi> which he hath made as a <hi>Well</hi> of <hi>Waters</hi> in my <hi>bowels;</hi> And principally, becauſe that
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33625:66"/>
               <hi>Reprehenſion</hi> is an <hi>infallible token</hi> of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Love</hi> to his <hi>Seed</hi> in all Nations and Lands, teſtified by the Spirit to <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle, ſaying, <hi>Whom I love, I <hi>rebuke</hi> and <hi>chaſten;</hi> be zealous therefore and repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> Becauſe it is the <hi>undeniable Duty</hi> of <hi>all</hi> men upon the face of the Earth, to <hi>love the Rebukes of the LORD;</hi> as it is purely the <hi>LORD's Mercy,</hi> and of his <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Love,</hi> to ſend them as <hi>Viſitations</hi> of his <hi>Love</hi> unto all Nations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> Becauſe the <hi>reſisting</hi> of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke,</hi> is the <hi>reſiſting</hi> of the <hi>token</hi> of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>GOD;</hi> which renders men <hi>unworthy</hi> of the <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Mercies</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> their Maker: And becauſe it <hi>vails</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> from the <hi>life</hi> of the <hi>true Zeal</hi> in ſpirit, and hardens the <hi>heart</hi> in the Wrath of <hi>Cain</hi> towards <hi>Abel,</hi> of <hi>Eſau</hi> to <hi>Jacob,</hi> and of the <hi>Jews</hi> to <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. Becauſe the Righteous <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is of the ſame <hi>nature,</hi> full of <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Reprehenſion</hi> of every <hi>Evil,</hi> not reſpecting the <hi>Perſon</hi> of any <hi>man,</hi> and is at <hi>unity</hi> with every ſuch <hi>ſpirit</hi> of its own <hi>nature</hi> in ſo <hi>good</hi> a work; for the which cauſe it was righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly added of <hi>GOD:</hi> for if there were <hi>no bridle,</hi> how ſhould the <hi>Beast</hi> be tamed?
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:33625:67"/>
if <hi>no Helm,</hi> how ſhould the <hi>Ship</hi> be ſailed? And without <hi>Correction,</hi> there is no <hi>perfect Inſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. Becauſe the <hi>Rebuke</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> is as a <hi>Steel</hi> which ſmiteth at the <hi>Flint</hi> of man's <hi>heart,</hi> and kindleth in his <hi>Internals,</hi> the <hi>fire</hi> of the <hi>fear</hi> of his <hi>Creator,</hi> which is the <hi>beginning of Wiſdom,</hi> which reveals the <hi>knowledge</hi> of the <hi>countenance</hi> of the <hi>Father,</hi> whom <hi>to know, is Life eternal:</hi> and becauſe of <hi>Solomon's</hi> proverbial commendation of the work of <hi>Reprehenſion,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof</hi> of the Righteous, is like Apples of Gold in Pictures of Silver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. Becauſe, as the <hi>matter</hi> of my ſaid <hi>Writings</hi> is manifeſtly compoſed of <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> and covered with the <hi>Countenance</hi> of the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>GOD;</hi> ſo the <hi>manner</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſtands in <hi>unity</hi> with the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apostles,</hi> which were in the <hi>nature</hi> of <hi>Divinity,</hi> which covereth not <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> with daubing <hi>Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. Becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> the <hi>Meſſenger</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> juſtified him which <hi>propheſied in the Camp,</hi> (whom the People complained againſt) thus anſwering and ſaying, <hi>Would God all the Lords People were Prophets.</hi> And becauſe GOD Almighty is unchangeably
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33625:67"/>
the <hi>ſame,</hi> as <hi>yeſterday,</hi> ſo <hi>this day,</hi> and for <hi>ever;</hi> of theſe <hi>ſtones</hi> able to raiſe <hi>a Seed</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. Becauſe of the <hi>amiable Example</hi> of the geſture of <hi>David</hi> the <hi>King</hi> under the <hi>ſharp Reprehenſion</hi> of <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet; who perſecuted not the <hi>Prophet,</hi> but with a <hi>contrite ſpirit</hi> repented of his own ſin. And the like of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>People</hi> of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> who perſecuted not <hi>Jonah,</hi> though he cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their <hi>Deſtruction</hi> in the <hi>Streets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. Becauſe the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied it, as the <hi>great Evil</hi> of ſuch a People, which would make a man <hi>an Offender for a Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. Becauſe that for the <hi>ſame things,</hi> (like unto them, my ſaid Writings in <hi>life</hi> and <hi>nature</hi>) the <hi>Prophets, CHRIST,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> (by ungodly and unrighteous Rulers) were <hi>perſecuted</hi> and made <hi>ſufferers</hi> in the world; And becauſe from the day of <hi>Cain's Cruelty,</hi> even unto this <hi>moment,</hi> there was never any other <hi>ſpirit</hi> in the world, which did or doth <hi>perſecute</hi> any ſoul for his <hi>pure Conſcience</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> beſides the thick ſpirit of <hi>darkneſs,</hi> which is of the old Serpent the <hi>Devil,</hi> to which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in his day held his Teſtimony, ſaying, <hi>As it
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33625:68"/>
was <hi>then,</hi> he that was born after the fleſh, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted him that was born after the Spirit, even ſo it is <hi>now.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. Becauſe the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>CHRIST</hi> teacheth his Church, to <hi>recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence</hi> all men <hi>good</hi> for <hi>evil,</hi> and not any man <hi>evil</hi> for <hi>evil;</hi> ſeeing the recompence of <hi>evil</hi> for <hi>evil</hi> rendreth men manifeſtly as <hi>children</hi> of the <hi>Devil;</hi> and much more the rendring <hi>evil actual,</hi> for the work of <hi>good ſincerely intentional.</hi> And becauſe that <hi>Chriſt reprehended</hi> that ſpirit of <hi>Revenge</hi> in the youth of his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> which would have had <hi>Fire</hi> come down from <hi>Heaven</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy his <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> ſaying, <hi>You know not of what ſpirit you are.</hi> Who, though the <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Power</hi> of the <hi>Father</hi> was with Him, (which could do all things) yet <hi>perſecuted</hi> no man, but ſuffered <hi>all things.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we do not <hi>perſecute you,</hi> nor <hi>any</hi> other <hi>Sect</hi> beſide you.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Becauſe that when <hi>CHRIST</hi> ſo ſharply reprehended <hi>Peter,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan:</hi> And when he ſaid alſo to the <hi>Jews, You are of your father the Devil, and the lust of your father you will do,</hi> and <hi>he was a lyar from the beginning:</hi> Neither his <hi>friend</hi> nor his <hi>foes</hi> perſecuted
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:33625:68"/>
Him with that <hi>bitterneſs,</hi> wherewith you have perſecuted me. I might moreover inſtance <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> crying againſt the <hi>Temple,</hi> which once <hi>GOD</hi> commanded; <hi>Paul's</hi> Reprehenſion of the High Prieſt; <hi>Peter's</hi> of <hi>Simon Magus; Paul's</hi> Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Reproof to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> in the open Court of the <hi>Arreopageans;</hi> with many other Acts of <hi>CHRIST</hi> and his <hi>Apostles;</hi> yea, and a <hi>Cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to the day of Judgement, and to teſtifie the <hi>Innocency</hi> of the <hi>Juſt</hi> at the <hi>open Bar</hi> of <hi>Tribunal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. Becauſe the <hi>Kingdom, Weapons,</hi> and <hi>Warfare</hi> of the <hi>LORD JESUS</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> were not, nor are not <hi>carnal,</hi> but <hi>ſpiritual;</hi> and alſo becauſe my <hi>Writings, Sayings,</hi> and <hi>Speeches</hi> are not <hi>carnal,</hi> nor tending to a <hi>carnal end,</hi> but <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,</hi> tending to a <hi>ſpiritual life,</hi> without <hi>end;</hi> The which <hi>ſpiritual Holineſs,</hi> if you call <hi>ſpiritual Wickedneſs,</hi> yet profeſſing your ſelves to be the <hi>Church,</hi> which is the <hi>Body,</hi> ſhould conſequently in the <hi>Channel</hi> and <hi>clear Courſe</hi> of the <hi>running River</hi> of <hi>Righteous REASON,</hi> be ſubject unto <hi>CHRIST,</hi> whom you confeſs to be the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Body</hi> to be
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:33625:69"/>
ſubject to the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Head,</hi> and not to make the <hi>Head</hi> ſubject to the <hi>luſt</hi> of your <hi>body;</hi> and then you would do as <hi>CHRIST</hi> did, and as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> practiſed, cut down the <hi>ſpiritual Wickedneſs</hi> with <hi>ſpiritual Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons:</hi> For when the <hi>Jews</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Jeſus, Thou hast a Devil, and in the name of</hi> Beel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub <hi>doſt cast out Devils:</hi> the <hi>LORD</hi> (then, whom you are not greater, in whoſe hand all Power was) <hi>perſecuted</hi> not their <hi>perſons,</hi> but fought with them with the <hi>ſpiritual Weapons,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>If I in the name of the Prince of Devils do caſt out Devils, then is his Kingdom divided;</hi> and ſo with the <hi>ſpiritual Weapons</hi> cut down the <hi>ſpiritual Wickedneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the things which I call <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reaſon</hi> to every <hi>righteous rational man living.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Foraſmuch alſo as for more than two years ſpace (as precited) and in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the interval of the ſaid time, as op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, ſundry and divers, were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, I having in the ſpirit of ſobriety moved, and modeſtly urged for an <hi>open, fair</hi> and <hi>legal Tryal,</hi> according to the holy Law of GOD, and of his Son <hi>JESUS CHRIST,</hi> which righteouſly regulateth
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33625:69"/>
among his Church, the which was many times <hi>promiſed,</hi> but being hitherto never <hi>performed,</hi> may give <hi>juſt occaſion</hi> unto every perſon of prudent underſtanding, which hath, or may hear thereof, to conceive that my <hi>continued Reſtriction,</hi> thus debarred from the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Equity,</hi> is of the nature of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from, and conſequently in <hi>Antipathy</hi> unto the <hi>ſage, moral Ty</hi> of <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity,</hi> and all things which are of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Subſtance <hi>heavenly;</hi> And that from the conſideration of the <hi>ſubſequent cauſes,</hi> which I the rather <hi>intimate,</hi> from the <hi>cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> that they may be rationally as an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement</hi> and <hi>Inſtigation</hi> of you, to <hi>expediate</hi> my hitherto <hi>detarded Tryal</hi> at <hi>open Tribunal</hi> of <hi>Law,</hi> where I may juſtly find <hi>ample Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to <hi>illuſtrate</hi> (unto all attending <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions</hi>) the perſpicuity of the <hi>Defence</hi> of mine <hi>Innocency;</hi> In due <hi>progreſs</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, therefore, from this Spirit of <hi>meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> O ye <hi>Rulers</hi> of <hi>ROME,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe the <hi>ſimple, proper, pure, ſolid,</hi> and <hi>ſole end</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> and all Righteous Laws of <hi>Nations,</hi> is <hi>really, righteouſly,</hi> and <hi>equally,</hi> for the <hi>expedition</hi> of <hi>Judgment</hi> on <hi>every Tranſgreſſor,</hi> for the <hi>fact</hi>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:33625:70"/>
of his <hi>Tranſgreſſion,</hi> without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for the <hi>perfecting Righteouſneſs</hi> in the Earth: and where the <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> is made <hi>void,</hi> there the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the whole <hi>Law</hi> is deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe <hi>puniſhment</hi> inflicted upon any man by any <hi>Judge</hi> or <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> which hath a <hi>Law</hi> without <hi>Judgment,</hi> and <hi>open Conviction</hi> by the <hi>Law,</hi> is not, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Righteouſneſs, ſo much an act of <hi>Equity,</hi> as directly contrary <hi>to all Law,</hi> and unreaſonable conſtriction of the <hi>cruelty</hi> of <hi>Tyranny;</hi> and ſuch an <hi>Act</hi> ſtains the glory of his Tribunal of <hi>Authority:</hi> For by a <hi>Law</hi> he holdeth the Seat of his <hi>Superiority,</hi> and the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Judgement,</hi> by the Law being the Glory of the <hi>Chair</hi> of his <hi>Magistracy; Judgment</hi> being pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the <hi>Juſt Tribunal</hi> is overturned, and thereby the <hi>Glory</hi> thereof rendred as a <hi>ſtage</hi> of <hi>Infamy:</hi> And thus the <hi>Law</hi> being <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated,</hi> mark what follows, The Land by <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs</hi> ruined.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe the <hi>conſtriction,</hi> and <hi>continuation</hi> of <hi>Bonds</hi> through <hi>ſuſpence</hi> of <hi>Judgment,</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of a <hi>Perſon</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>open Conviction</hi> by the <hi>Law,</hi> ſtands in contrariety to the pure
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:33625:70"/>
               <hi>practice</hi> and <hi>life</hi> of <hi>true Christianity,</hi> which actually leadeth to the <hi>doing unto all men, as a man would that another ſhould do unto him;</hi> in which alſo conſiſts both the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets.</hi> And becauſe it is but of the ſame, which the Proverb rendreth moſt infamous, ſaying, <hi>Hang a man first, and Judge him afterwards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Becauſe it is expreſly in <hi>oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> to the pure Nature of <hi>GOD</hi> your <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator,</hi> who looketh for the work of <hi>Judgment</hi> in the <hi>Land,</hi> and ſent <hi>Judgment</hi> into that Land, in which the Righteouſneſs thereof was <hi>ſcanted;</hi> and where againſt the <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> the <hi>Judgment</hi> thereof is found <hi>delayed</hi> and <hi>ſuſpended,</hi> there the <hi>meaſure</hi> is <hi>ſcanted,</hi> and the <hi>ballance</hi> falſified upon the <hi>Stall;</hi> and there the preſumptuous Luſt of <hi>irrational</hi> and <hi>unſatiable Will</hi> ruleth in the <hi>Seat</hi> of <hi>wrongful Revenge,</hi> in the enmity to the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> it ſelf, which was <hi>added</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> for the regulating of that <hi>gluttonous Luſt</hi> of the ſpirit of <hi>Revenge;</hi> and, ſo where the <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <hi>ſuſpended,</hi> there the <hi>wrongs</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries</hi> heaped upon the <hi>Innocent,</hi> never come (by the Magiſtrate) to be <hi>removed</hi> and <hi>ended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:33625:71"/>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Becauſe that in the Land where <hi>Judgment</hi> is not equally <hi>practiſed,</hi> but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſly <hi>detarded,</hi> and tediouſly <hi>ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> the fame thereof breaks an <hi>inlet</hi> in that Land, unto all <hi>Aſſaults, Deceits, Wrongs, Robberies, Riots, Rapes</hi> and <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;</hi> For there the Judge's <hi>Inſolencies</hi> is made the <hi>preſident</hi> of the <hi>Subjects Villanies;</hi> and there the <hi>two</hi> can ſup of <hi>one cup</hi> in the <hi>communication,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Give me of thy Broth,</hi> and lo, <hi>thou ſhalt partake of my Bread:</hi> And thus the <hi>Juſt</hi> is violently led to languiſh in the Land.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Becauſe through the <hi>ſuſpenſe</hi> of the <hi>Juſt Judgment</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> (which was added becauſe of Tranſgreſſion, and provided as God's Ordinance, for the removal of Oppreſſion) as the <hi>Innocent</hi> is thereby on the one hand <hi>oppreſſed,</hi> and his <hi>Yoak</hi> not broken, but <hi>ſtrengthened;</hi> ſo by the ſame, on the other hand, the <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor</hi> alſo receives not his <hi>due,</hi> but a <hi>wrong;</hi> and ſo no man hath <hi>right</hi> by the <hi>Law</hi> which God hath appointed for every <hi>man's right,</hi> either of <hi>Condemnation</hi> or <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification</hi> by due and open Tryal at <hi>Tribunal</hi> of <hi>Law;</hi> but thus the Law, which GOD hath ordained for the removal of <hi>Oppreſſion</hi>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:33625:71"/>
from all, through <hi>violation</hi> is <hi>converted,</hi> and made as an Inſtrument of <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> unto <hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Becauſe the <hi>ſuſpenſe</hi> of <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is contrary to the <hi>good Examples,</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed of <hi>God's holy men of old;</hi> Witneſs <hi>Moſes,</hi> and his <hi>true Succeſſors</hi> in the ſame <hi>ſeat;</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſe King, who when the <hi>cauſe</hi> of conteſt between the <hi>two women</hi> (concerning the <hi>living Child</hi>) came before him, delayed it not, but inſtantly <hi>called for a Sword,</hi> and thereby in the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> finding the <hi>true Mother,</hi> immediatly gave her <hi>her due:</hi> Likewiſe <hi>CHRIST,</hi> who ſuſpended not the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the Cauſe of the <hi>Harlot,</hi> but quickly judged, <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is free from ſin, let him cast the first ſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Becauſe the righteous Son of <hi>GOD,</hi> marked out that <hi>unjust Judge,</hi> (by the name of a man that <hi>feared not God,</hi> nor <hi>regarded man</hi>) who <hi>ſuſpended</hi> the Cauſe of the <hi>oppreſſed</hi> and <hi>wronged Widow,</hi> and <hi>judged</hi> it not for the ſake of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity,</hi> but detarded it, until he found himſelf <hi>wearied</hi> with the <hi>Widows importunity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> Becauſe the very <hi>Jews</hi> hard-heartedneſs <hi>ſuſpended</hi> not the <hi>Tryal</hi> of the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:33625:72"/>
               <hi>Just Man JESUS,</hi> by keeping him <hi>Two years,</hi> or more, under the <hi>temptation</hi> of the <hi>ſeverity of Bonds,</hi> to make him deny his <hi>Calling,</hi> and conſequently the <hi>Father</hi> which <hi>ſent him,</hi> but <hi>quickly</hi> and <hi>publickly</hi> (though unrighteouſly and againſt Law) <hi>judging</hi> Him <hi>worthy</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> expoſed him to the <hi>pangs</hi> of the <hi>ſame;</hi> and becauſe alſo the <hi>Jews</hi> in the ſame <hi>unbelief</hi> and <hi>hardneſs of heart,</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in the <hi>Heatheniſm</hi> and <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> divers times gave <hi>Audience,</hi> to the open Declaration of <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle in defence of his <hi>Righteous Cauſe.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, though it might have been appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended as an <hi>Affront</hi> to his <hi>Country-men,</hi> when he the ſaid <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> in the day of his <hi>Tryal</hi> in the Court of <hi>Judicature,</hi> appealed [from them] unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> yet becauſe of the <hi>Law,</hi> had his <hi>Appeal</hi> aſſented him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> Becauſe That <hi>Perſon</hi> whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, that under <hi>pretence</hi> of a <hi>Law,</hi> violates the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> by <hi>perverting the Law</hi> (as the <hi>Jews</hi> did in the Judgment of <hi>Jeſus</hi>) or by unequal <hi>ſuſpending</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> which is given into his hands, as a <hi>Stewardſhip,</hi> to handle, in equal admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of <hi>just Judgment</hi> unto all, without <hi>ſuſpenſe</hi> or <hi>reſpect of perſons,</hi> thus wilfully
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:33625:72"/>
acting in contrariety to all <hi>true humanity,</hi> the pure practice of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> the holy <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> and nature of the <hi>true GOD,</hi> appears manifeſtly (in the Chryſtal glaſs of the Law of Equity) but as a <hi>beaſtly, lustful, lawleſs fighter</hi> with his <hi>horns</hi> of <hi>Superiority,</hi> upon the high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of <hi>Arrogancy,</hi> an <hi>Oppreſſor</hi> of the <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Simple</hi> in his <hi>Innocency;</hi> and ſo warreth not only againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets purity,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt's ſanctity,</hi> but alſo againſt <hi>GOD Almighty</hi> his <hi>Creator's Divinity;</hi> and thus renders himſelf but as <hi>one</hi> in the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſm</hi> and curſed <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> a ſubject of the <hi>Vengeance</hi> of <hi>GOD's Juſt Judgments</hi> in the actual work of deſpairation, which ſhuts from the <hi>true hope</hi> of the leaſt <hi>drop</hi> of the Mercy of the <hi>LORD GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things I call <hi>Silver</hi> (ſeven times) <hi>refined, Drops</hi> of the Repreſentation of <hi>Righteous Reaſon,</hi> which in the <hi>ſubſtantial, practical,</hi> and living <hi>chanels,</hi> run down like <hi>ſtreams</hi> from the top of the <hi>Mountain</hi> of <hi>Sion,</hi> which ſtands in the <hi>midſt</hi> of the <hi>holy City</hi> of <hi>GOD;</hi> the which, if no man can confidently ſtand to oppoſe openly to my face, yet if any man will <hi>wilfully</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand in ſecret behind my back, let him
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:33625:73"/>
ſend me in <hi>writing</hi> the ſtrength of his <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition;</hi> and with further <hi>priviledge,</hi> I in the only <hi>ſtrength</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> may haply ſhew his <hi>confuſion,</hi> that ſo the work of <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> may proſper in the Land, the which is <hi>ſincerely deſired.</hi> But finally, if <hi>approved,</hi> and not <hi>oppoſed,</hi> then in <hi>Juſtice,</hi> without further <hi>ſuſpenſe,</hi> let them ſerve to the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of one of the enſuing Propoſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Either for my <hi>fair, open, cleer, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> and <hi>legal Tryal</hi> at <hi>Tribunal of Law,</hi> if any man hath juſtly to <hi>charge</hi> me as a <hi>Tranſgreſſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Or, if not a <hi>Trnſgreſſor,</hi> then to be righteouſly <hi>acquitted</hi> of theſe <hi>Bonds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, Conſider in <hi>ſoberneſs,</hi> O ye <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> of <hi>ROME,</hi> that if by any man's means I ſtand wrongfully <hi>repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented</hi> before you, as a <hi>tranſgreſſor;</hi> whether more than <hi>Two years Impriſonment,</hi> doth not equivolently <hi>anſwer</hi> ſuch a <hi>Law,</hi> as counteth not the <hi>repreſented Fact</hi> to be ſo <hi>criminal,</hi> as that it is worthy of the <hi>cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance</hi> of <hi>Judgment</hi> at the Bar of <hi>Tribunal:</hi> For my God weigheth all things in an equal ballance.</p>
            <p>Summarily, if the <hi>ſtrong will</hi> of cauſleſs irrational <hi>Revenge,</hi> hath not glutted her
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:33625:73"/>
appetite on me, I am ſtill the <hi>ſame,</hi> in the <hi>ſame Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Content</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience;</hi> as <hi>yeſterday,</hi> ſo alſo <hi>to day,</hi> even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>last day,</hi> until her <hi>greedy mouth</hi> hath ſucked my <hi>last blood</hi> and <hi>breath,</hi> and ſo this very <hi>Priſon</hi> to be made the <hi>Ax</hi> of <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of a <hi>Martyr</hi> of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> And know ye to the utmoſt, that I am of the Spirit of <hi>Stephen,</hi> and Life of the <hi>Lord,</hi> which pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and deſpited not.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>JOHN the lowly Lamb in the Life of JESUS the Son of GOD; To the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis City hath ill requited the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of my bowels of the <hi>Eternal Love</hi> (as well towards her Inhabitants) as they have been largely manifeſted to thy <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the time of their moſt grievous diſtreſs; Once, when about 120 perſons were <hi>impriſoned</hi> in the City of <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenny,</hi> to be ſent as <hi>Captives</hi> to the <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does,</hi> &amp; but one man more beſides me in all that Land, either <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Iriſh,</hi> that durſt to appear in their behalfs to plead their
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:33625:74"/>
cauſe for them; which the God of Heaven knows that I did (without an Earthly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) with the then Governor of that City; (who ſometime before that, ſent me up <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner</hi> to <hi>Dublin,</hi> proſecuting my Life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I had written about <hi>three ſheets of Paper,</hi> that repreſented the <hi>ſore Grievances</hi> and <hi>heavy Oppreſſions</hi> of all thy Children in that Land, which none of them inſtigated me unto, but was only carried forth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto in the <hi>Mercies, Pities</hi> and <hi>Compaſſions</hi> that God had put into my ſoul, beholding them a <hi>bleeding People</hi>) With the ſaid Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour I pleaded (for the ſaid perſons) firſt, in his <hi>private houſe,</hi> and next, with him, and all the Commiſſioners, in the <hi>open Court of Justice,</hi> and obtained a <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> for the <hi>delivery</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Priſoners,</hi> which I went perſonally to ſee <hi>executed;</hi> but the <hi>Marſhal,</hi> hoping to gain <hi>Moneys,</hi> diſobeyed it; which made me go a ſecond time to the <hi>Court,</hi> and open the <hi>Cauſe afreſh,</hi> whereby I obtained my <hi>Deſire</hi> as full as I could poſſibly expect; for with a <hi>ſecond Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> I returned to the <hi>Priſon</hi> (not giving truſt to any humane eye beſides my own) and ſaw them all delivered; at which time many fell down upon their knees to me in
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:33625:74"/>
the open ſtreet, worſhiping me as if I were a <hi>God,</hi> and not a <hi>man;</hi> which I then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, remembring the words of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of the <hi>Angel,</hi> that ſaid, thou ſhalt <hi>worſhip GOD,</hi> and <hi>Him only</hi> ſhalt thou worſhip.</p>
            <p>Beſides, other times I have appeared for ſome <hi>poor Widows,</hi> being formerly of <hi>eminency</hi> and <hi>repute</hi> in the World, and thy <hi>Children,</hi> and many other <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> in their diſtreſſes; and GOD Almighty knows that the Pitties of my ſoul were ſuch to them all, that I was ſo far from expecting a <hi>Gift</hi> for all that I did for them, that beſides my <hi>Expences</hi> in ſeveral <hi>Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> to ſerve their needs, my hand was <hi>open to all,</hi> and not one of thy Children can ſay that he came to my Door for <hi>an Alms,</hi> and went away <hi>empty-handed.</hi> Beſides all this, the GOD of Knowledge remembers that I have ſtript off the Apparrel imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly from my body to cloath thy <hi>Children</hi> that I ſaw in need and want.</p>
            <p>Therefore conſider thee this <hi>Caſe,</hi> as thou wilt appear to be a natural Father: And becauſe I have not found Mercy in this City anſwerable to the leaſt part of my Bowels to thy <hi>Children</hi> in their <hi>woful di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes;</hi> yet ſhew me Juſtice but <hi>to plead my
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:33625:75"/>
own Cauſe</hi> in a <hi>publick Court</hi> of <hi>Judicature,</hi> as I have <hi>openly</hi> pleaded the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of thy <hi>Children</hi> in a <hi>publick Court of Judicature</hi> in time of <hi>their miſery,</hi> when they could not plead it themſelves, nor durſt others do it for them, and it ſhal ſatisfie my ſoul; which <hi>ſpirituality,</hi> nay nor <hi>humanity</hi> it ſelf will deny me: the which I ſeek in the <hi>Spirit of meekneſs,</hi> as one that is delighted in the <hi>Order of Truth,</hi> loving and praying for <hi>Enemies,</hi> and watching to recompence <hi>good</hi> for <hi>evil,</hi> that the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Lamb</hi> in me may appear as a City ſet on a Hill.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Who am thy Priſoner in the Priſon of Madmen, called the</hi> Engliſh Quaker, <hi>JOHN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>And though ſomething was (a long while before) deſired, and earneſtly beſought by divers of the <hi>Pope's Prieſts</hi> and other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, for me to write unto the <hi>Pope,</hi> even in this wiſe, yet after I had ſent and heard of its <hi>delivery</hi> to the <hi>Pope</hi> at his Palace, the <hi>Anſwer</hi> which I received was, this, <hi>(viz.) That I ſhould have no hearing;</hi> and withal, I was ſtript of all my <hi>Writings</hi> which could be found, together with <hi>Pen, Ink</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:33625:75"/>
and threatned to have my Door <hi>walled up,</hi> and <hi>half,</hi> or <hi>more,</hi> of the Window alſo <hi>walled up;</hi> and ſcarcely <hi>Water</hi> to be brought unto me for my neceſſary uſe: Whereby the very worſt of men may diſcern that the ſpirit which ruleth in <hi>Rome</hi> is not of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A POST-SCRIPT to all the zealous <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> (which have ſought God in their Imaginations, but yet have not found him to poſſeſs him in the Subſtance) that they may all come to find and enjoy Him in his Everlaſting Life of Pleaſure.</head>
            <p>AFter all the former fruits of <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> ſhewn forth by <hi>Epiſtle, Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, Admonition, Reproof, Queſtions,</hi> and <hi>Righteous Reaſon,</hi> none of which being at any time <hi>anſwered</hi> by any <hi>perſon</hi> or <hi>perſons</hi> in <hi>ROME,</hi> or <hi>elſewhere,</hi> Now I am come to ſhew the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of all the <hi>Pope's Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> in that City; who when they ſaw that they could not <hi>anſwer</hi> the fore-going <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> (unleſs it ſhould be to their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation)
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:33625:76"/>
took occaſion to cenſure me under the Judgment of being in the ſtate of a <hi>Mad-man,</hi> thinking that the <hi>Cruelties</hi> which were determined in their Council, to be inflicted upon my <hi>Body,</hi> might prove to be the means of <hi>turning</hi> my <hi>ſoul</hi> from the work of <hi>GOD's Righteouſneſs</hi> effected in my <hi>heart;</hi> to which end I was ſent (as precited) from the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> unto the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of <hi>Mad-people;</hi> In which place I was <hi>firſt chained by the Neck to the wall,</hi> in which <hi>Chain</hi> I had the exact liberty of <hi>ſtanding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreight,</hi> of <hi>ſitting,</hi> or of <hi>lying down;</hi> but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>three nights</hi> had paſſed, it was ordered that the <hi>Chain</hi> was to be taken from off my <hi>Neck,</hi> and another <hi>Chain</hi> lock'd on my <hi>Leg,</hi> which was about <hi>ſix foot long,</hi> which gave me liberty to walk the length of <hi>three ſteps</hi> from the <hi>Wall</hi> whereunto it was <hi>faſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> which abode upon me for the full time of <hi>fourteen weeks;</hi> in which ſpace of time (it proving then to be Winter ſeaſon, and the Winter alſo proving very cold) ſhrank up the <hi>Sinews</hi> of my <hi>Leg</hi> on which the <hi>chain</hi> was lock'd, ſo that when (at the expiration of the aforeſaid <hi>fourteen weeks</hi>) it was taken off, I found my ſelf a <hi>lame man;</hi> but (through ſore ſuffering) in <hi>twelve dayes</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:33625:76"/>
the Lord (in whom I believed) made me again a <hi>ſound lim'd perſon;</hi> whoſe <hi>Name</hi> my ſoul <hi>magnifieth, praiſeth, bleſſeth,</hi> and <hi>thanketh</hi> for his <hi>goodneſs</hi> and <hi>loving-kindneſs,</hi> whoſe <hi>mercies</hi> endure for ever.</p>
            <p>Moreover, in the ſaid time of my being <hi>chained,</hi> I was divers times <hi>beaten, tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> and <hi>ſorely bruiſed</hi> and <hi>wounded</hi> in my <hi>body,</hi> by perſons appointed thereunto, uſing for the moſt part a <hi>dryed Bulls Pizzle</hi> as the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> for <hi>puniſhing</hi> of me, <hi>bruiſing</hi> and <hi>breaking my body</hi> with the <hi>ſame;</hi> yea, and after that I had the freedom of the <hi>Room</hi> in which I was kept (which I judge could not exceed in <hi>latitude</hi> 9, and <hi>longitude</hi> 14 feet) I was alſo ſeveral times <hi>beaten</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly <hi>wronged in my body,</hi> once <hi>eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi> my <hi>Torturers</hi> came into the Room, by whom I was <hi>ſtript of all my Cloathes</hi> from <hi>top</hi> to <hi>toe,</hi> and with the aforeſaid <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument fell upon me,</hi> and did in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>beat me</hi> with the ſame <hi>[as I was ſtark naked]</hi> that they left me from the very <hi>crown</hi> of the <hi>head</hi> unto the <hi>ſoals</hi> of my <hi>feet, <hi>black</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>bloody,</hi> having broken their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument</hi> about me. I might ſpeak and write that which would fill many <hi>Volumns</hi> of my Sufferings, both in <hi>body</hi> and <hi>ſpirit,</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:33625:77"/>
which are well known unto God, but in brief may ſum up all in a ſhort ſaying, not mentioning the many <hi>Particulars</hi> which were <hi>day</hi> after <hi>day,</hi> and <hi>night</hi> after <hi>night</hi> exerciſed upon me; as <hi>revilings, mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, infamous names, beatings</hi> by <hi>Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> with other <hi>abuſes,</hi> which in modeſty I cannot well expreſs by <hi>Pen,</hi> but may ſay thus, <hi>(viz.)</hi> even ſuch as paſſeth the bounds of all humanity, when I have been <hi>kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> at <hi>Prayer,</hi> and when I have been <hi>walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in <hi>Praiſes</hi> and <hi>Thanksgivings</hi> unto God. Ah! can I number, can I number again the <hi>many thouſands</hi> of <hi>Temptations</hi> that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended me, beſides <hi>blows, wounds, mocks</hi> and ſuch-like abuſes? <hi>tryed <hi>with Wine,</hi> proved <hi>with Women,</hi> tempted <hi>with Riches</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>all the Pleaſures that ever my heart could deſire;</hi> after that I was <hi>threatned</hi> even <hi>day</hi> after <hi>day,</hi> and <hi>night</hi> after <hi>night;</hi> ſometimes with <hi>Tortures,</hi> and ſometimes with <hi>Death;</hi> by <hi>Gallows,</hi> by <hi>Fire,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>ſubtilly</hi> by <hi>Poyſon;</hi> Well, what ſhall I ſay? I have read the Sufferings of <hi>Job,</hi> and the Slaughters of many of the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> but yet this can I ſay in God, that ſuch were my <hi>ſuffering-dayes</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> (as I have ſaid in body and ſpirit)
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:33625:77"/>
that no ſoul that lived immediatly in his Grace, ever ſuffered the like, even ſince the day of <hi>Adam's</hi> being a <hi>man</hi> created of his <hi>Maker</hi> from the <hi>beginning,</hi> [which I made manifeſtly <hi>appear</hi> unto my <hi>Afflictors, Torturers</hi> and <hi>Tormentors</hi> in <hi>ROME,</hi> even unto their <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>confuſion,</hi> whilſt in <hi>bonds</hi> I was ſo <hi>conſtrained</hi> unto <hi>ſufferings</hi> in the ſtate of my <hi>manifeſt</hi> and <hi>approved Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency</hi> in the <hi>ſight</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> and <hi>themſelves</hi> my <hi>utter Enemies.</hi> All which was <hi>inflicted</hi> upon me to turn my <hi>heart</hi> from the <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Way</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> which is manifeſt to you by their <hi>many Temptations</hi> (for me to ſpeak a <hi>Lye</hi>) and often <hi>Provocations</hi> to break me from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Content,</hi> which I held in my God.</p>
            <p>Now the aforeſaid <hi>Puniſhments</hi> &amp; <hi>Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> having been laid upon me for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited cauſes, which all the foregoing Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings (diſpenſed unto them forth of the <hi>Inquiſition</hi>) ſheweth, the <hi>unrighteouſneſs</hi> of their <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and the <hi>unreaſonableneſs</hi> of their <hi>Weapons,</hi> which fought and battelled againſt me; whom I ſhewed (in the time of my Sufferings) That if they judged me to be a <hi>Mad-man,</hi> they ſeemed to me to be nigh <hi>ſenſleſs,</hi> to ſeek me by Temptations of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:33625:78"/>
               <hi>Cruelties</hi> and <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> to turn unto them, by ſinning againſt the Lord of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>And again, I remonſtrated to their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, <hi>viz.</hi> That if the <hi>Pope, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, Doctors, Jeſuites, Prieſts, Fryars, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, Phyſicians,</hi> and all the <hi>wiſe Councils</hi> and <hi>Counſellors</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> were fallen ſo far from the <hi>knowledge of GOD,</hi> and degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated ſo much below <hi>humane Reaſon,</hi> as not to judge of a humane ſtate in a more ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſort, than to conclude me to be a <hi>Mad-man,</hi> that Soul was in a moſt miſerable deſtroying ſtate that ſhould truſt unto their Judgements concerning any thing which they ſhould judge was <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> tending to the Worſhip of <hi>GOD,</hi> and <hi>Salvation;</hi> For if all could not rightly judge of a Cauſe <hi>external,</hi> in ſo low a degree, it is impoſſible that they ſhould judge of things <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> which are matters of the higheſt concernments; and therefore muſt needs conclude my ſelf, a <hi>wilful deſtroyer of mine own Soul,</hi> if I ſhould have adhered unto ſuch ſpirits, as were not able rightly to judge, betwixt a ſtate of <hi>true ſence</hi> and <hi>madneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all which it is my deſire, that the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:33625:78"/>
               <hi>poor, ſimple, hungry</hi> and <hi>thirſty Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> (whoſe ſouls are not ſatisfied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the enjoyment of the true God) may know the <hi>real cauſe</hi> why they yet walk with <hi>heavy hearts</hi> and <hi>preſſed-down minds,</hi> not having the comfort of the aſſurance of <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> in them, though they have careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſought many years to find it, going un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many <hi>Maſſe-houſes,</hi> to <hi>communicate of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> and to <hi>pray frequently,</hi> and to <hi>confeſſe ſeveral times in the year,</hi> and to <hi>bear penance for their ſins willingly,</hi> and yet all hath been ſo ſhort of making their <hi>perfect Peace</hi> with God, that a thouſand times more than all whatever they practiſed, cannot take away from their <hi>hearts,</hi> nor waſh from their <hi>ſouls</hi> one of their <hi>leaſt ſins;</hi> I ſay, one cauſe is this, as the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Leaders of this People cauſe them to err, and they which are led of them are deſtroyed:</hi> And the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> whoſe lips ſhould <hi>keep Knowledge,</hi> have <hi>hid Knowledge from the eyes of the People;</hi> and therefore hath the Lord complained, ſaying, <hi>For want of Knowledge my People periſh;</hi> which your <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> have really hid from your eyes, having led you into the wayes of their own <hi>Inventions,</hi> which they ſought
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:33625:79"/>
and found out in the <hi>Counſels</hi> of their <hi>own Wills,</hi> whilſt the immediate Word of the LORD was not inſtantly in and among them, but abſolutely wanting from them, who therefore led you into thoſe things which the LORD GOD never requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from you; and therefore in your <hi>daily ſacrifices,</hi> you cannot expect another <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> from <hi>GOD</hi> than this, as the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> ſaith, <hi>Who hath required theſe things at your hands?</hi> For <hi>GOD</hi> never inſtituted <hi>Beads,</hi> nor <hi>Images</hi> of <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>Croſſes;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ever ſaid he, That the <hi>inviſible ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Worſhip</hi> of Him the <hi>Spiritual GOD,</hi> ſtands in the <hi>viſible</hi> and <hi>carnal appearances,</hi> which cannot reach unto the <hi>ſoul,</hi> to <hi>ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, waſh</hi> and <hi>cleanſe</hi> the ſoul from every <hi>evil</hi> and <hi>dead work, word</hi> and <hi>thought:</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as nothing but an <hi>inviſible</hi> and an <hi>eternal Subſtance</hi> is able to reach unto, to <hi>waſh, purge</hi> and <hi>cleanſe</hi> your <hi>inviſible</hi> and <hi>immortal ſouls</hi> from your ſins, which are the <hi>cauſes</hi> of your <hi>weights, preſſures</hi> and <hi>burdens</hi> which yet remain upon you, not knowing your Deliverance from them.</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore, that you have long <hi>practiſed</hi> to find, but have not <hi>partaked</hi> of the <hi>ſubstance</hi> of the thing deſired, having
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:33625:79"/>
               <hi>ſought</hi> eaſe, but not <hi>found</hi> eaſe, having <hi>ſought</hi> it, but in the way of your Leaders, who <hi>cauſe you to erre;</hi> and not having ſought it in any other way, but in that which (your ſouls have experience, through long pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice) brings you not unto the <hi>true End</hi> of your hope; not having ſought it as you ought to ſeek; <hi>trying all things, and holding faſt that which is good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come ye therefore, and try this <hi>Way of GOD,</hi> and <hi>prove</hi> the <hi>LORD</hi> in <hi>his Way,</hi> even the <hi>Merciful GOD,</hi> who hath <hi>proved you</hi> in your <hi>wayes,</hi> and alwayes found you <hi>defective</hi> in your wayes; and <hi>mark</hi> Him in <hi>his Way,</hi> and <hi>try</hi> and <hi>ſee</hi> if it ſhall be with you in the <hi>dayes to come,</hi> as it hath been with you in the <hi>dayes that are past;</hi> For now Reaſon may tell you, that if your way was <hi>imperfect,</hi> ſurely the Way of GOD muſt needs <hi>be perfect,</hi> which <hi>leads</hi> unto a <hi>perfect end;</hi> firſt, to a <hi>perfect Life in Him</hi> that is the <hi>Beginning,</hi> and conſequently unto <hi>perfect Peace</hi> in the <hi>ſame,</hi> who is <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out End.</hi> Can you do leſſe than to <hi>prove</hi> and <hi>ſee</hi> and <hi>ſeek</hi> in <hi>that,</hi> wherein I know aſſuredly you ſhall <hi>find,</hi> that you ſhall not always walk as in <hi>weariſomneſs</hi> &amp; <hi>faintneſs,</hi> nor be in your hearts as <hi>parched heaths,</hi> nor
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:33625:80"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:33625:80"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:33625:81"/>
in your minds as <hi>barren mountains,</hi> neither ſhall be as <hi>Bryars</hi> of the <hi>Woods,</hi> and <hi>Thorns</hi> of the <hi>Forreſts;</hi> nay, nor as <hi>pricking Thiſtles</hi> of the <hi>Stubble-fields;</hi> neither ſhall you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes walk as <hi>afflicted, toſſed</hi> and <hi>tormented</hi> through the ſwellings of the <hi>waves</hi> of <hi>temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> paſſing over your <hi>weary minds;</hi> you ſhal not always <hi>mourn</hi> like <hi>doves</hi> for a <hi>mate,</hi> nor <hi>grieve</hi> like <hi>Widows</hi> for the <hi>loſſe</hi> of their <hi>Beloveds;</hi> neither ſhall your dayes be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <hi>Tribulations,</hi> nor the continuance of your time as ſurpaſſing <hi>pangs</hi> of <hi>pains:</hi> But ſurely you ſhall draw into a <hi>good time,</hi> wherein <hi>Beauty</hi> ſhall be given into your ſouls <hi>for Aſhes,</hi> the <hi>Oyl of Joy</hi> for <hi>Mourning,</hi> and the <hi>Garments of Praiſe</hi> for the <hi>ſpirit of heavineſs;</hi> in which time the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the <hi>LORD</hi> your <hi>Maker</hi> ſhall be the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villion</hi> of you <hi>Peace,</hi> and you ſhall <hi>rest</hi> in his <hi>Joys for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well therefore, O ye <hi>tender Friends,</hi> (whom my ſoul is ſeeking in the Love of my <hi>Father,</hi> to be united unto Him in his <hi>Holineſs</hi>) Come and experience <hi>this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> and prove this <hi>new</hi> and <hi>living Way</hi> of the <hi>LORD</hi> (though not another than that which from the beginning was; but only new unto the old nature of all fleſh,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:33625:81"/>
which corrupteth its way in the ſight of the Lord God) which is the <hi>Way</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the holy <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and ſuffering <hi>Servants</hi> of <hi>JESUS lived</hi> and <hi>walked;</hi> and being but <hi>one,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, There is <hi>one Way, one Truth,</hi> and <hi>one Life,</hi> as ye believe and confeſs, there is but <hi>one <hi>True GOD:</hi>
               </hi> and therefore, as ye find in your way <hi>coruption abounding,</hi> ye have <hi>cauſe</hi> alſo to confeſs that the Way of God being but <hi>one,</hi> cannot be the Way in which you walk; Foraſmuch as GOD hath ſaid by the mouth of his holy Prophet, ſpeaking of the Meſſiah, <hi>I will give him for <hi>a Way,</hi> and for an <hi>high way,</hi> which the wayfaring-men, though fools, ſhall not erre therein;</hi> Who alſo ſpake by the ſame Prophet, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I will give Him for a <hi>Covenant</hi> to the People, for a <hi>Light</hi> to the Gentiles, that He may be my <hi>Salvation</hi> unto the ends of the Earth;</hi> of whom alſo in the fulneſs of the diſpenſation of time <hi>John the Baptist</hi> bore Witneſs, teſtifying Him to be the <hi>True LIGHT that lighteth all mankind coming into the World;</hi> as Chriſt himſelf ſaid, <hi>I am the LIGHT of the World; he thot believeth in me, ſhall not abide in Darkneſs, but ſhall have the Light of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:33625:82"/>This is the Way, even the <hi>true Way</hi> of the <hi>LORD GOD,</hi> which I deſire (through proof) your ſouls may experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; And to the end that you may have the <hi>true Witneſs <hi>within you</hi>
               </hi> of the Power of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> which leads into <hi>perfect Unity</hi> with the <hi>Perfect GOD,</hi> in the <hi>Innocent Life</hi> of the <hi>Lamb</hi> of <hi>GOD that taketh away the ſin of the World;</hi> I tenderly exhort, counſel and adviſe you, to turn your <hi>minds</hi> unto that <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Lamb</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> which ſhineth into all your <hi>Souls,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing you in all your <hi>Conſciences</hi> of <hi>all your ſins,</hi> and joyning your <hi>minds</hi> unto it in <hi>perfect Love</hi> of it, becauſe it is of the <hi>pure Nature</hi> of your <hi>pure Creator,</hi> you ſhal come in due time to find and ſee aſſuredly, that as that ſame <hi>Light</hi> which ſhineth in all your Conſciences, is of ſuch a <hi>powerful</hi> and <hi>virtuous Nature,</hi> as that it not onely ſearcheth your <hi>hearts,</hi> and tryeth your <hi>reins,</hi> and finds out your moſt <hi>ſecret ſins,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo convinceth you as well of the <hi>least,</hi> as of the <hi>greateſt</hi> of your <hi>ſins;</hi> ſo it will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe free, deliver, and eaſe you from the <hi>burden</hi> of your <hi>ſins,</hi> which is the cauſe of your <hi>diſſatisfaction</hi> and many <hi>ſorrows;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that as it is of GOD, <hi>pure, perfect,</hi>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:33625:82"/>
and altogether <hi>virtuous</hi> in its <hi>nature,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not change from its property, nature, and vertue; but as it <hi>convinceth</hi> of the <hi>leaſt ſin,</hi> being loved and lived in, muſt alſo <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver</hi> from the <hi>leaſt ſin;</hi> and being ſtill of the <hi>ſame vertue</hi> and <hi>nature of GOD,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing your ſouls of your <hi>greateſt ſins,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loved and lived in, muſt alſo <hi>free</hi> and <hi>deliver</hi> you from your <hi>greateſt ſins;</hi> and being found of ſo <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>powerful</hi> a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and vertue to <hi>free</hi> and <hi>deliver</hi> your <hi>ſouls</hi> from your <hi>leaſt</hi> and from your <hi>greateſt ſins,</hi> muſt alſo of neceſſity in the ſame love, <hi>deliver</hi> you from <hi>all your ſins:</hi> The which all muſt confeſs, excepting ſome in <hi>Atheiſm</hi> might ſay, That the perfect <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Alſufficient GOD</hi> is an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient Medicine</hi> to heal the ſoul <hi>perfectly</hi> of all its <hi>maladies</hi> and <hi>infirmities:</hi> But I am better perſwaded of all you that <hi>deſire</hi> the <hi>true Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>living God,</hi> having a <hi>ſenſible Underſtanding</hi> in you, that there is ſuch a <hi>Light</hi> ſhining <hi>into your ſouls,</hi> that ſheweth you <hi>all your ſins,</hi> the which ye may remember you have had from your <hi>Childhood;</hi> becauſe you cannot otherwiſe ſay, but that from your <hi>Childhood</hi> it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed you of all your ſins in the <hi>ſecrets</hi>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:33625:83"/>
of your <hi>Conſciences,</hi> which no one elſe could accuſe you of; but yet ye were not then directed unto it as you are now coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled, and therefore could not know the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>virtue,</hi> becauſe you never proved its <hi>force, ſtrength</hi> and <hi>virtue,</hi> through a perfect love, <hi>yeelding,</hi> in obedience unto its <hi>motions</hi> and often <hi>checks</hi> of your minds; Wherefore, this is the <hi>happy day</hi> of your <hi>Viſitation,</hi> wherein it is told you, that if you <hi>love</hi> that <hi>LIGHT,</hi> which ſhews you the nature of all Temptation unto Evil, and <hi>joyn</hi> unto the LIGHT, ſo as to be <hi>guided</hi> by the LIGHT, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>all Evil,</hi> it will deliver you from the <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>Tempter</hi> which preſents the <hi>Temptation,</hi> by <hi>ſaving</hi> you from the Evil: which <hi>Light</hi> you will then know in the inviſible power of the holy God, which is given you for the <hi>perfecting</hi> of his <hi>Praiſe</hi> in your <hi>hearts,</hi> through the <hi>forming</hi> and <hi>new-creating</hi> your hearts into the mind of his own <hi>Righteous Spirit;</hi> which thing you cannot know but through the <hi>experience</hi> and <hi>tryal,</hi> which in the <hi>tryal</hi> I am ſure (as God is <hi>holy,</hi> and that meaſure of Light in your <hi>Conſciences</hi> is of GOD, which is <hi>holy, vertuous</hi> and <hi>powerful</hi>) will <hi>purifie</hi>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:33625:83"/>
you from <hi>ſin,</hi> and <hi>perfectly ſave</hi> and <hi>deliver</hi> you from <hi>all evil;</hi> And therefore I muſt needs conclude, that he is moſt <hi>extreamly ſinful</hi> and <hi>desperatly evil,</hi> that ſaith, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth to be delivered from <hi>all ſin</hi> and <hi>evil,</hi> which will not try to <hi>experience</hi> ſuch a <hi>power</hi> and <hi>virtue</hi> of the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> given into his ſoul, which is able to <hi>ſave</hi> and <hi>deliver</hi> him from <hi>all evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be ye therefore wiſe (O People) unto your <hi>own Salvation;</hi> having had experience of the <hi>vanity</hi> of your own <hi>way,</hi> and <hi>wayes;</hi> try ye now the <hi>Righteous Way of GOD</hi> in which you <hi>cannot tranſgreſs,</hi> and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in your wayes you have not found <hi>rest</hi> to your <hi>deſirous</hi> and <hi>thirſty ſouls,</hi> which of all things would chooſe rather to be cloathed with the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving GOD;</hi> and, after <hi>tryal</hi> by <hi>pure obedience</hi> (in <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>undefiled</hi> love) if ye find not <hi>deliverance</hi> from <hi>your ſins,</hi> which is the <hi>cauſe</hi> of your <hi>preſſures</hi> and <hi>burdens,</hi> and afterwards the <hi>peace</hi> of your <hi>poor ſouls,</hi> and <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> of your <hi>ſimple tender minds,</hi> even in <hi>fulneſs</hi> of <hi>Content</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> in the <hi>Pleaſures</hi> of <hi>Immortal Life,</hi> which is the <hi>end</hi> of all your <hi>Deſires, Requeſts,</hi> and <hi>earneſt ſeekings.</hi> Then may ye alſo ſay, we have
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:33625:84" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſought in the <hi>way of Light,</hi> but our <hi>Creator</hi> cannot be found <hi>there:</hi> But truly, this is my <hi>Testimony</hi> of my <hi>heavenly Father,</hi> unto whom there is none like, in Goodneſs, Mercy and Deliverance, That if any one <hi>ſeeketh</hi> Him <hi>in his Way of Holineſs</hi> (in which ſin cannot be committed) he will ſatisfie the <hi>deſires</hi> of that <hi>ſoul</hi> in <hi>due time,</hi> and <hi>overspread</hi> it with his <hi>abundant Fulneſs;</hi> And therefore to that of <hi>GOD in your ſelves</hi> I cannot but commend you, which is more ſafe for you to mind, obey and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, than the invented <hi>cuſtoms, wayes</hi> and <hi>ſtatutes</hi> ordained of <hi>men,</hi> which never came to live in that <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> (which was the <hi>Light</hi> in all their <hi>Conſciences</hi>) which could have led them out of all their ſins, into the <hi>true knowledge</hi> of the <hi>waſhing by the Blood of CHRIST,</hi> which <hi>cleanſeth</hi> from <hi>all ſin;</hi> which being taken away, puts an end to the <hi>ſuppoſed Purgatory;</hi> for, if any thing purgeth from ſin, it is the <hi>Everlaſting Blood of the Lamb of GOD</hi> (which was ſlain ſince the foundations of the World was) which <hi>waſheth away all ſin;</hi> And this alſo puts an end to the vain thoughts of the <hi>Popes remiſſion of ſins,</hi> which ſtands in oppoſition to his <hi>profeſſed Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:33625:84" rendition="simple:additions"/>
after this life: for, if he forgives <hi>all ſins,</hi> excepting <hi>one ſin,</hi> how is it that <hi>after</hi> his <hi>forgiveneſs</hi> generally all ſouls of his Sect muſt enter into <hi>Purgatory</hi> to be <hi>clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> from <hi>that</hi> which he hath <hi>formerly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given them?</hi> ſo that you may ſee either his profeſſion of forgiveneſs is <hi>deceit</hi> and <hi>vanity,</hi> or elſe that his <hi>profeſſed Purgatory</hi> is a <hi>deceit</hi> and <hi>vanity;</hi> becauſe to the one work of <hi>forgiveneſs</hi> and <hi>cleanſing from ſin,</hi> there is not a need of any but one thing to <hi>effect it;</hi> and becauſe I <hi>know</hi> that the <hi>Blood of CHRIST,</hi> and <hi>only</hi> the <hi>Blood of CHRIST</hi> (which is his powerful Life) doth it, I am <hi>aſſured</hi> in the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>holy GOD,</hi> and therefore do <hi>aſſert it,</hi> That both the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Purgatory,</hi> which ſtand croſſing one the others <hi>virtue</hi> and <hi>authority,</hi> are both but a <hi>deceit</hi> and <hi>witchery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This therefore may awaken you from all <hi>ſlumber</hi> of ſuppoſed <hi>ſecurity</hi> concerning your way, and induce to take heed unto the <hi>LIGHT</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> in your ſelves, that it may lead you out of your own <hi>thoughts, words,</hi> and <hi>wayes,</hi> to walk with God in <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> all your dayes; that of Him you may be made Partakers of his <hi>Endleſſe Everlasting Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Life, Peace</hi> and <hi>Joy,</hi> which
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:33625:85"/>
will ſwallow you up in his <hi>high Praiſes,</hi> who is worthy of the Glory of his Works in the whole Earth, even for <hi>ever</hi> and <hi>ever, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <head>A <hi>Concluding Word</hi> to thoſe that falſly accuſe me, and my Brethren of being Papiſts.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>FInally,</hi> Whereas there are divers that have accuſed <hi>me</hi> and my <hi>Brethren,</hi> as being perſons which in the bottom of our hearts are <hi>Papiſts,</hi> This may plainly ſerve as a Teſtimony very ſubſtantial, that we are ſo judged upon none other than a wrong and falſe account, as hath been demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by <hi>Doctrine, Life, Example,</hi> and <hi>large Suffering,</hi> among ſuch <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and in ſuch <hi>places</hi> as are counted the moſt <hi>reputed Papiſts</hi> upon the face of the Earth: Which is more than ever <hi>Luther, Calvin,</hi> or any <hi>Proteſtant</hi>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:33625:85"/>
or other Sect, teſtified or witneſſed, <hi>viz.</hi> againſt the perſons in the ſame place; yea, than any would be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to do amongſt all the Sects in <hi>England,</hi> that cry againſt <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Popery</hi> here at home in their own Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, or upon <hi>ſoft Cuſhions</hi> on <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits:</hi> yea, I can ſay, that I have found many that have falſly accuſed me of <hi>Popery,</hi> that would not for a King's Ranſom go to <hi>Rome,</hi> and cry againſt it, as I have done; and therefore their own <hi>Conſciences</hi> may rather accuſe themſelves of <hi>Deceipt,</hi> or at leaſt-wiſe, as <hi>Backbiters,</hi> whilſt they ſpeak that againſt the <hi>Pope</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> which they would not ſpeak to the <hi>Pope himſelf</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> (as I ſought to clear my Conſcience to the <hi>Pope's</hi> face) and therefore are but like the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that backbite and ſpeak evil of <hi>Engliſh Sects,</hi> in the Countries where their own is tolerated and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of, which is but of one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:33625:86"/>
nature in them all of all Parties. From all which the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of my Accuſers do turn upon their own heads, as an undeniable Covering of ſhame; who henceforth in prudence may rather chooſe the keeping of <hi>ſilence,</hi> than utterance of <hi>ſlanders,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Yet after all the precited Paſſages, I do hereby intimate a few of the <hi>Papiſts Principles,</hi> which I (together with the reſt of the People of God, called <hi>Quakers</hi>) do utterly deny, as not being of GOD'S holy Spirit of Truth, but conſequently of the ſpirit which produced all their other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented Traditions, which ſuite not with the holy Nature of the holy Eternal GOD.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>We deny the</hi> Pope <hi>and his</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals <hi>to be of the Election of GOD,</hi> Angels, <hi>or</hi> Saints; <hi>and therefore in their Places and Offices not of GOD, nor the Truth; but contrary to God, and the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:33625:86"/>2. <hi>We deny the ſuppoſed place of</hi> Purgatory, <hi>which the</hi> Papiſts <hi>profeſſe to be after death; we owning no</hi> Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory <hi>for the Soul after the Body is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>We utterly deny</hi> all Images <hi>which the</hi> Papiſts <hi>worſhip and bow down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>We deny the</hi> Maſſe, <hi>both</hi> matter <hi>and</hi> manner <hi>thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>We deny</hi> Prayers <hi>to be made unto</hi> Saints <hi>or</hi> Angels (<hi>which the</hi> Papiſts <hi>uſe) ſeeing Chriſt ſaith,</hi> Ye ſhall hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ask nothing of me, but of the Father in my Name.</p>
            <p>Many other things I could inſert, but at preſent forbear. But where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, laſtly, that I have denyed the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boveſaid five Particulars to be any thing of Truth, it lyes upon the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> to prove them according to the Spirit of Truth, if they are able, and not according to their own, nor their
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:33625:87"/>
father's inventions; elſe all men may ſee that they live in Deceit, Errour, and Falſhood, of which let all men take heed, leſt they ſhould be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deſtroyed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Perrot.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33625:87"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33625:88"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
